i'm sure most people watching this are
aware of the former kgb
agent turned cia informant yuri besmanov
in the 1980s besmanoff went around the
usa
speaking mostly to conservative groups
about how the usa had been infiltrated
with communist
agents sent from moscow when many people
started to pay attention to what was
going on in politics on youtube
a few years back many of his interviews
and lectures went viral
and for a lot of people this was one of
their first steps to having their eyes
opened he describes a four-stage process
of demoralization
destabilization crisis and normalization
a deliberate soviet attempt at
infiltration and subversion
now many aspects of this story are true
but i'm afraid that there are some
detailed old yuri
left out and besides you've got to ask
yourself
how is it that you've heard of this guy
how is it that millions of people have
watched
yuri besmanov videos here on youtube why
is it as i pointed out a couple of
months ago
that yuri has been mainstreamed well i'm
going to answer some of those questions
shortly but first let's take a quick
break
if you like academic agents content on
this channel sign up for a course on the
academic agency
he's now offering foundations of
economics
click the link in the show description
and level up your econ knowledge
okay so what's wrong with the story yui
besmanoff tells
i will explain but before i do so let me
note that in this video i'm going to be
using very mainstream
sources by which i mean left-wing
journals and wikipedia
entries in order to show that there is
no aspect of
what i'm telling you that could be
described as conspiracy theory
this is all completely open information
freely available to anyone with access
to google okay with that noted the
problem with
yuri's narrative is that the ultimate
source of the demoralization
program he describes was not moscow
but frankfurt and specifically the
frankfurt school
which i am sure you have heard of it
included a group of radical thinkers
including theodore adorno
max horkheimer eric fromm and herbert
marcouza
the institute for social research at
goethe university in frankfurt
was set up in 1923 by the marxist
carl grumberg it was bankrolled by the
son of a german millionaire
grain merchant importantly though
this was an alternative branch of
marxism
which was against the soviet project
and sought to analyze its problems which
is to say that it was entirely
independent
of moscow max horkheimer took over as
director
of the institute in 1930 and then
recruited adorno
from and later marcus among others
after the rise of hitler in 1933
horkheimer moved the institute from
frankfurt to geneva
eric fromm went on a trip to the united
states around this time
where he persuaded columbia university
based in new york
to grant the institute for social
research refuge
while germany was under nazi rule and so
the frankfurt school
new home from 1935 was new york city
while there the frankfurt school devoted
much thought to what had gone wrong in
germany
from their perspective and located the
problem
in both the german mindset which is to
say the psychology of the german people
and in german culture which is to say
the cultural modes which perpetuate
this psychology anti-semitism
for example was diagnosed as a pathology
a symptom
of the authoritarian personality type
hawkheimer
made a number of strategic alliances in
new york
most importantly he allied the frankfurt
school
with the american jewish committee a
non-profit
jewish advocacy group which is
headquartered in new york
which had some but not total influence
in washington
the frankfurt school proposed some very
radical solutions to the problem of
fascism in europe
as early as 1941 horkheimer had drawn up
plans for nothing less than the total
re-education of the german people
the aims of which were quote the mental
transformation
of the german human being culture and
society
towards democracy morality which
respects human dignity
and the world in 1942
herbert marcuser started working
directly for the office of strategic
services which was the predecessor
organization of the cia
now i should be clear here this is not
to suggest that the frankfurt school
or marcusa were directly in charge of
running u.s government policy
or anything like it a country like the
usa is big
and complex the government is not a
monolith
it has different networks and different
nodes of power
for example for almost the entirety of
his time working for the government
marcusa was under surveillance by the
fbi
and the suspicion of being a communist
infiltrator
and in fact this dynamic of these
frankfurt school
thinkers operating in the u.s government
at the same time
that the red scare was going on is a
source of much confusion
but all of this should be made much
clearer in your own mind
if you see the frankfurt school thinkers
as the new left
entirely independent of and even against
moscow and the soviet union who are the
old left
as marcusa and others such as franz
newman and otto kirkheimer
joined the office of strategic services
in washington dc
horkheimer and adorno relocated to
california
hawkheimer had been appointed as
director of the scientific division
of the american jewish committee and it
was in this capacity he started his
five studies in prejudice and the
aforementioned research
into the authoritarian personality type
when
the second world war ended the allied
powers embarked on a program called
denazification a vast propaganda effort
essentially to convert the german
population from supporting nazism
to supporting liberal democracy in the
case of
west germany and to supporting socialism
or communism
in the case of east germany the
administration
for this program was divided into four
zones
one under the americans one under the
british
one under the soviets and one under the
french
this is significant because we can see
side by side
how the de-nazification effort as
directed by washington
and moscow respectively were applied
note
that hawkheimer's plan to completely
re-educate and remold the german mindset
from the ground
up or i should say from the top down was
here
effectively adopted as the official
policy
of the us federal government in order to
achieve their aims general eisenhower
set up the institute on re-education
of the axis countries stating only an
inflexible long-term
occupation authority will be able to
lead the germans to a fundamental
revision
of their recent political philosophy
this was under the auspices of the
psychological warfare division
of the supreme headquarters allied
expeditionary force
now if the phrase psychological warfare
sounds familiar to you
perhaps it is because our old friend
yuri besmanov
uses it to describe the four-stage
process of demoralization and subversion
now in practice the americans faced two
quite separate problems here
the first was the very practical problem
that if they arrested
anyone who would work for the nazi party
or the german government in any capacity
at all
it would result in having to process
over 35 million people
the second was the more intangible issue
of the
everyday thoughts and beliefs of the
german people the logistical nightmare
of the first problem
led the us army to declare that most
german people had simply been
brainwashed by nazi propaganda
so efforts were intensified on the
second problem
the us army seized 37 german newspapers
six radio stations 314 theaters
642 cinemas 101 magazines
237 book publishers and 7
384 book dealers and printers over 30
000 books were banned all copies of
these books were confiscated and
destroyed
the representative of the military
directorate admitted that
the order was in principle no different
from the nazi
book burnings remember always accuse
your enemy
of that which you are guilty yourself
now although
in the short term only high-ranking
nazis were individually
punished and most germans were not
under the logic that they had been
brainwashed
in the longer term the official policy
of the american
denacification program was to get
germans to accept
collective responsibility for what had
happened
including posters which showed
atrocities and said things like
this is your fault and these atrocities
your fault and this is chiefly where the
frankfurt schools work on fascism being
some sort of
inborn psychological trait of the german
mindset
started to take root as official policy
in fascism the career of a concept
paul gottfried chronicles how the
definition of fascism
or the authoritarian personality type
expanded
far beyond the specific atrocities of
the nazis
and came to be seen as something endemic
in german culture
and history as a whole even going so far
as to implicate
christianity itself sydney bernstein
the chief of the psychological warfare
division in 1946
said the aim of this program was to
shake and humiliate the germans and
prove to them
beyond any possible challenge that these
german crimes against humanity
were committed and that the german
people and not just the nazis and the ss
bore responsibility in fact america
forced germany
through all four stages of the
process that yuri besmonoff describes
and
by the 1970s had been largely successful
certainly if you look at germany today
you can see just how successful
they were i think it's notable that most
of the
support for the afd for example which is
the far-right group
one so-called far-right group in germany
is in east germany
not in west germany in contrast the
soviets in their denuncification efforts
did
practically none of this they were much
more brutal
and much less sophisticated in their
methods simply sending
former nazis to the gulag and their
propaganda efforts
were focused much more squarely on
getting germans to accept socialism
and remove anti-socialist sentiment
rather than to renounce
their entire history and culture
and accept responsibility collectively
for nazi atrocities
you can see how different the approach
was from the american
effort just from these few details now
at the top level
successive american governments came to
lose interest
in the denunciation program as they
became
more embroiled in the cold war in 1949
horkheimer and adorno returned to
frankfurt and reestablished the
institute of social research around this
time
the us formally handed over control of
the process to the germans who
would now be responsible for their own
re-education
now it strikes me that since this time
since
1949 1950 the institutions
and processes that were set up in the
direct aftermath
of world war ii continued largely
unchecked
the definition of fascism didn't stop
with the german people
or with german culture over time it
expanded to include
european culture as a whole british
culture
and indeed american culture no one
person
needed to be in charge of this it worked
almost
by itself as frankfurt school
type thought came to dominate western
universities
in the 1960s and onwards not
as the result of infiltration from
moscow
but as a form of continuation from
systems
institutions and programs that have been
set up by the frankfurt
school and their allies in the 1940s
if the original sin of the germans was
to be the holocaust
each other country would find its own
original sin
in britain it was the empire and
colonialism
in america it was slavery and racism now
in 2020
all of these things have coalesced into
one unifying concept called
whiteness and for the re-education
program finally to be completed
of course the symbols of these things
must be destroyed or else the new
mindset cannot
take root in other words the
denotification program
never ended it only expanded itself to
include
more and more things under the
definition of fascism
that's why antifa see themselves as
fighting
fascism so now you know what yuri
didn't tell you if you like academic
agents content on this channel
sign up for a course on the academic
agency he's now offering foundations
of economics click the link in the show
description
and level up your econ knowledge
be sure to like this video and subscribe
and if you really like my content maybe
consider joining the channel or
donating or maybe even buy a mug i am
grateful for all of your support
now get out