our conversation is with mr. Yuri
Alexandrovich desmond othe ii when i
started working for the Soviet embassy
in India I to my horror I discovered
that we are millions times more
oppressive than any colonial or
imperialist power in the history of
mankind that my country brings to India
not freedom progress and friendship
between the nations but racism
exploitation and slavery and and of
course economical inefficiency to this
country since I fell in love with India
I I developed something which by KGB
standards is extremely dangerous thing
it's called split loyalty when an agent
likes a country of assignment more than
his own country I literally fell in love
with this beautiful country a country of
great contrasts but also great humility
great tolerance and if philosophical and
intellectual freedoms my ancestors used
to live in caves and eat raw meat when
India was highly civilized nation 6000
years ago so obviously the choice was
not to the advantage of my own nation I
decided to defect and to entirely
dissociate myself from the brutal regime
see first of all because defecting in
India is virtually impossible thanks to
very strong pressure from the Soviet
government excuse me you were in India
on assignment and yes I was working for
the Soviet embassy in New Delhi as a
press officer and defecting for a Soviet
diplomat is next to impossible it's a
suicide as I said because a great friend
Indira Gandhi pushed a law through
Parliament which says and I quote no
defector from any country has a right of
political asylum in any embassy on the
territory of Indian Republic which is a
masterpiece of hypocrisy no other
defector but the Soviet one needs a
political asylum so knowing that
perfectly well I I planned a craziest
possible way to defect
I started counterculture
in India there are there were thousands
of young American boys and girls with no
shoes long hair smoking hash and
marijuana studying sometimes Indian
philosophy sometimes simply pretending
that they study and they greatly annoyed
Indian police and they were
laughingstock of Indians because
obviously they they were
good-for-nothing students I started
carefully where they congregate what
roots they travel what language they
speak what do they smoke and one day I
simply joined a group of hippies to
avoid detection of Indian police I was
dressed as a typical hippie with blue
jeans long kameez shirts with all kind
of nice decorations like beads long
hairs I bought a wig because for several
weeks I had to turn myself from a
conservative Soviet diplomat into a very
progressive American hippie
my first assignment was to India as a
translator with the Soviet economical
aid group building refinery complexes in
the heart state and which are at state
at the time I was still naively
idealistically believing that what I was
doing contributes to the understanding
and cooperation between the nations it
took me quite a number of years to
realize that what we were bringing to
India was a new type of colonialism
thousand times more oppressive and
exploitative than any colonialism or
imperialism in history of mankind but at
that time I was still hoping that well
maybe it's not that bad could be worse
and things may go for better and I even
tried to implement the beautiful Marxist
smarter proletarians of all the
countries unite I tried to unite with a
nice indian girl and I was actually I
was fascinated by Indian culture by by
the family life in in this country my
first assignment in India I was promoted
to the position of a public relations
officer you can see me here translating
a speech by a Soviet boss and you're on
the right I am on the right here yes and
it was the occasion was commissioning of
the refinery complex in Bihar Baroni
another area of activity when I was
working for the novice tea was to
accompany groups of so-called
progressive intellectuals writers
journalists publishers teachers
professors of colleges you can see me
here in Kremlin I'm second on the left
with a group of Pakistani and Indian
intellectuals most of them pretend that
they don't understand that we are
actually working on behalf of the Soviet
government and the KGB they pretended
that they are actually being guests a
VIP intellectuals that they are treated
according to their merits and and their
intellectual abilities for us they were
just a bunch of political prostitutes to
be taken advantage for various
propaganda of
Asians therefore you can see perfectly
well they senior colleague of mine on
the left doesn't really have that much
respect on his face and myself with a
very skeptical smile typical KGB
sarcastic smile anticipating another
victim of ideological brainwashing this
is how a typical conference in novice
tea headquarters in Moscow look likes
sitting in the middle is boris butakov
the then director of norms depress
agency high-ranking party bureaucrat in
the department of propaganda I am
standing next to a famous Indian poet
Sumitra and on punt he was famous
because he was an author he was the
author of the famous poem titled
Rhapsody to Lenin that's why he was
invited to USSR and everything was paid
by the Soviet government the pay special
attention to number of bottles on the
table this is one of the ways to kill
the awareness or curiosity of the
foreign journalists my one of my
functions was to keep foreign guests
permanently intoxicated the moment they
land at Moscow Airport I had to take
them to the VIP launch and toast to
friendship and understanding within the
nations of the world glass of vodka then
the second glass of vodka and in no time
my guests would be feeling very happy
they would see everything in kind of
pink nice color and that's the way I I
had to keep them permanently for the
next 15 or 20 days at certain point in
time I had to withdraw alcohol from them
so that some of them were the most
recruitable would feel a little bit
shaky guilty trying to remember what
they were talking last night that's the
time to approach them with all kind of
nonsense such as joint communique or
statement for for Soviet propaganda
that's the time they aren't the most
flexible and of course what they didn't
understand they didn't realize or
pretended not to realize that myself who
was drinking together with them
was not drinking at all I had ways to
get rid of alcohol through various
techniques including special peels which
were given to me by my colleagues but
they were taking it seriously in other
words they they they would consume quite
large volumes of alcohol and feel quite
uneasy next morning this is the first
stage of befriending a professor you can
see myself on the left with the same
James Bond smile on my on the right is
my KGB supervisor comrade Leonid metro
Keon and in the middle a professor of
political science in Delhi University
the next stage would be to invite him to
a gathering of in the Soviet Friendship
Society there he is sitting next to his
wife before he is being sent to USSR for
free trip everything is paid by the
Soviet government he was made to believe
that he is invited to USSR because he is
a talented sober thinking intellectual
absolutely false he is invited because
he is a useful idiot because he would
agree and subscribe to most of the
Soviet propaganda cliche and when he is
coming back to his own country he is
going for years and years to teach the
beauties of Soviet socialism to newer
and newer generations of his students
thus promoting the Soviet propaganda
line part of the building of USSR
embassy and my supervisors on the left
is comrade McGee an Indian communist and
on the right
comrade Metro him my supervisors in the
secret department of research and Contra
propaganda it has nothing to do with
either research or country propaganda
most of the activity of the department
was to compile huge ammount volume of
information on individuals who were
instrumental in creating public opinion
publishers editors journalists actors
educationalists professors of political
science members of parliament
representatives of business circles most
of these people were divided roughly
into groups those who would toe the
Soviet foreign policy they would be
promoted to the positions of power
through media and
the opinion manipulation those who
refuse the Soviet influence in their own
country would be character assassinated
or executed physically come revolution
under the guidance of the Soviet embassy
in Hanoi and same thing I was doing in
New Delhi to my horror I discovered that
in the files where people were doomed to
execution there were names of pro-soviet
journalists with whom I was personally
friendly pressure of him yes they were
idealistically minded leftists who made
several visits to USSR and yet the KGB
decided that come revolution or drastic
changes in political structure of India
they will have to go wise not because
they know too much simply because you
see the useful idiots the the leftists
who are idealistic aliy believing in the
beauty of soviet socialist or communist
or whatever system when they get
disillusioned they become the worst
enemies that's why my KGB instructors
specifically made the point never bother
with leftists forget about these
political prostitutes aim higher this
was my instruction try to get into into
large circulation established
conservative media reach filthy rich
movie makers intellectuals so-called
academic circles cynical egocentric
people who can look into your eyes with
angelic expression and tell you a lie
this are the most recruitable people
people who lack moral principles who are
either too greedy or to suffer from
self-importance
they feel that they they matter a lot
these are the people who KGB wanted very
much to recruit but to eliminate the
others to execute the others don't they
serve some purpose wouldn't they be not
one they realize they serve purpose only
at the stage of destabilization of a
nation for example your leftists in
United States all these professors and
all this beautiful civil rights
defenders they are instrumental in the
process of the of the subversion only to
disturb you lies the nation
when their job is completed they are
known they are not needed anymore they
know too much some of them when they get
disillusioned when they see that Marxist
Leninist come to power obviously they
get offended they think that they will
come to power that will never happen of
course they will be lined up against the
wall and shot but they may turn into the
most bitter enemies of Marxist Leninist
when most of the Indians who were
cooperating with the Soviets especially
without the Department of Information of
the USSR embassy were listed for
execution and when I discovered that
fact of course I was sick I was mentally
and physically sick I thought the time
I'm going to explode one day during the
briefing at the ambassador's office I
would stand up and say something that we
are basically a bunch of murderers
that's what we are we yeah there's
nothing to do with friendship and
understanding between the nation and
blah blah blah we're murderers we behave
as a bunch of thugs in the country which
which is hospitable to us a country
which which with ancient traditions but
I I did not the fact I tried to get the
message across to my horror
nobody wanted even to listen least of
all to believe what I had to say and I
tried all kinds of tricks I would I
would I would leak information through
letters or lost documents or something
like that and still I got no message the
message was not published even in the
conservative mass media of India the
immediate impulse to defect was
Bangladesh crisis which was described by
American correspondence as Islamic
grassroot Revolution which is absolute
baloney there was nothing to do with
Islam and there was no grassroot
revolution actually there are no
grassroot revolutions period any
revolution is a byproduct of a highly
organized group of conscientious and
professional and organizers but there's
nothing to do with grassroot in
Bangladesh it was nothing
with grassroots most of the Awami League
party members of a mulignans People's
Party were trained in Moscow in the hi
party school most of the Mukti fauj
leaders Mukti forages in Bengali means
People's Army same as SWAPO and and all
kind of Liberation Army's all over the
world the same bunch of useful idiots
they were trained at Lumumba University
and various centres of the KGB in
Simferopol in in Crimea and in Tashkent
so when I saw that India Indian
territory is being used as a jumping
board to destroy East Pakistan
I saw myself thousands of so-called
students traveling through India to East
Pakistan through the territory of India
and Indian government pretended not to
see what was going on they knew
perfectly well the Indian pollutin knew
it the intelligence Department of Indian
government knew it the KGB of course
knew it and the CIA knew it that that
was most infuriating because when I
defected and I explained to the CIA
debriefers they should watch out because
East Pakistan is going to erupt any
moment they said I was look I was
reading to too many James Bond novels
anyway so East Pakistan was doomed
one of my colleagues in in the Soviet
consulate in Calcutta when he was dead
drunk he ventured into the basement to
relieve himself and he found the big
boxes which said printed matter to Dhaka
University
Dhaka is the capital of East Pakistan
and since he was drunk and curious he
opened one of the boxes and he
discovered not printed metric he
discovered Kalashnikov guns and
ammunition in there anyway it's a long
story when I saw the preparations for
the for the invasion into East Pakistan
obviously I wanted to defect immediately
the only thing I couldn't I couldn't at
that time make up my mind when and where
and how one of the reasons of course you
see I was in love with the India I
mentioned it before I spoke the
languages I socialized with people and I
understood that I had to act fast unless
I want this beautiful country to be
permanently and irreparably damaged by
our presence
[Music]