my father was
he is on the left here my father was
officer of the general staff of the
soviet army
he was inspector of land forces soviet
troops stationed in countries like
mongolia cuba
east european countries this is the
picture taken at the entrance of my
institute of oriental languages it's a
part of moscow state university
as every soviet student i was quote
unquote volunteering
for harvesting grain in kazakhstan
by the end of my training in school i
was recruited by the kgb
this picture was taken on that day and
you can see again how happy
it feels to be recruited by the kgb
pay special attention to number of
bottles on the table one of my functions
was to keep foreign guests
permanently intoxicated the moment they
land at moscow airport
in 1967 the kgb attached me to this
magazine look magazine a group of 12
people
arrived to ussr from united states to
cover
the 50th anniversary of october
socialist revolution in my country
from the first page to the last page it
was a package of lies
[Music]
our conversation is with mr yuri
alexandrovich besmianov
mr besvanov was born in 1939
in a suburb of moscow he was the son of
a high-ranking soviet army officer
he was educated in the elite schools
inside the soviet union and became an
expert in
indian culture and indian languages
he had an outstanding career with
novastie which was the
pr and still is i should say the press
arm or the press agency of the soviet
union it turns out that this is also a
front
for the kgb one of his interesting
assignments was to brainwash
foreign diplomats when they visited
moscow and
he'll tell us a little bit about how
they did this and how they planted
information which eventually wound up in
the press of the free world
he escaped to the west in 1970 after
becoming totally disgusted with the
soviet system
and he did this at great risk to his
life
he certainly is one of the world's
outstanding experts on the subject of
soviet propaganda
and disinformation and active measures
mr besmianov i'd like to begin by having
you tell us a little bit about some of
your childhood memories
well the most vivid memory of my
childhood was second world war
or to be more precise the end of the
second world war when all of a sudden
united states from a friendly uh
nation which helped us to defeat
nazism turned overnight into a deadly
enemy
and it was very shocking because all
newspapers
were trying to present an image of
belligerent aggressive american
imperialism
most of the things that we were taught
is that united states
is aggressive power which is just about
to invade our beautiful
free socialist country uh that american
cia
is dropping colorado beetles on our
beautiful potato fields
to eliminate our crops and each
schoolboy had a
picture of colorado bug on the on the
back page of his
notebook and we were instructed to go
into collective fields
to search for those little colorado bugs
of course we couldn't find any
neither we could find many potatoes and
that was explained again by the
encroachments
of the decadent imperialist power
the anti-american paranoia hysteria in
in the soviet propaganda was to such an
a
of such a higher degree that many
less skeptical people or less stubborn
would really believe that united states
is just about to invade our beautiful
motherland
and some secretly hope that it will come
true
that's interesting yes well getting back
to
life inside the soviet union or inside
communist countries in general in this
country
at the university level primarily we
read and hear
that uh the soviet system is different
from ours but not that different
and that there is a convergence
developing between
all of the systems of the world and that
really doesn't make an awful lot of
difference what system you live under
because
you have corruption and dishonesty and
tyranny and
all that sort of thing from your
personal experience what is the
difference between life under communism
and life in the united states
well life is obviously very much
different for simple reason that
the soviet union is a state
capitalist economically it's a state
capitalism
where an individual has absolutely no
rights no value his life is nothing it's
just like an insect
he is disposable whereby in the united
states even the
even the worst criminal is treated as a
human being
he has a fair trial and some of them
capitalize on their crimes they they
publish their memoirs in their prisons
and get handsomely paid by your crazy
publishers
the differences of course in the daily
life
are very various depending on who
whom we are talking about in my own
private life i never suffered from
communism simply because i was brought
up in the family
of high ranking military officer
most of the doors were open for me most
of my expenses were paid by the
government
and i never had any troubles in with the
authorities or
with the police so in other words i i
would say i
i enjoyed or i had good reasons to enjoy
all the advantages of so-called
socialists
system my main
motivations to defect was had nothing to
do with affluence
it was mainly moral indignation moral
protest
rebellion against the inhuman methods of
of the soviet system
well specifically what did you object to
i objected first of all
against oppression of my own dissidents
and intellectuals and that was the most
disgusting thing that that i witnessed
as a
as a young man young student who was
brought up
a very troublesome period in our history
from stalin to khrushchev
from total tyranny and oppression to
some kind of liberalization second
when i started working for the soviet
embassy in india
i to my horror i discovered that we are
millions times more oppressive than any
colonial or
imperialist power in the history of
mankind
that my country brings to india not
freedom
progress and friendship between the
nations
but racism exploitation
and slavery and and of course economical
inefficiency to this country
since i fell in love with india i i
developed something which by kgb
standards is extremely dangerous thing
it's called split loyalty when an agent
likes a country
of assignment more than his own country
i literally fell in love with this
beautiful country
a country of great contrasts but also
great humility great tolerance and and
if philosophical and intellectual
freedoms my ancestors used to live in
caves and eat raw meat when
india was highly civilized nation six
thousand years ago
so obviously the choice was not to the
advantage of my own nation
i decided to defect and to entirely
dissociate myself from that brutal
regime
mr besmianov we've read a lot about the
concentration camps and the slave labor
camps under the stalin regime
now the general impression in america is
that those things are part of the past
are they still going on today or what is
the status yes
there is no qualitative change in in the
soviet concentration camp system
there are changes in in numbers of
prisoners
again this is uh unreliable soviet
statistics
we don't know how many political
prisoners are there in the soviet
concentration camps
but we sure know from from various
sources
that at each particular time there are
close to
25 to 30 million of soviet citizens who
are virtually kept as slaves in forced
labor
camp system the size of the population
of
country like canada is serving terms
as prisoners incredible so
um i would say that
those intellectuals who try to convince
american public that concentration camp
system is
a thing of a past are either
conscientiously misleading public
opinion
or they are not in very intellectual
people they
they're selectively blind they don't
they lack
um intellectual honesty when they say
that
well we've spoken about the
intellectuals in this country and also
the intellectuals
in the soviet union what about down
at the broad mass level do the
people in general the worker and the
working people the workers in general
and the soviet union do they support the
system do they tolerate it
what is their attitude well average
soviet citizen if there is such an
animal of course
does not like the system because it
hurts
it kills he may not understand the
the reasons he may not have enough
information
or or educational background to
understand
but i doubt very much there are many
people who are conscientiously
supporting the soviet system that are
not such
such people in ussr even those who have
all the reasons to enjoy socialism
people like myself
were a member of journalistic elite uh
they
they also hate system for for different
reasons though not because they lack
material affluence
but because they are unfree to think
they're in constant fear
duplicity split personality and this is
the greatest tragedy for my nation
well what do you think are the chances
of the people actually
overcoming their system or replacing it
there is a great possibility that system
will sooner or later
be destroyed from within that is a
self-destructive mechanism
built in into any socialist or communist
or fascist system
because there is lack of feedback
because the system does not
rely upon loyalty of population
but until and until this soviet junta is
being supported
by the western so-called imperialists
that is
multinational companies establishments
governments and let's face it
intellectuals so-called academia in the
united states is famous for supporting
the soviet system
as long as the soviet junta will keep on
receiving credits
money technology grain deals and
political recognition
from all these traitors of democracy or
freedom
uh there is no hope there is not much
hope for
for changes in my country
and the system will not collapse by
itself
simply because it's being nourished by
so-called american imperialism this is
the greatest
paradox in history of mankind when a
capitalist world supports
and actively nourishes its own destruct
destroyer destructor
i think you're trying to tell us
something oh yes
i'm trying to tell you that it has to be
stopped unless you want to end up in
in gulag system and enjoy all the
advantages of socialist
equality uh working for free
catching fleas on your body sleeping on
on the
planks of plywood in in alaska this time
i guess
that's where americans will belong
unless they will wake up of course and
force their government to stop aiding
soviet fascism
well you told us a moment ago why you
left the system
i'd like to hear the details of how you
did it it must have been a very
dangerous thing
it was not so dangerous it was crazy
first of all because defecting in india
is virtually
impossible thanks to very strong
pressure from the soviet government
excuse me you were in india on
assignment yes i was working for the
soviet embassy in new delhi
as a press officer and
uh defecting for a soviet diplomat
is next to impossible it's a suicide as
i said because
a great friend indira gandhi
pushed a law through parliament which
says and i quote
no defector from any country has a right
of political asylum
in any embassy on the territory of
indian republic
which is a masterpiece of hypocrisy no
other defector but the soviet one
needs a political asylum so knowing that
perfectly well
i i i planned a craziest
possible way to defect i studied counter
culture in
india there are there were thousands of
young american boys and girls with no
shoes long hair
smoking hush and marijuana studying
sometimes
indian philosophy sometimes simply
pretending that they study
and they greatly annoyed indian police
and they were laughing stock of indians
because obviously they were good for
nothing students
i studied carefully where they
congregate what routes they travel what
language they speak what do they smoke
and one day i simply joined a group of
hippies
to avoid detection of indian police
i was dressed as a typical hippie with
blue jeans
long cummies shirts with all kind of
nice
decorations like beads long hairs
uh i i bought a wig because for several
weeks i had to turn myself from a
conservative soviet diplomat
into a very progressive american hippie
and that was the only way that that i
could
uh avoid detection
it was very interesting experience
but it was necessary because um from my
own knowledge
as a member of soviet embassy staff
i knew that there were many cases when
soviet defectors were betrayed by
indian police and also some western
embassies played a very dirty
role in betraying the soviet defectors
according to our information
they were some i wouldn't call them
double agents but simply
a moral people working for this
for the united states embassy and uh
confining in in people like this would
be a suicide
so i had to be extremely careful i could
not trust anyone
uh and that was the that was the reason
for such a crazy way to defect well had
you been
caught in the act of trying to get out
what would have happened to you
oh most likely i would i end up in in
concentration camp
or depending on the situation and
on the on the whim of some bureaucrat
and kgb
uh maybe even executed that this is
normal practice
quietly of course not publicly
but that would be the end of my
defection of course well
when did you finally make it to the
united states uh
in 1970 after about
six months of debriefing in athens by
the cia
and i presume fbi too they let me go
first to germany then to canada that was
my decision i had to change my identity
to protect my family
and my friends in ussr
and also i was little bit paranoid
uh knowing that both soviet kgb
and probably some double agents within
american system may be after me
so i wanted to settle down as far away
as possible
i requested cia to give me some kind of
new identity and just let me go
on my own and i settled in canada i was
a student
i changed many professions from
farm help and and laundry truck driver
to instruct language instructor and
broadcaster for canadian broadcasting
corporations in montreal have you had
any threats on your life or any uh
yeah uh in about five years kgb
eventually discovered that i'm working
for canadian broadcasting
uh see i made a very big mistake i
started talk i started working for
overseas service of cbc which is similar
to
voice of america in russian language and
of course
monitoring service in ussr picked up
every new
voice uh every new announcer would
they they would make it a point to
discover who he is and in five years
sure enough slowly but surely they
discovered that i am
not thomas schuman that i am yuri
aleksandrovich bismianov and the time
working for canadian broadcasting
and undermining beautiful the town
between canada and ussr
and the soviet ambassador alexander
yakovlev
made it his personal effort to discredit
me he complained to pierre trudeau who
is known to be
a little bit soft on socialism and
the management of cbc behaved in a very
strange cowardly way unbecoming to
representatives of a
independent country like canada
they listened to every suggestion that
soviet ambassador gave
and they started shameful investigation
analyzing content of my broadcasts to
ussr
sure enough they discovered that some of
my statements were probably
to would be
offending to the soviet politburo
so i had to to leave my my job and of
course subtle intimidations they would
say something like please cross the
street carefully because you know
traffic is very heavy in quebec and
fortunately i know about the psychology
and
the logic of activity of the kgb and i
never allowed myself to be intimidated
this is the worst thing this is what
they expect a person a defector to be
intimidated once they spot that that you
are scared
they keep on developing that line and
then
uh eventually you either have to give up
entirely and and work for them
or you they neutralize you they they
would
definitely stop all kind of political
activity
which they failed to do in my case
because i was stubbornly
working for the canadian broadcasting
and
in response to their intimidations i
said that look this is a free country
and
i am as free as you are and i also can
drive very fast
and gun control is not yet established
in canada so i had a couple of good
shotguns
in my basement so welcome to visit me
someday
with your kalashnikov's machine guns so
obviously it didn't work intimidation
didn't work
so they they tried different approach
as i described they approached on the
highest level
on the level of canadian bureaucracy
and that level they were on that level
they were successful on
individual level they failed flat
mr besmianov has brought a series of
slides with him that he has taken
from the soviet union and i think this
is a good time to
take a look at the slides now the
viewers will be able to see these slides
as we talk about them yes this is a
collection of slides which are
some of them are snapshots from my
family album some of them are documents
which i smuggled from the soviet embassy
and some are reproductions from local
mass media i usually show them
to establish my credibility as a de
facto this is a picture of my
native town metish about 20 miles not
from moscow
characteristically there's a statue of
comrade lenin in the central square
this is myself at the age of seven again
characteristically on the statue of
comrade stalin
extending his friendly hand to peoples
of the world
at that age of course uh i was still
idealistically minded young communist
and um i still believe that sooner or
later things will go for better
but i realized that the system stinks
that something is fishy
and that ideology is is fake
and the uh propaganda about that
advanced soviet agriculture simply
didn't meet the criteria of reality
if they talk about uh abundance of food
and there's none
in the stores there must be something
wrong
my father was he is on the left here my
father was
officer of the general staff of the
soviet army he was inspector of land
forces
soviet troops stationed in countries
like mongolia cuba
east european countries were here alive
today
most likely he would be inspecting
soviet troops in in nicaragua angola
and many other parts of the world
fortunately he died
and he didn't see the disgrace because
deep inside he was
a russian patriot he didn't he didn't
like the idea of expanding soviet
military might
especially in the areas where we were
not welcomed at all
unlike many other military officers he
was reporting directly to the minister
of defense
bypassing kgb and diplomatic service in
other words he was a trusted
military professional and my impression
that this type of people
are much less hawkish and adventuristic
than party bureaucrats
in kremlin when american mass media
describes soviet military as potentially
dangerous counterpart for
for pentagon i simply laugh because i
know better
i know that the most dangerous part of
the soviet power structures
are not military at all most likely if
they come to power in my country there
will be more sensible
negotiators for nuclear disarmament and
withdrawal of the soviet troops from
many parts of the world but if someone
from the
party structure or the kgb structure
were to give the orders
for military they have to obey as far as
their their professional military
but they you see the triangle of power
and hate in ussr is the party at the top
the party elite the oligarchy of the
party then the military and the kgb at
the bottom
they hate each other and the the most
hated
triangle the most hated corner of the
triangle is the communist party
bureaucrats
they are the most adventuristic senile
megalomaniacs
they can start war i wouldn't be
surprised not the military
they know what war is yes at least my
father did
this is the picture taken at the at the
entrance of my
institute of oriental languages it's a
part of moscow state university
i graduated in 1963
and i just excuse me which one were you
on i i'm on the right you're on the
right and on the left is my
uh call my schoolmate vadim smirnov who
later was a
aparachid in the central committee of
the soviet
union communist party what is an
apparatchik it's it's a
it's a function it's something like
civil service in british empire
some someone who is never fired from
from the service he stays there
internally
he may not be promoted to high but he's
a dependable
bureaucrat who will stay forever
i started not only languages but also
history literature
even music i'm on this picture i'm
trying to learn
how to play musical in indian musical
instrument
i haven't tried to look like an indian
when i was second year students not bad
right
uh yes and actually it was strongly
encouraged by the
by the instructors in my school because
these the graduates of my school were
later on employed as
diplomats foreign journalists or spies
as every soviet student i was quote
unquote volunteering for
harvesting grain in kazakhstan this is a
biggest agricultural blunder of the
soviet government
but i didn't have much choice of course
because the communist motto borrowed
from the bible says those who do not
work
shall not eat and you can see me eating
therefore i was working and you can see
how happy i was about it
i went through a very extensive physical
and military training
including the manure including the
military games in
areas suburban areas of moscow
and here for example we are on the tour
in arkhangelsk area
and by the end of my training in school
i was recruited by the kgb this picture
was taken on that day and you can see
again how happy
it feels to be recruited by the kgb
our conversation with yuri alexandrovich
besmianov
who is a defector from the soviet union
a former propaganda agent
for navasti and the kgb will continue
after this message
[Music]
all right as every student in ussr i
i went through very extensive physical
and military training
and civil defense training too unlike in
united states
where civil defense is virtually
non-existent
zero in ussr every student
whatever is major subject has to go
through very extensive four-year
military and civil defense training
you can see me here with the group of
students during one of the war games in
near moscow the
main idea of course is to prepare a
huge reserve army of of the ussr
each student has to to graduate as a
junior lieutenant
in my case it was administrative and
military
intelligence service my first assignment
was to
india as a translator with the soviet
economical aid group
building refinery complexes in bihar
state and gujarat state
at that time i was still naively
idealistically believing that what i was
doing contributes to the
understanding and cooperation between
the nations
uh it took me quite a number of years to
realize that what we were bringing to
india was
a new type of colonialism thousand times
more oppressive and
exploitative than any colonialism or
imperialism in history of mankind
but at that time i was still hoping that
well maybe it's not that bad could be
worse and things may go for better
and i even tried to implement the
beautiful marxist motor proletarians of
all the countries unite
i tried to unite with the nice indian
girl
and i was actually i was fascinated by
indian culture by
by the family life in in this country
but obviously communist party had
different plans for my genes
so i had to marry this beautiful russian
girl
in the span of my career i married three
times
most of these marriages were marriages
of convenience
on advice from the department of
personnel this is normal practice in
ussr when a soviet citizen
is assigned to a foreign job he has to
be married
either to keep family in ussr as
hostages or
if it's a convenience marriage like mine
uh so that the husband and wife are
virtually informers on
each other to prevent defection or
contamination by decadent imperialist or
capitalist ideas
in my case i hated that girl so much
that the moment i landed in moscow we
we were divorced and i i married
later second time by the end of my first
assignment
in india i was promoted to the position
of
public relation officer you can see me
here translating
a speech by a soviet boss and you're on
the right i'm on the right here
yes and it was the occasion was
commissioning of the refinery complex in
bihar
barrani uh back in moscow
i was immediately recruited by novice
press agency which is a propaganda and
ideological subversion front for the kgb
75 percent of the members of the novosti
are
commissioned officers of the kgb the
other 25
are like myself co-opted agents who are
assigned to specific operations in this
particular case you can see me talking
to
students of lumumba friendship
university in moscow
um this is the you know a huge school
under the direct control of the kgb and
central community
where future leaders of the so-called
national liberation movements are being
educated
and selected carefully and some of them
have absolutely
neither this for example is a group of
students from lumumba they don't look
like students at all they look more like
military and that's exactly what they
were
they were dispatched back to their
countries to be leaders of the
so-called national liberation movements
or to be translated into normal human
language
leaders of international terrorist
groups
another uh area of activity
when i was working for the nova sc was
to accompany groups of so-called
progressive intellectuals
writers journalists publishers
teachers professors of of colleges
you can see me here in kremlin i'm
second on the left
with a group of pakistani and indian
intellectuals
most of them pretended they don't
understand that
we are actually working on behalf of the
soviet government and the kgb
they pretended that they are actually
being guests
a vip intellectuals that they are
treated according to their merits and
and their intellectual abilities for us
they were just
a bunch of political prostitutes to be
taken advantage for various propaganda
operations therefore you can see
perfectly well
the senior colleague of mine on the left
doesn't really have that much respect on
his face
and myself with a very skeptical smile
typical kgb sarcastic smile anticipating
another victim of of ideological
brainwashing
this is how at a typical uh
conference in novosti headquarters in
moscow look likes
the sitting in the middle is boris
burkhoff the then
director of navy press agency high
ranking party bureaucrat
in the department of propaganda i am
standing next to a
famous indian poet sumitra nandan pant
he was famous because he was an author
he was the author of the famous
poem titled rhapsody to lenin that's why
he was invited to ussr
and everything was paid by the soviet
government
the pay special attention to number of
bottles on the table this is one of the
ways to kill the awareness or
curiosity of foreign journalists
my one of my functions was to keep
foreign guests
permanently intoxicated the moment they
land at moscow airport
i had to take them to the vip launch and
toast to friendship and understanding
between the nations of the world
glass of vodka then the second glass of
vodka and in no time my guests would be
feeling very happy
they would see everything in kind of
pink nice color
and that's the way i i had to keep them
permanently for the next 15 or 20 days
at certain point in time i had to
withdraw alcohol from them
so that some of them who are the most
recruitable would feel a little bit
shaky
guilty trying to remember what they were
talking last night
that's the time to approach them with
all kind of nonsense such as
joint communicate or statement for for
soviet propaganda
that's the time they are the most
flexible
and of course what they didn't
understand they didn't realize or
pretended not to realize that
myself who was drinking together with
them was not drinking at all
i had ways to get rid of alcohol through
various techniques including
special pills which were given to me by
my colleagues
but they were taking it seriously in
other words they they would consume
quite a
large volumes of alcohol and feel quite
uneasy next morning
in 1967 the kgb attached me to this
magazine look magazine a group of 12
people
arrived to ussr from united states to
cover
the 50th anniversary of october
socialist revolution in my country
from the first page to the last page it
was a package of lies
propaganda cliche which were presented
to american
readers as opinions and deductions of
american journalists
nothing could be far from truth this
were not
opinions they were not opinions at all
they were
the cliches which the soviet propaganda
wants
american public to think that they think
that if it does make any sense at all
it sure does because from the viewpoint
of the soviet propaganda although there
are some subtle criticism of the soviet
system
the basic message is that russia today
is a nice functioning
efficient system supported by majority
of population
that's the biggest lie and of course
american intellectuals and journalists
from look magazine
elaborated on that untruth in various
different ways they intellectualized
that lie
they found all kinds of justifications
for telling lies to american public
this is excuse me it was partly your job
to make sure that they got these ideas
and accepted them as their own ideas
right actually
even before they arrived to ussr and
they paid astronomical sum of money for
that visit
uh they were submitted this novice press
agency developed so-called backgrounders
20 25 pages of information and opinions
which were presented to the journalists
even before they bought their tickets to
moscow they had to analyze this
situation and judging on their reaction
to that background
the local novice representative or local
soviet
diplomat in washington dc would assess
whether they
have whether they be given visa to ussr
or not but they were selected oh yes
they were they were pre-selected
very carefully and there is not much
chance for honest journalists to arrive
to ussr
and to stay there for one year and to
bring this
package of lies back home this for
example
is a center fold of the tie of the look
magazine
they presented this monument erected by
communist party in stalingrad
as the symbol personification of russian
military might
and they said in the article which is
published
on the side that soviets are very proud
of the victory in the second world war
this is another big myth a lie no
sensible people would be proud to lose
20 millions of their countrymen
in the war which was started by genocide
hitler
and comrade stalin and paid by american
multinationals
most of the soviet citizens look at this
type of monuments with disgust
and sorrow because every family lost
father brother
sister or child in the second world war
yet american journalists who were trying
to
appease to please their hosts presented
this picture on the center fold
as the symbol and personification of
soviet national
they call it russian national spirit
and it was greatest greatest
misconception
and a very tragic misunderstanding
of course look magazine was not
distributed in ussr
the main audience was in the united
states
but i presume that many americans
millions of americans who were reading
look magazine at that time
had absolutely wrong idea about the
sentiments of my nation about what the
soviets are proud of and what they hate
this is a group you see the same lady
with this ward
in stalingrad this is the group of
journalists myself is in the center with
the same devilish smile
and mr philip harrington is on the
extreme left
there with with his camera this is the
gentleman
which was so deaf
or so uninterested in what i had to say
to him
this is the same picture a blow up of
the same the same picture
many many guests from various countries
in this particular case from asia and
africa were taken by me
as a novice to press agency employee
for a tour across siberia for example we
would show them
typical kindergarten you see nothing
special by american standards
just nice children sitting eating their
breakfast or or lunch
what they could not understand or they
pretended not to understand that this is
an exemplary kindergarten this is not
the kindergarten for average person or
average family in ussr
and we maintain that illusion in their
minds
you can see myself under the red spot in
the middle there with the same
business-like expression i'm on you know
i'm doing my job that that's what i'm
assigned to do and that's what i was
paid to do
but deep inside i still hope that at
least some of these
useful idiots would understand that what
they are looking at has nothing to do
with the level of affluence
in my nation this is a better picture
which reflects the true spirit of
of the soviet uh soviet childhood
this picture was printed in a canadian
government publication
by mistake in the middle you can see
children playing on a
small courtyard and the caption goes
this is a typical kindergarten in
siberia
what these idiots didn't understand that
it is not kindergarten at
all it is a prison for children of
political prisoners
but there was not a single mentioning
that what they were visiting
actually was an area of concentration
camps
and the job of people like myself to
help them
to not to notice that they are actually
talking to prisoners
most of the children were dressed
especially on the occasion of the
foreigners visit
the of course there were no corpses in
on the ground
there were no machine gun guards and the
well it looks not very pleasant as you
see it looks dull but obviously it does
not create an impression that this
is actually a prison well did any of the
journalists have the
uh curiosity to ask about uh prisons and
that kind of thing they were in siberia
this is what you
saw yes some of them asked questions and
naturally we would give them the
for the stupid question we give them
stupid answer no there are no prisons in
siberia no
most of the people who you see are free
citizens of ussr they are very happy to
be here
and they are contributing to the glory
of the socialist system
uh some of them pretended that they they
believe what what i was
telling them and um most of them
we may discuss it later what are the
motivations of these people
why would they stubbornly bring lies to
their own population
through their own mass media i have
various answers to this there is not a
single explanation
it's a complex of explanations it's fear
pure biological fear they understand
that they are on the territory of an
enemy state a police state and just to
save their rotten skins
and their miserable jobs their affluence
back home
they would prefer to tell a lie then to
to ask
truthful questions and and report
truthful information
second most of these schmucks were
afraid to lose their jobs because
obviously if you tell truth about my
country you will not last long as a
correspondent of new york times
or los angeles times they will fire you
what kind of correspondent are you you
obviously cannot find common language
with russians
if they kick you out in 24 hours so
just by by trying to be conformist to
their own editorial bosses
they tried not to offend the sentiments
of the soviet administrators and people
like myself
deep inside i hope they would insult my
uh or offend my sentiments obviously
they preferred not to
another reason uh i did i refuse to
believe it but
obviously there is another reason
obviously
it's agreed these people earn a lot of
money
when they come back to usa they claim
that they are experts in my country
they write books which sells in million
copies titled like russians the truth
about russia
most of it is lie about russia yet they
claim to be sovietologists
they they break they play back myth
about my country
the propaganda cliches yet they are
stubbornly resist
the word of truth if a person like
solzhenitsyn is either defecting or
kicked out of ussr
they try all their best to dis to
discredit him and to discourage him
i don't have much chance to appear on
national network
uh with the true story about my country
but a useful edit like hendrick smith or
robert kaiser
they are big heroes they come back from
ussr they say oh we were talking to
dissidents in russia
big deal soviet distances are chasing
american correspondents
in the streets and they are cowardly
escaping from these contacts
for some strange reason if you want to
know more about spain
you refer to spanish writers if you want
to learn more about french
you read french or writers
even about antarctica i bet you would
read penguins
only about the soviet union for some
strange reason
you read hendricks and schmendricks and
all kind of kissingers
because they claim that they know more
about my country they know
nothing or next to nothing or they
pretend that they know
more than they actually do i would say
they are dishonest
people who lack integrity and
common sense and intellectual honesty
they bring back
all kind of stories like that a
kindergarten in siberia
a meeting the most important fact it's a
prison
for children of political prisoners
another greatest example of monumental
idiocy
of american politicians edward kennedy
was in moscow
and he thought that he is a popular
charismatic
american politician who is easy going
who can smile
dance at the wedding in in russian
palace of marriages
what he does what he did not understand
or maybe he pretended not to understand
that actually he was being taken
for a ride this is a staged bedding
especially to impress
foreign media or or useful idiots like
ed kennedy
most of the of the guests there they had
security clearance
and they were instructed what to say to
foreigners
this is exactly what i was doing you can
see me in the same damn
bedding palace in moscow where ed
kennedy was dancing here
you see smiling he thinks he is very
smart
from the viewpoint of russian citizens
who observe this idiocy
he is he's narrow-minded
egocentrical idiot who tries to earn his
own popularity through the
uh through participation in propaganda
forces like this
here you can see myself on the right
again
exemplary soviet bride on the left three
journalists from various countries asia
africa and latin america
obviously they enjoying the situation
they they will go back home and write
the reports we were present and
on the regular soviet wedding they were
not present on the regular soviet
they were present they were part of a
farce of a circus performance
another thing which i had to
sometimes risking my life to explain to
foreigners
time magazine for example is very
critical of
south african racist regime
the whole article was dedicated to the
shameful internal passport system where
black
blacks are not allowing to live with
whites
for some strange reason for the last 14
years since my defection nobody wanted
to pay attention to my passport
this is my passport it also shows my
nationality
and it it has a police rubber stamp
which is called prapiska
in russian language which assigns me to
a certain
area of residence i cannot leave that
area
same way as this black man cannot leave
the area
in south africa yet we call south
african government racist regime
not a single jane jane schmonder or
fonda is
brave enough courageous enough to come
to media and say
look this is what happens in ussr i send
a copy of my passport to many
american liberals and civil rights uh
defenders
and all the other useful idiots they
never they never bothered to answer me
back
this shows what kind of integrity what
kind of honesty these people are
they're a bunch of hypocrites because
they don't want to recognize
a good example of racism in my country
this is the first stage of befriending a
professor you can see myself on the left
with the same james bond
smile on my on the right is my kgb
supervisor congratulations
and in the middle a professor of
political science in delhi university
the next stage would be to invite him to
a gathering of in the soviet friendship
society there he is sitting next to his
wife
before he is being sent to ussr for free
trip
everything is paid by the soviet
government he was made to believe that
he is invited to ussr because he is a
talented
sober thinking intellectual
absolutely false he is invited because
he is a useful idiot
because he would agree and subscribe to
most of the soviet propaganda cliche
and when he is coming back to his own
country he is going for years and years
to teach the beauties of soviet
socialism to
newer and newer generations of his
students thus promoting the soviet
propaganda line
the kgb was even curious about
this gentleman it may look innocent
maharishi mahesh yogi
a great spiritual leader or maybe a
great charlatan and crook
depending on which from which side you
are looking at him
beetles were trained at his ashram in
hardware in
india how to meditate mia faro and and
other
uh useful idiots from hollywood visited
his
uh school and they returned back to
united states absolutely zonked out of
their minds with marijuana
hashish and crazy ideas of meditation
to meditate in other words to isolate
oneself
from the current social and political
issues of your own country
to get into your own bubble to forget
about troubles of the world
obviously kgb was very fascinated with
such a beautiful school
such a brainwashing center for stupid
americans
i was dispatched by the kgb to check
what kind of vip
americans attend this school that's you
on the left yes i'm on the left
i i i was trying to get enrolled in that
school unfortunately
maharishi mahashiyogi asked too much he
wanted 500 american dollars for
enrollment
but my function was not actually to get
enrolled in the school my function was
to discover
what kind of people from united states
attend
this school and we discovered that yes
there are some
influential members of family
public opinion makers of united states
who come back with the crazy stories
about indian philosophy
indians themselves look up upon them as
idiots
useful idiots to say nothing about kgb
who looked at them as as
as extremely naive misguided people
obviously a vip say a wife of
of a congressman or or a prominent
hollywood personality
after the after being trained in that
school is much more
instrumental in the hands of of
manipulators of public opinion
and kgb than a normal person who who
understands who who looks through this
this this this type of
fake religious training why would they
be more susceptible to manipulation
i just mentioned that because you see a
a person
who is too much involved in in
in introspective meditation you see if
you carefully look what what maharishi
mahashiyogi is teaching to
to americans is that all most of the
problems
most of the burning issues of today can
be solved simply by meditating
don't don't don't rock the boat don't
get involved
just sit down look at your navel and
meditate and the things
due to some strange logic due to cosmic
vibration will will
will settle down by themselves this is
exactly what the kgb and marxist
leninist propaganda wants from americans
to destruct their opinion uh attention
and
mental energy from real issues of united
states
into a non-issues into a non-world
non-existent
harmony obviously it's more beneficial
for the soviet aggressors
to have a bunch of duped americans than
americans who are self-conscious
healthy physically fit and alert
to the reality maharishi mahesh yogi
obviously is not on the payroll of the
kgb
but whether he knows it or not he
contributes greatly to demoralization of
american society
and he is not the only one there are
hundreds of those gurus
who come to you to your country to
capitalize on naivete
and stupidity of americans it's a
fashion
it's a fashion to meditate it's a
fashion not to be involved
so obviously you can see that if if kgb
were
that curious if they paid my trip to
hardware if they assigned me to that to
that strange
job obviously they were very much
fascinated
they were convinced that that type of of
brainwashing is very efficient
and instrumental in demoralization of
united states
our conversation with yuri alexandrovich
besmienov
who is a defector from the soviet union
a former propaganda agent
for navasti and the kgb will continue
after this message
[Music]
this picture shows the part of the
building of ussr
embassy and my supervisors on the left
is comrade mehdi
an indian communist and on the right
komrad mit rohin
my supervisors in the secret department
of research and country propaganda
it has nothing to do with either
research or country propaganda
most of the activity of the department
was to compile huge
amount volume of information on
individuals who were instrumental in
creating public opinion
publishers editors journalists
actors educationalists professors of
political science
members of parliament uh representatives
of business circles
most of these people were divided
roughly into groups
those who would tow the soviet foreign
policy they would be promoted to the
positions of power
through media and public opinion
manipulation those who refused the
soviet influence in their own country
would be character assassinated or
executed physically come revolution
same way as in the small town of huwa in
south vietnam
several thousands of vietnamese were
executed in one night
when the city was captured by viet cong
for only two days
an american cia could never figure out
how could possibly communists
know each individual where he leaves
where where to get him
and would be arrested in one night
basically
in some four hours before dawn put on a
van
taken out of the city limits and shot
the answer is very simple
long before communists occupied the city
there was extensive network of
informers local vietnamese citizens
who knew absolutely everything about
people who are instrumental in public
opinion
including barbers and taxi drivers
everyone who was sympathetic to united
states was executed
same thing was done under the guidance
of of the soviet embassy in hanoi and
same thing i was doing in new delhi
to my horror i discovered that in the
files where people were doomed
to execution there were names of
pro-soviet journalists with whom
i was personally friendly yes
they were idealistically minded leftists
who
made several visits to ussr and yet the
kgb decided that com revolution or
drastic changes in political structure
of india they will have to go why is
that
because they know too much simply
because you see the useful idiots the
the leftists who are
idealistically believing in the beauty
of soviet socialist or communist or
whatever system
when they get disillusioned they become
the worst enemies
that's why my kgb instructors
specifically made the point
never bother with leftists forget about
these political prostitutes
aim higher this was my instruction
try to get into into a large circulation
established conservative media reach
filthy reach movie makers intellectuals
so-called academic circles
cynical egocentric people who can look
into your eyes with angelic expression
and tell you a lie
this are the most recruitable people
people who lack moral principles
who are either too greedy or to
suffer from self-importance they feel
that
they they matter a lot these are the
people who
kgb wanted very much to recruit but to
eliminate the others to execute the
others
don't they serve some purpose wouldn't
they be the ones that realize they serve
purpose only at the stage of
destabilization of a nation for example
your leftists in the united states all
these professors and all these
beautiful civil rights defenders they
are instrumental in the process of the
of the uh
subversion only to destabilize the
nation
when their job is completed they're not
they're not needed anymore
they know too much some of them when
when they get disillusioned when they
see that marxist lenin has come to power
obviously they get offended they think
that they will come to power
that will never happen of course they
will be lined up against the wall and
shot
but they may turn into the most bitter
enemies
of marxist leninist when they come to
power and that's what happened in
nicaragua you remember most of these
former marxist leninists were either put
to prison
or one of them split and now he's
working against sandinistas
it happened in grenada when maurice
bishop
was he was already a marxist he was
executed by by a new marxist who was
more marxist than this marxist
same happened in afghanistan when uh
first there was taraki he was killed by
amin and amin was killed by
karmal with the help of kgb same
happened in in bangladesh when mujibur
rahman very pro-soviet leftist
was assassinated by his own
marxist-leninist
military comrades it's the same pattern
everywhere
the moment they serve their purpose all
the useful idiots are used
either be executed entirely all the
idealistically minded marxists
or were exiled or put in prisons like in
cuba many many former marxists are in
cuba
i mean in prison so most of the indians
who were cooperating with the soviets
especially without the department of
of uh information of the ussr embassy
were
listed for execution
and when i discovered that fact of
course i was sick i was mentally and
physically sick i thought that i'm going
to explode one day
during the briefing of the ambassador's
office i would stand up and say
something that
we are basically a bunch of murderers
that's what we are we
it has nothing to do with friendship and
understanding between the nation and
blah blah blah
we are murderers we behave as a bunch of
thugs
in in a country which which is
hospitable to us a country which
with ancient traditions but i i did not
defect i tried to get the message across
to my
horror nobody wanted even to listen
least of all to believe what i had to
say
and i tried all kind of tricks i would i
would i would
leak information through letters uh or
lost documents or something like that
and still i got no message
the message was not published even in
the conservative mass media of
india the immediate impulse to defect
was bangladesh crisis which was
described by american correspondents
as islamic grassroots revolution which
is
absolute baloney there was nothing to do
with islam
and there was no grassroots revolution
actually there are no grassroots
revolutions period
any revolution is a byproduct of a
highly organized group
of conscientious and professional
organizers
but has nothing to do with grassroots in
bangladesh
it was nothing with grassroots most of
the
avami league party members of amilign's
people's
party were trained in moscow in the high
party school
most of the mukti fault leaders
muktifajis in bengali means people's
army
same as swappo and and all kind of
liberation armies all over the world
the same bunch of useful idiots they
were trained at lumumba university and
various centers of the kgb in sinfiropol
in
in crimea and in tashkent
so when i saw that india indian
territory is being used as a as a
jumping board
to destroy east pakistan i saw myself
thousands of of so-called students
traveling through india to east pakistan
through the territory
of india and indian government pretended
not to see what was going on
they knew perfectly well the indian
police knew it the intelligence
department of indian government
knew it the kgb of course knew it and
the cia knew it
that that was most infuriating because
when i defected and i explained to the
cia debriefers
they should watch out because east
pakistan is going to erupt any moment
they said i i was i was reading to too
many james bond novels
anyway so east pakistan was doomed
uh one of my colleagues in in the soviet
consulate in kolkata when he was dead
drunk he ventured into the basement
to relieve himself and he founded big
boxes
which said printed matter to dhaka
university
dhaka is the capital of his pakistan and
since he was drunk and curious he opened
one of the boxes and he discovered not
printed matter he discovered kalashnikov
guns and ammunition in there
anyway it's a long story when i saw the
preparations for the
for the uh invasion into east pakistan
obviously i wanted to defect immediately
the only thing i couldn't
i couldn't at that time make up my mind
when
and where and how one of the reasons of
course you see
i was in love with india i mentioned it
before
i spoke the languages i socialized with
people
and i understood that i had to to act
fast
unless i want this beautiful country to
be permanently and
irreparably damaged by our presence
one of the reasons not to defect was as
you can see i was living in relative
affluence
who the hell in in the normal mind
would defect and do what to be abused by
your media
to be called mccarthyist and fascist and
paranoid
or to drive a taxi in new york city what
for what the hell for should i defect
to be abused by americans to be insulted
in exchange for my effort to bring the
truthful information about
impending danger of subversion as you
can see i was living
in quite a comfortable conditions next
to swimming pool where
indians were not allowed by the way i
was highly paid expert in propaganda
i had my family i was respected by my
nation
my career was cloudless the third reason
how to defect with the family
to defect with the baby and the wife
would be virtual suicide because
according to law that hypocritical law
which i quoted before
the indian police will have to hand me
over back to the kgb
and that will be the end of my defection
and probably my life
again i cannot smuggle my wife
because she was not quite sure what what
i was doing she was not that
idealistically involved and she was
definitely not in in the total picture
of what i was doing for the kgb
she would be shocked if i if i
you know put her in my van and drive her
to american embassy or elsewhere
that would be a greatest danger so
again i had to defect in such a way that
my defection would look
as simple disappearance and there were
many cases like that
when the soviet agents simply
disappeared either killed in action
or thanks to their curiosity and and
their close contacts with radicals some
of them were killed by the marxist by
the way
it happened in many african countries
when the soviet kgb were killed by
africans themselves not because they
hated marxism leninist but because they
were simply trigger happy
bunch of unruly characters if you give
them machine gun they will shoot
and some of the soviets obviously were
not careful enough to protect themselves
and they got into embarrassing
situations when they were shot
at the crossfire between factions of
so-called liberation movements
anyway so i i decided as i said to study
the
counter culture i decided this probably
would be the best way to disappear
i socialize with characters like this on
the left
you see he's a barefoot american hippie
it took me quite a long time to study
exactly what they were doing and how to
mix with them
but eventually i did it most of indian
newspapers carried my picture
and promise of 2 000 rupees for
information
about my whereabouts but they were
looking for wrong person because they
obviously tried to stop a young soviet
diplomat
in white shirt and thai and this is how
i looked at the time of defection nobody
could possibly
think that the soviet diplomat would be
as crazy as to join a bunch of hippies
that's you yes travel indian smokehouse
so
i made it literally almost like a
hollywood style
detective story uh from under the nose
of the kgb in bombay airport
i landed the plane and i flew to to
greece where i was debriefed by the cia
that's basically the most that's all for
my
slides we can turn off the projectors
and that's very interesting
well you spoke several times before
about ideological subversion that is a
phrase that
i'm afraid some americans don't fully
understand when
the soviets use the phrase ideological
subversion what do they mean by it
ideological subversion is is the process
which is legitimate overt
and open you can see it with your own
eyes all you have to do all american
mass media has to do is to unplug their
bananas from their ears
open up their eyes and they can see it
there's no mystery there's nothing to do
with espionage
i know that espionage intelligence
gathering looks more romantic
it sells more deodorants through the
advertising probably that's why
your hollywood producers are so crazy
about james bond
type of thrillers but in reality
the main emphasis of the kgb is not in
the area of its
intelligence at all according to my
opinion and opinion of many defectors of
my caliber
only about 15 of time money and
manpower is spent on espionage as such
the other 85 percent
is a slow process which we call either
ideological subversion or active
measures
activeness in the language of the kgb
or psychological warfare what it
basically means is
to change the perception of reality of
every
american to such an extent that despite
of the abundance of information
no one is able to come to sensible
conclusions
in the interests of defending themselves
their families
their community and their country it's a
great brainwashing process which goes
very slow and is divided in four basic
stages
uh the first one being demoralization it
takes from 15 to 20 years to demoralize
a nation
why that many years because this is the
minimum number of years which requires
to
educate one generation of students
in the country of of of your enemy
exposed to the ideology of the enemy
in other words marxism leninism ideology
is being pumped into the soft heads of
of at least three generations of
american students without being
challenged or counterbalanced by the
basic values
of americanism american patriotism the
result
the result you can see most of the
people who graduated in 60s
dropouts or half-baked intellectuals are
now occupying the positions of power in
the government
civil service business mass media
educational system
you are stuck with them you cannot get
rid of them they are contaminated they
are
programmed to think and react to certain
stimuli
in a certain pattern you cannot change
their mind even if you if you
expose them to authentic information
even if you prove that white is white
and black
is black you still cannot change the
basic
perception and the logic of behavior
in other words these people the process
of demoralization
is complete and irreversible to get rid
society of these people you have you
need
another 20 or or 15 years
to educate a new generation of
patriotically minded
and and common common sense
people who would be acting in
favor and in the interests of of the of
united states society and yet these
people have been programmed and as you
say in place
and who are favorable to an opening with
the soviet concept
these are the very people who would be
marked for extermination in this country
most of them yes
simply because the psychological shock
when they will see in future what the
what the beautiful
society of equality and social justice
means in practice
obviously they will revolt they they
will
they will be very unhappy frustrated
people
and the marxist leninist regime does not
tolerate these people
they obviously they will join the links
of the centers
dissidents uh unlike in present
united states there will be no place for
descent in future marxist leninist
america here you can you can get
popular like daniel ellsberg and filthy
rich like jane fonda
for being dissident for criticizing your
pentagon
in future these people will be simply
squashed like cockroaches
nobody is going to pay them nothing for
their beautiful noble ideas of equality
this they don't understand and it will
be greatest shock for them of course
the demoralization process in the united
states is basically completed already
uh for the last 25 years actually it's
over fulfilled because
demoralization now reaches such areas
where previously
not even comrade and drop off
would even dream of such a tremendous
success
most of it is done by americans to
americans
thanks to lack of moral standards as i
mentioned before
uh exposure to true information does not
matter anymore
a person who was demoralized is unable
to assess
true information the facts tell nothing
to him
uh even if i shower him with information
with
authentic proof with documents with
pictures
even if i take him by force to the
soviet union and show him concentration
camp
he will refuse to believe it until
he is going to receive a kick in the in
his fat bottom
when the military boot crashes his then
he will understand
but not before that that's the tragic of
the situation of demoralization
so basically america is stuck with
demoralization and
unless even if if you start right now
here this minute you start educating new
generation of americans
it will still take you 15 to 20 years to
turn the tide
of ideological perception of reality
uh back to normal normalcy and
patriotism the next stage is
destabilization
this time subverter does not care about
your ideas and the patterns of your
consumption
whether you eat junk food and get fat
and flop it doesn't matter anymore
this time and it takes only from two to
five years to destabilize the nation
uh it's what what matters is essentials
economy foreign relations defense
systems
and you can see it quite clearly that in
some areas
in such sensitive areas as defense
and economy the influence of marxist
leninist
ideas in the united states is absolutely
fantastic i could never believe it 14
years ago when i landed
in this part of the world that the
process will go that fast
the next stage of course is crisis it
may take only
up to six weeks to to bring a country to
the verge of crisis
you can see it in in central america now
and after crisis
with a violent change of of power
structure and economy
you have so-called the period of
normalization it may last indefinitely
normalization is a cynical expression
borrowed from soviet propaganda
when the soviet tanks moved into
czechoslovakia in 68
comrade brezhnev said now the situation
in brotherly czechoslovakia is
normalized
this is what will happen in the united
states if you allow all the schmucks to
bring the country to crisis
to promise people all kind of goodies
and the paradise on earth
to to destabilize your economy
to eliminate the principle of free
market competition
and to put a big brother government
in washington dc with the benevolent
dictators like walter mondale
who will promise lots of things never
mind whether the promises are
fulfillable or not
he will go to moscow to kiss the bottoms
of new
generation of soviet assassins never
mind he will create
false illusions that the situation is
under control situation is not
under control situation is disgustingly
out of control
most of the american politicians media
and educational system
trains another generation of people who
think they
are living at the peace time false
united states is in the state of war
undeclared
total war against the basic principles
and the foundations of this system
and and the initiator of this war is not
covered on drop off of course
uh it's it's the system however
ridiculous it may sound
the world communist system or the world
communist conspiracy whether i scare
some people or not
i don't give a hoot if if you are not
scared by now
nothing can scare you but you don't have
to be paranoid about it
what what actually happens now that
unlike myself
you have literally several years to live
on unless united states wake up
the the time bomb is ticking with every
second the disaster is coming closer and
closer
unlike myself you will have nowhere to
defect to
unless you want to live in antarctica
with penguins this is it this is the
last country of freedom
and possibility okay so what do we do
what is your recommendation to the
american people well
uh the the uh the immediate thing that
comes to my mind
is of course there must be a very strong
national effort to educate people in in
in the spirit of real patriotism number
one number two
to to explain them the real danger of
socialist communist whatever welfare
state
big brother government if people will
fail to grasp the
impending danger of that development
nothing ever can help united states you
may kiss goodbye to your freedom
including freedoms to homosexuals to
a prison inmate all this freedom will
vanish evaporating in five seconds
including your precious lives
the second thing i the moment at least
part of united states
population is convinced that the danger
is real
they have to force their government and
i'm not talking about sending letters
signing petitions
and all this beautiful noble activity
i'm talking about
forcing united states government to stop
aiding communism because there is no
other problem
more burning and urgent than to stop the
soviet military industrial complex
from destroying what is whatever is left
of the free world
and it is very easy to do no credits
no technology no money no political or
diplomatic recognition
and of course no such idiocy as grain
deals to ussr
the soviet people 270 millions of
soviets will be
eternally thankful to you if you stop
aiding a bunch of murderers who sit now
in kremlin
and whom president dragon respectfully
calls government they do not govern
anything
least of all such complexity as the
soviet economy
so basic two very simple maybe two
simplistic answers
or solutions but never nevertheless they
are the only solutions educate yourself
understand what's going on around you
you are not living at the time of peace
you are in a state of war and you have
precious
little time to save yourself um
you don't have much time especially if
you are talking about young generation
there's not much time left for
convulsions
to the beautiful disco music
very soon it will go just just overnight
if we are talking about capitalists or
or or
wealthy businessmen they i think they
are selling the rope on which they will
hang very soon
if they don't stop it they cannot curb
their
unsaturated desire for profit and if
they keep on trading with the monster of
the soviet communism
they are going to hang very soon and it
they will pray to be killed
but unfortunately they will be sent to
alaska probably to manage
industry of slaves it's
it's simplistic i know it sounds
unpleasant i know americans don't like
to listen to things which are
unpleasant but i have defected not to
tell you the stories
about such idiocies as microfilm james
bond type
espionage this is garbage
you don't need any espionage anymore i
have come to talk about
survival it's a question of survival of
this system
you may ask me what is it for me
survival obviously because unlike
i as i said i am now in your boat
if we sing together we will sing
beautifully together
there is no other place on this planet
to defect
[Music]
you