what you're about to see is an interview
from the year ironically
1984. it involves KGB Defector Yuri
besminoff and his revelation of what he
called the Soviet subversion Model A
four-point Plan by which the Soviet
Union sought to subvert the United
States from within I think I can assure
you that you're going to find what he
says chilling and how it seems to be
playing out right before our very eyes
Mr bezmianov was born in 1939 in a
suburb of Moscow he was the son of a
high-ranking Soviet army officer he was
educated in the elite schools inside the
Soviet Union and became an expert in
Indian culture and Indian languages
he had an outstanding career with novice
which was the pr and still is I should
say the Press arm or the Press agency of
the Soviet Union it turns out that this
is also a front for the KGB
he escaped to the West in 1970 after
becoming totally disgusted with the
Soviet system and he did this at Great
risk to his life
he certainly is one of the world's
outstanding experts on the subject of
Soviet propaganda and disinformation and
active measures
well you spoke several times before
about ideological subversion that is a
phrase that I'm afraid some Americans
don't fully understand when the Soviets
used the phrase ideological subversion
what do they mean by ideological
subversion is is the slow process
which we call either ideological
subversion or active measures active in
the language of the KGB or psychological
warfare what it basically means is to
change the perception of reality of
every American
to such an extent that despite of the
abundance of information
no one is able to come to sensible
conclusions
in the interests of Defending themselves
their families their community and their
country
all right I just want to make sure we
have that definition really set in front
of us here as he takes us through the
process big picture besminoff is making
the point that much of the work of the
KGB had literally nothing to do with the
James Bond like glamors of Espionage and
Intrigue instead much of it involved a
very slow very patient but very
deliberate process of undermining the
stability of a rival Nation through what
they called ideological subversion and
here's how we Define that quote
what it basically means is to change the
perception of reality of every American
to such an extent that despite the
abundance of information no one is able
to come to sensible conclusions in the
interest of Defending themselves their
families their community and their
country
I gotta say when I first heard that
sometime back I asked myself is he
defining or is he describing
because what he just said there could
easily be a description of many in our
society today we have we have an entire
class of people whose perception
realities quite literally beyond the
sensible beyond the biological beyond
the national they're increasingly
pushing a vision of reality that
seemingly makes no sense even the people
on the left like Bill Maher and yet
everyone's scared to death to confront
them on it to stand up to this lest you
be excommunicated canceled
it's a great brainwashing process which
goes very slow and it's divided in in
four basic stages
uh the first one being demoralization it
takes from 15 to 20 years to demoralize
the nation why that many years because
this is the minimum number of years
which requires to educate one generation
of students
in the country of of your enemy exposed
to the ideology of the enemy in other
words Marx's leninism ideology is being
pumped into the soft heads of of at
least three generations of American
students without being challenged or
counterbalanced by the basic values of
americanism American patriotism
the demoralization process in the United
States is basically completed already
for the last 25 years actually it's over
fulfilled because demoralization now
reaches such areas where previously not
even comrade and drop off and on all his
experts would would even dream of such a
tremendous success most of it is done by
Americans to Americans thanks to lack of
moral standards as I mentioned before
exposure to True information does not
matter anymore
a person who was demoralized is unable
to assess true information the facts
tell nothing to him even if I shower him
with information with with authentic
proof with documents with pictures
even if I take him by force to the
Soviet Union and show him concentration
camp he will refuse to believe it until
he he is going to receive a kick in the
in his fat bottom when a military boat
crashes his balls then he will
understand but not before that that's
the tragic of the situation of
demoralization when he talked about this
first stage of demoralization I could
not help but think of the Frankfurt
School which was a group of European
academics who came over to the United
States to escape Hitler but brought
their cultural Marxist ideas to the
American University and for various
reasons the ideas flourished in colleges
Across the Nation and at the heart of
the Frankfurt school's ideology is this
notion of critical theory which teaches
students how to supposedly expose
everything in our culture from our
politics to our economics from our
entertainment to our fashion you name it
as inherently racist sexist and
homophobic and eventually critical
theory entered into our K-12 classrooms
through the broader notion of what's
called critical pedagogy from which we
get what's called CRT or critical race
Theory but what besminoff is saying here
is that all of that was highly
deliberate it wasn't simply an academic
development in the free exchange of
ideas it was more like a virus that was
deliberately injected into our national
culture and radically weakened our
social immune system and as he put it it
was more effective than any KGB agent
could have imagined and he would go on
to say that that's going to take a new
generation of Americans to rise up and
push back against this neo-marxas
ideological filth that so permeated the
last couple of generations
the next stage is destabilization this
time subverter does not care about your
ideas and the patterns of your
consumption whether you eat junk food
and get fat and flub it doesn't matter
anymore this time and it takes only from
two to five years to destabilize the
nation uh it's what what matters is
Essentials economy Foreign Relations
defense systems
and you can see it quite clearly that in
some areas in such sensitive areas is
defense and economy the influence of
marxist leninist ideas in the United
States is absolutely fantastic I could
never believe it 14 years ago when I
landed in this part of the world that
the process will go that fast
well it's only gone downhill from there
won't cancel culture is completely
infected our mainstream economy and
unfortunately our military and I
personally find it offensive
that we are accusing the United States
military our General Offices our
commissioned non-commissioned officers
of being quote woke or something else
because we're studying some theories
that are out there that was started at
Harvard Law School years ago and it
proposed that there were laws in the
United States anti-bellum laws prior to
the Civil War that led to a power
differential with African Americans that
were three quarters of a human being
when this country was formed and then we
had a civil war and emancipation proper
probation to change it and we brought it
up to the Civil Rights Act in 1964 took
another 100 years to change that so look
it I do want to know yeah that's woke
Millie General Mark milley chairman of
the Joint Chiefs of Staff defending
teaching cultural Marxism to our
officers
hey gang I've been teasing you all month
that I've got something big to share
with you at the end of the month well
here we are this Friday at 12 Eastern
I'm sending out a special email to my
email list only I can't share it here
but I'll give you a little hint if
you're a fan of the TV show The Chosen
you're gonna love this so what could be
my special announcement I'm sharing this
important announcement on my newsletter
this Friday at noon Eastern and you
don't want to miss it all you got to do
is click on the link below and sign up
for my newsletter now at turleytalks.com
forward slash subscribe you will not
hear this news news that's really
important for our movement you're not
going to hear it anywhere else but from
my email list so make sure to click on
that link below right now and subscribe
uh the next stage of course is Crisis it
it may take only up to six weeks to to
bring a country to the verge of Crisis
you can see it in in Central America now
and after crisis with a violent change
of power structure and economy you have
so-called the period of normalization it
may last indefinitely normalization is a
cynical expression borrowed from Soviet
propaganda when the Soviet tanks moved
into Czechoslovakia in 68 comrade
breshner said now the situation in
brotherly Czechoslovakia is normalized
this is what will happen in the United
States if you allow all these Schmucks
to bring the country to crisis
to promise people all kind of goodies
and the paradise on Earth to to
destabilize your economy to eliminate
the principle of free market competition
and to put a big brother government
in Washington DC with the benevolent
dictators Like Walter Mondale who will
promise lots of things never mind
whether the promises are fulfillable or
not yeah again as I hear him describe
this crisis stage I just couldn't help
but think of where we are today with the
Bumble and binding Administration I mean
unprecedented inflation surging gas
prices a looming recession baby formula
shortages supply chain interruptions I
need another hand border implosion of
violent crime epidemic defunding the
police woke school boards Global
pandemics Mass lockdowns
unconstitutional vax mandates and then
after that normalization this crisis
condition ends up being The New Normal
a fully destabilized nation is now the
new normal and the enemy has been
thwarted from within I mean it's pretty
terrifying stuff but again the good news
is that besmenoff believed that we were
just one generation away from American
renewal
and everywhere we look that's exactly
what we're seeing there's nothing short
of a massive Grassroots backlash against
woke cultural Marxism and it's just the
beginning we will take our nation back
and we will go through a conservative
Renaissance and while people like Yuri
besminoff
to thank
as always make sure to smack that Bell
And subscribe button you definitely want
to check out my latest video on a
Vietnam vet getting challenged by woke
bullies and you won't believe what
happened next you could absolutely love
it make sure to click on that link and
I'll see you over there God bless
[Music]