well you spoke several times before
about ideological subversion that is a
phrase that uh I'm afraid some Americans
don't fully understand when uh the
Soviets use the phrase ideological
subversion what do they mean by it
ideological subversion is is the process
which is legitimate over word and open
you you can see it with your own eyes
all all you have to do all American mass
media has to do is to unplug their
bananas from their ears open up their
eyes and they can see it there is no
mystery there's nothing to do with
Espionage I know that Espionage
intelligence gathering looks more
romantic it sells more deodorant through
the advertising probably that's why your
Hollywood producers are so crazy about
James Bond type of of Thrillers but in
reality the main emphasis of the KGB is
not in the area of intelligence at all
according to my opinion and opinion of
many def factors of my caliber only
about 15% of time money and Manpower is
spent on Espionage as such the other 85%
is a slow process which we call either
ideological subversion or active
measures activ in the language of of the
KGB or psychological warfare what it
basically means is to change the
perception of reality of every
American to such an extent that despite
of the abundance of
information no one is able to come to
sensible conclusions in the interest of
Defending themselves their families
their community and their
country it's a great
brainwashing uh process which goes very
slow and it's divided in in four basic
stages uh the first one being
demoralization it takes from 15 to 20
years to demoralize a nation why that
many years
because this is the minimum number of
years which requires to educate one
generation of students in the country of
of of your enemy exposed to the ideology
of the enemy in other words Marxism
leninism ideology is being pumped into
the soft heads of of at least three
generations of American students without
being challenged or counterbalanced by
the basic values of americanism American
patriotism the result the result you can
see most of the people who graduated in
60s dropouts or half-baked intellectuals
are now occupying the positions of power
in the government civil service business
mass media educational system you are
stuck with them you cannot get rid of
them they are contaminated they are
programmed to think and react to certain
stimuli in a certain pattern you cannot
change their mind even if you if you
expose them to authentic information
even if you prove that why white is
white and black is black you still
cannot change the basic perception and
the logic of behavior and another words
these people uh uh the process of
demoralization is complete and
irreversible to get rid Society of these
people you have you need another 20 or
or or 15 years to educate a new
generation of patriotically minded and
and and uh common common sense people
who would be acting in favor and in the
interests of of the of the United States
society and yet these people who' been
programmed and as you say in place and
who are favorable to an opening with the
Soviet concept these are the very people
who would be marked for extermination in
this country most of them yes uh simply
because the psychological shock when
when they will see in future what the
what the beautiful Society of equality
and social justice means in practice
obviously they will Revolt they they
will they will be very unhappy
frustrated people and the Marxist
leninist regime does not tolerate these
people uh they obviously they will join
the links of denters dissidents yes uh
unlike in present United States there
will be no place for descent in in
future Marxist leninist America uh here
you can you can get uh popular like
Daniel ellberg and Filthy Rich like Jane
Fonda for being dissident for
criticizing your Pentagon in Future
these people will be simply squashed
like cockroaches nobody's going to pay
them nothing for their beautiful Noble
ideas of equality this they don't
understand and uh it will be greatest
shock for them of course the
demoralization process in the United
States is basically completed already uh
for the last 25 years actually it's over
fulfilled because demoralization now
reaches such areas where previously not
even comrad andropov and and all his
experts would would even dream of such a
tremendous success most of it is done by
Americans to Americans thanks to lack of
moral standards as I mentioned before uh
exposure to True information does not
matter anymore a person who was
demoralized is unable to assess true
information the facts tell nothing to
him uh even if I shower him with
information with with authentic proof
with documents with pictures even if I
take him by force to the Soviet Union
and show him concentration camp he will
refuse to believe it until he he's going
to receive a kick in the in his fat
bottom when a military boot crashes his
then he will understand but not before
that that's the tragic of the situation
of demoralization so basically American
Amica is stuck with with demoralization
and unless even if if you start right
now here this minute you start educating
new generation of American it will still
take you 15 to 20 years to turn the tide
of uh of ideological perception of
reality uh back to normal normaly and
and
patriotism the next stage is
destabilization this time subverter does
not care about your ideas and the
patterns of your consumption whether you
eat junk food and get fat and flab it
doesn't matter anymore this time and it
takes only from 2 to 5 years to
destabilize a nation uh it's what what
matters is Essentials economy Foreign
Relations defense
systems uh and you can see it quite
clearly that in some areas uh in such
sensitive areas as as uh defense and
economy the influence of marxist
leninist ideas in the United States is
absolutely fantastic I I could never
believe it 14 years ago when I landed uh
in this part of the world that the
process will go that
fast uh the next stage of course is
Crisis it it it may take only up to six
weeks to to bring a country to the verge
of Crisis you can see it in in Central
America now and after crisis with a
violent change of of power structure and
economy you have so-called the period of
normalization it may last indefinitely
normalization is a cynical expression
borrowed from Soviet propaganda when the
Soviet tanks moved into Czechoslovakia
in ' 68 comr BR said now the situation
in brotherly Czechoslovakia is
normalized this is what will happen in
United States if you allow all the
Schmucks to bring the country to
crisis to promise people all kind of
goodies and the paradise on Earth uh to
to destabilize your economy to eliminate
the principle of free market competition
and to put a big brother government in
Washington DC with the benevolent
dictators Like Walter Mondale who will
promise lots of things never mind
whether the promises are fulfilled or
not he will go to Moscow to kiss the
bottoms of of new generation of Soviet
assassins never mind he will create
false illusions that the situation is
under control situation is not under
control situation is disgustingly out of
control most of the American politicians
media and educational system trains
another generation of people who think
they are living at a peace time false
United States is in the state of War UND
declared total war against the basic
principles and the foundations of of
this
system and and the initiator of this war
is not comrad andropov of
course uh it's it's the
system however ridiculous it may sound
the world communist system or the world
communist conspiracy whether I scar some
people are not I don't give a hood uh if
if you are not scared by now nothing can
scare you but you don't have to be
paranoid about it what what actually
happens now that unlike myself you
have literally several years to live on
unless the United States wake up the the
time bomb is ticking with every second
the disaster is coming closer and closer
unlike myself you will have nowhere to
defect to unless you want to live in
Antarctica with penguins this is it this
is the last country of freedom and and
possibility okay so what do we do what
is your recommendation to the American
people well uh the the um the immediate
thing that comes to my mind is of course
there must be a very strong National
effort to educate people in in in the
spirit of real patriotism number one
number two to to explain them the real
danger of Socialist Communist whatever
welfare state Big Brother government if
people will fail to grasp the impending
danger of that development nothing ever
can help United States you make his
goodbye to your freedom including
freedoms to to homosexuals to prison
inmate all the Freedom will vanish
evaporating in 5 seconds including your
precious
lives um the second thing I the moment
at least part of United States
population is convinced that the danger
is real they have to force their
government and I'm not talking about
sending letters signing petitions and
all this beautiful Noble activity I'm
talking about forcing United States
government to stop aiding
communism because there is no no other
problem more burning and and urgent than
to stop the Soviet military industrial
complex from destroying what is whatever
is left of the Free World and it is very
easy to do no credits no technology no
money no political or diplomatic
recognition and of course no such ID as
grain deals to
USSR the Soviet people 270 millions of
of Soviets will be eternally thankful to
you if you stop aiding a bunch of
murderers who sit now in Kremlin and
whom president dragan respectfully calls
government they do not govern anything
list of all such complexity as the
Soviet economy so basic two two very
simple maybe two simplistic answers or
Solutions but never nevertheless they
are the only solutions educate yourself
understand what's going on around you
you are not living at the time of Peace
you are in a state of war and you have
precious little time to save
yourself um you don't have much time
especially if you're are talking about
Young Generation there's not much time
left for
convulsions to the beautiful uh disco
music very soon it will go just just
overnight if we are talking about
capitalists or or or wealthy
businessmen they I think they are
selling the Rope on which they will hang
very soon if they don't stop if they can
not curb their unsettle desire for
profit and if they keep on trading with
the monster of the Soviet
communism they are going to hang very
soon and it they will pray to be killed
but unfortunately they will be sent to
Alaska probably to manage industry of
slaves it's it's simplistic I know it
sounds unpleasant I know Americans don't
like to listen to things which are
unpleasant but I have defected not to
tell you the stories about such idiocy
is as microfilm James Bond type
Espionage this is
garbage uh you don't need any Espionage
anymore I have come to talk about
survival it's a question of survival of
this
system you may ask me what is it in for
me survival obviously because unlike I
as I said I am now in your boat if if we
sing together we will sing beautifully
together there is no other place on the
this planet to defect
[Music]
to