my father was he is on the left here
my father was officer of the General
Staff of the Soviet Army
he was inspector of land forces Soviet
troops stationed in countries like
Mongolia Cuba East European countries
this is the picture taken at the
entrance of my Institute of Oriental
languages it's a part of Moscow State
University as every Soviet student I was
quote-unquote volunteering for
harvesting grain in Kazakhstan by the
end of my training in school I was
recruited by the KGB this picture was
taken on that day and you can see again
how happy it feels to be recruited by
the KGB pay special attention to number
of bottles on the table one of my
functions was to keep foreign guests
permanently intoxicated the moment they
land at Moscow Airport in 1967 the KGB
attached me to this magazine Look
magazine a group of 12 people arrive to
USSR from the United States to cover the
50th anniversary of October socialist
revolution in my country from the first
page to the last page it was a package
of lies
[Music]
our conversation is with mr. Yuri
Alexandrovich Desmond auth mr. Boozman
auth was born in 1939 in a suburb of
Moscow he was the son of a high-ranking
Soviet Army officer he was educated in
the elite schools inside the Soviet
Union and became an expert in Indian
culture and Indian languages he had an
outstanding career with novice T which
was the French still is I should say the
press arm or the press agency of the
Soviet Union it turns out that this is
also a front for the KGB one of his
interesting assignments was to brainwash
foreign diplomats when they visited
Moscow and he'll tell us a little bit
about how they did this and how they
planted information which eventually
wounded them the press of the free world
he escaped to the west in 1970 after
becoming totally disgusted with the
Soviet system and he did this at great
risk to his life he certainly is one of
the world's outstanding experts on the
subject of Soviet propaganda and
disinformation and active measures mr.
Boozman off I'd like to begin by having
you tell us a little bit about some of
your childhood memories well the most
vivid memory of my childhood was Second
World War
or to be more precise the end of the
Second World War when all of a sudden
United States from a friendly nation
which helped us to defeat Nazism turned
overnight into a deadly enemy and it was
very shocking because all newspapers
were trying to present an image of
belligerent aggressive American
imperialism most of the things that we
were taught is that the United States is
aggressive power which is just about to
invade our beautiful free socialist
country that American CIA is dropping
Colorado beetles on our beautiful potato
fields to eliminate our crops and each
schoolboy had a picture of Colorado
bargained on the back page of his
notebook and we were instructed to go
into collective fields to search for
those little Colorado bugs of
course we couldn't find any neither we
could find many potatoes and that was
explained again by the encroachments of
the decadent imperialist power the
anti-american paranoia hysteria in the
Soviet propaganda was to such an
agreement achill people or less stubborn
would really believe that the United
States is just about to invade our
beautiful motherland and some secretly
hope that it will come true
that's interesting yes well getting back
to life inside the Soviet Union or
inside communist countries in general in
this country at the university level
primarily we read and hear that the
Soviet system is different from ours but
not that different and that there is a
convergence developing between all of
the systems of the world and that really
doesn't make an awful lot of difference
what system you live under because you
have corruption and dishonesty and
tyranny and all that sort of thing from
your personal experience what is the
difference between life under communism
and life in the United States well life
is obviously very much different for
simple reason that the Soviet Union is a
state capitalist economically it's a
state capitalism where an individual has
absolutely no rights no value his life
is nothing it's just like an insect
he is disposable whereby in the United
States even though even the worst
criminal is treated as a human being he
has a fair trial and some of them
capitalize on their crimes they
published their memoirs in their prisons
and get handsomely paid by your crazy
publishers the differences of course in
the daily life are very various
depending on who or whom we are talking
about in my own private life I never
suffered from communism simply because I
was brought up in the family of
high-ranking military officer most of
the doors were open for me
most of my expenses were paid by the
government and I never had any troubles
and with the authorities or
with the police so in other words I
would say I enjoyed or I had good
reasons to enjoy all the advantages of
so-called socialist system my main
motivations to defect was had nothing to
do with affluence it was mainly moral
indignation moral protest rebellion
against the inhuman methods of of the
Soviet system well specifically what did
you object to I objected first of all
against oppression of my own dissidents
and intellectuals and that was the most
disgusting thing that that I witnessed
as a as a young man young student who
was brought up a very troublesome period
in our history from Stalin to Khrushchev
from total tyranny and oppression to
some kind of liberalisation second when
I started working for the Soviet embassy
in India I to my horror I discovered
that we are millions times more
oppressive than any colonial or
imperialist power in the history of
mankind that my country brings to India
not freedom progress and friendship
between the nations but racism
exploitation and slavery and it can of
course economical inefficiency to this
country since I fell in love with India
I developed something which by KGB
standards is extremely dangerous ting
it's called split loyalty when an agent
likes a country of a silent more than
his own country I literally fell in love
with this beautiful country a country of
great contrasts but also great humility
great tolerance and philosophical and
intellectual freedoms my ancestors used
to live in caves and eat raw meat when
India was highly civilized nation 6,000
years ago so obviously the choice was
not to the advantage of my own nation I
decided to defect and to entirely
dissociate myself from that brutal
regime mr. bears me enough we've read a
lot about the concentration camps and
the slave labor camps under the Stalin
regime
now the general impression in America is
that those things are part of the past
are they still going on today or what is
there that is yes there is no
qualitative change in this Soviet
concentration camp system there are
changes in in numbers of prisoners again
this is unreliable service statistics we
don't know how many political prisoners
are there in the soviet concentration
camps but we sure know from from various
sources that at each particular time
there are close to 25 to 30 million of
soviet citizens who are virtually kept
as slaves in forced labor camp system
the size of the population of country
like Canada is serving terms as
prisoners incredible so I would say that
those intellectuals who try to convince
American public that concentration camp
system is a thing of a past or either
conscientiously misleading public
opinion or they are not in very
intellectual people they they're
selectively blind they don't they lack
intellectual honesty when they say that
well we've spoken about the
intellectuals in this country and also
the intellectuals in the Soviet Union
what about down at the broad mass level
do the people in general the working and
the working people the workers in
general and the Soviet Union do they
support the system do they tolerate it
what is their attitude well every Soviet
citizen if there is such an animal of
course does not light the system because
it hurts it kills he may not understand
the the reasons he may not have enough
information or educational background to
understand but I doubt very much there
are many people who are conscientiously
supporting the Soviet system there are
such people in USSR even those who have
all the reasons to enjoy socialism
people like myself we're a member of
journalistic elite they they also hate
system food for different reasons don't
not because they lack material affluence
but because they are unfree to think
they're in constant fear duplicity split
personality and this is a greatest
tragedy for my nation well what do you
think are the chances of the people
actually overcoming their system or
replacing it there is a great
possibility that system will sooner or
later will be destroyed from within
there is a self-destructive mechanism
built-in into any socialist or communist
or fascist system because there is lack
of feedback because the system does not
rely upon loyalty of population but
until and until this Soviet Volta is
being supported by the Western so-called
imperialists that is multinational
companies establishments governments and
let's face it intellectuals so-called
academia in the United States is famous
for supporting the Soviet system as long
as the Soviet hunter will keep on
receiving credits money technology grain
deals and political recognition from all
these traitors of democracy or freedom
there is no hope there is not much hope
for for changes in my country and the
system will not collapse by itself
simply because it's being nourished by
so-called American imperialism this is
the greatest paradox in history of
mankind
when capitalist world supports and
actively nourishes its own destructor
destructor I think you're trying to tell
us something
oh yes Center and trying to tell you
that it has to be stopped unless you
want to end up in in gulag system and
enjoy all the advantages of socialist
equality
working for free catching fleas on your
body sleeping on the planks of plywood
in in Alaska this time I guess that's
where Americans will belong unless they
will wake up of course and force their
government to stop aiding Soviet fascism
well you told us a moment ago why you
left the system I'd like to hear the
details of how you did it it must've
been a very dangerous thing it was not
so dangerous it was crazy first of all
because defecting in India is virtually
impossible thanks to very strong
pressure from the Soviet government
excuse me you were in Indian on
assignment and yes I was working for the
Soviet embassy in New Delhi as a press
officer and defecting for a Soviet
diplomat is next to impossible it's a
suicide as I said because a great friend
Indira Gandhi pushed a law through
Parliament which says and I quote no
defector from any country has a right of
political asylum in any embassy on the
territory of Indian Republic which is a
masterpiece of hypocrisy no other
defector but the Soviet one needs a
political asylum so knowing that
perfectly well I I planned a craziest
possible way to defect
I studied country culture in India there
are there were thousands of young
American boys and girls with no shoes
long hair smoking hash and marijuana
studying sometimes Indian philosophy
sometimes simply pretending that they
study and they greatly annoyed Indian
police and they were laughingstock of
Indians because obviously they they were
good-for-nothing students
I started carefully where they
congregate what roots they travel what
language they speak what do they smoke
and one day I simply joined a group of
hippies to avoid detection of Indian
police I was dressed as a typical hippie
bluejeans long come his shirts with all
kind of nice decorations like beads long
hairs I I bought a wig because for
several weeks I had to turn myself from
a conservative Soviet diplomat into a
very progressive American hippie and
that was the only way that that I could
avoid detection it was very interesting
experience but it was necessary because
from my own knowledge as a member of
Soviet embassy staff I knew that there
were many cases when Soviet defectors
were betrayed by Indian police and also
some Western embassies played a very
dirty role in betraying the Soviet
defectors according to all information
they were some I wouldn't call them
double agents but simply immoral people
working for this for the United States
embassy and confining in in people like
this would be a suicide so I had to be
extremely careful I could not trust
anyone and that was the that was the
reason for such a crazy way to defect
well had you been caught in the act of
trying to get out what would have
happened to you Oh most likely I would
end up in in concentration camp or
depending on the situation and on the
whim of some bureaucrat and KGB or maybe
even executed because this is normal
practice quietly of course not publicly
but that would be the end of my
defection of course well when did you
finally make it to the United States in
1970 after about six months of
debriefing in Athens by the CIA and I
presume FBI too they let me go first to
Germany then to Canada that was my
decision I had to change my identity to
protect my family and my friends in USSR
and also I was little bit paranoid
knowing that both Soviet KGB and
probably some double agents with an
American system may be after me so I
wanted to settle down as far away as
possible
I requested CIA to give me some kind of
new identity and just let me go on my
own
and I settled in Canada I was a student
I changed many professions from farm
help and laundry truck driver to
instruct language instructor and
broadcaster for Canadian Broadcasting
Corporation's in Montreal or have you
had any threats on your life or any yes
in about five years KGB eventually
discovered the time working for Canadian
Broadcasting scene I made a very big
mistake
I started talking I started working for
overseas service of CBC which is similar
to Voice of America in Russian language
and of course monitoring service in USSR
picked up every new voice every new
announcer would they would make it a
point to discover who he is and then
five years sure enough slowly but surely
they discovered that I am NOT Thomas
Schumann the time Yuri Alexandrovich
bismi enough and the time working for
Canadian Broadcasting and undermining
beautiful the tongue between Canada and
USSR and the Soviet ambassador Alexander
Yakovlev I made it his personal effort
to discredit me he complained to Pierre
Trudeau who is known to be a little bit
soft and socialism and the management of
CBC behaved in a very strange cowardly
way unbecoming to representatives of an
independent country like Canada they
listened to every suggestion that Soviet
ambassador gave and they started
shameful investigation analyzing content
of my broadcasts to USSR
sure enough they discovered that some of
my statements were probably too with the
offending to the Soviet Politburo so I
had to leave my job and of course subtle
intimidations they would say something
like please cross the street carefully
because you know traffic is very heavy
in Quebec and fortunately I know about
the psychology and the logic of activity
of the KGB and I never allowed myself to
be intimidated this is the word thing
this is what they expect a person a
defector to be intimidated once they
spot that you are scared they keep on
developing that line and then eventually
you either have to give up entirely and
and and work for them or you they
neutralize you that they would
definitely stop all kind of political
activity which they fail to do in my
case because I was turbine Li working
for the Canadian Broadcasting and in
response to they intimidations I said
that look this is a free country and I
am as free as you are and I also can
drive very fast and gun control is not
yet established in Canada so I had a
couple of good shotguns in my basement
so welcome to visit me someday
with your Kalashnikov machine guns so
obviously it didn't work intimidation
didn't work so they they tried different
approach as I described the approach on
the highest level
on the level of Canadian bureaucracy and
that level they on that level they were
successful on individual level they
failed flat mr. Boozman off has brought
a series of slides with him that he has
taken from the Soviet Union and I think
this is a good time to take a look at
the slides now the viewers will be able
to see these slices as we talk about
them yes this is a collection of slides
which are some of them are snapshots
from my family album some of them are
documents which I smuggled from the
Soviet embassy and some are referred
actions from local mass media I usually
show them to establish my credibility as
a defector this is a picture of my
native town mateship about 20 miles not
from Moscow
characteristically there is a statue of
comrade Lenin in the central square this
is myself at the age of 7 again
characteristically and the statue of
Comrade Stalin extending his friendly
hand to peoples of the world at that age
of course I was still idealistically
minded young communist and I still
believe that sooner or later things will
go for better but I realized that the
system stinks that something is fishy
and that ideology is is fake and the
propaganda about an advanced Soviet
agriculture simply didn't meet the
criteria of reality if they talk about
abundance of food and there is none in
the stores it must be something wrong
my father was he is on the left here my
father was officer of the General Staff
of the Soviet Army he was inspector of
land forces Soviet troops stationed in
countries like Mongolia Cuba East
European countries were he alive today
most likely he would be inspecting
Soviet troops in Nicaragua Angola and
many other parts of the world
fortunately he died and he didn't see
the disgrace because deep inside he was
Russian patriot he didn't bomb he didn't
like the idea of expanding Soviet
military might especially in the areas
where we were not welcomed at all unlike
many other military officers he was
reporting directly to the Minister of
Defense bypassing KGB and diplomatic
service in other words he was a trusted
military professional and my impression
that this type of people are much less
hawkish and adventurous tting than party
bureaucrats in kremlin when american
mass media describes soviet military as
potentially dangerous counterpart for
pentagon i simply laughed because i know
better i know that the most dangerous
part of the soviet power
structures are not military at all most
likely if they come to power in my
country they'll be more sensible
negotiators for nuclear disarmament and
withdrawal of the Soviet troops from
many parts of the world but if someone
from the party structure or the KGB
structure were to give the orders for
motivation to obey as follows they're
there they're professional military but
they you see the triangle of power and
hate in USSR is the party at the top the
party elite the oligarchy of the party
then the military and the KGB at the
bottom they hate each other and the most
hated triangle the most hated corner of
the triangle is the Communist Party
bureaucrats they are the most
adventurous t'k sanaya megalomaniacs
they can start war I wouldn't be
surprised not the military they know
what war is at least my father did this
is the picture taken at the entrance of
my Institute of Oriental languages it's
a part of Moscow State University I
graduated in 1963 and I excuse me which
one were you on I am on the right here
on the right and on the left is my
colleague my schoolmate Vadim Smirnoff
who later was a apparatchik than the
Central Committee of the Soviet Union
Communist Party what is an apparatchik
it's it's a it's a function is something
like civil service in British Empire
some someone who is never fired from
from the service he stays there
internally he may not be promoted to
high but he is a dependable bureaucrat
who will stay forever I started not only
languages but also history literature in
even music I'm on this picture I'm
trying to learn how to play musical in
Indian musical instrument I haven't
tried to look like an Indian when I was
second years - not bad yes and the
actually it was strongly encouraged by
the by the instructors in my school
because this the graduates of my school
were later on employed as diplomats
foreign journalists or spies as every
Soviet student I
quote-unquote volunteering for
harvesting grain in Kazakhstan this is a
biggest agricultural blunder of the
Soviet government but I didn't have much
choice of course because the Communist
motto borrowed from the Bible says those
who do not work shall not eat and you
can see me eating therefore I was
working and you can see how happy I was
about it I went through a very extensive
physical and military training including
the manure and including the military
games in areas suburban areas of Moscow
and here for example we are on the tour
in our hankins area and by the end of my
training in school I was recruited by
the KGB this picture was taken on that
day and you can see again how happy it
feels to be recruited by the KGB our
conversation with Yuri Alexandrovich
basmanov who is a defector from the
Soviet Union a former propaganda agent
or novice D and the KGB will continue
after this message
[Music]
all right as every student in USSR I
went through very extensive physical and
military training and Civil Defence
training - unlike in United States
where civil defense is virtually
non-existent zero in USSR every student
whatever is major subject has to go
through very extensive four-year
military and civil defence training you
can see me here with a group of students
during one of the war games in near
Moscow the main idea of course is to
prepare a huge reserve army of the USSR
each student has to graduate as a junior
Lefton and in my case it was
administrative and military intelligence
service my first assignment was to India
as a translator with the Soviet
economical aid group building refinery
complexes in the heart State and which
are at stake at the time I was still
naively idealistically believing that
what I was doing contributes to the
understanding and cooperation between
the nations it took me quite a number of
years to realize that what we were
bringing to India was a new type of
colonialism thousand times more
oppressive and exploitative than any
colonialism or imperialism in history of
mankind but at that time I was still
hoping that well maybe it's not that bad
could be worse and things may go for
better and I even tried to implement the
beautiful Marxist motto proletarians of
all the countries unite I tried to unite
with the nice indian girl and I was
actually I was fascinated by Indian
culture by by the family life in in this
country but obviously Communist Party
had different plans for my genes so I
had to marry this beautiful Russian girl
in the span of my career I married three
times
most of these marriages were marriages
of convenience on advice from the
Department of Personnel this is normal
practice in USSR when the Soviet citizen
is assigned to a foreign job
he has to be married either to keep
family in USSR as hostages or if it's a
convenience marriage like mine so that
the husband and wife are virtually
informers on each other to prevent
defection or contamination by decadent
imperialist or capitalist ideas in my
case I hated that girl so much that the
moment I landed in Moscow we we were
divorced and I I married late a second
time by the end of my first assignment
in India I was promoted to the position
of a public relations officer you can
see me here translating a speech by a
Soviet boss and on the right I am on the
right here yes and it was the occasion
was commissioning of the refinery
complex in Bihar Bharani back in Moscow
I was immediately recruited by novice
tea press agency which is a propaganda
and ideological subversion front for the
KGB 75% of the members of the novice tea
are commissioned officers of the KGB the
other 25 are like myself co-opted and
agents who are assigned to specific
operations in this particular case you
can see me talking to students of
Lumumba Friendship University in Moscow
and this is the universe cooled under
the direct control of the KGB and
Central Committee where future leaders
of the so-called national liberation
movements are being educated and
selected carefully and some of them have
absolutely they ignited this for example
is a group of students from the moment
they don't look like students at all
they look more like military and that's
exactly what they were they were
dispatched back to their countries to be
leaders of the so-called national
liberation movements or to be translated
into normal human language leaders of
international terrorist groups another
area of activity when I was working for
the novice team was to accompany groups
of so-called progressive intellectuals
writers journalists publishers
teachers professors of colleges you can
see me here in Kremlin I'm second on the
left with a group of Pakistani and
Indian intellectuals most of them
pretend that they don't understand that
we are actually working on behalf of the
Soviet government and the KGB they
pretended that they are actually being
guests a VIP intellectuals that they are
treated according to their merits and
and their intellectual abilities for us
they were just a bunch of political
prostitutes to be taken advantage for
various propaganda operations therefore
you can see perfectly well they senior
colleague of mine on the Left doesn't
really have that much respect on his
face and myself with a very skeptical
smile typical KGB sarcastic smile
anticipating another victim of
ideological brainwashing this is how a
typical conference in novice tea
headquarters in Moscow look likes
sitting in the middle is boris butakov
the then director of norms depress
agency high-ranking party bureaucrat in
the Department of propaganda I am
standing next to a famous Indian poet
Sumitra London punt he was famous
because he was an author he was the
author of the famous poem titled
Rhapsody to Lenin that's why he was
invited to USSR and everything was paid
then by the Soviet government the pay
special attention to number of bottles
on the table this is one of the ways to
kill the awareness or curiosity of the
foreign journalists my one of my
functions was to keep foreign guests
permanently intoxicated the moment they
land at Moscow Airport I had to take
them to the VIP launch and toast to
friendship and understanding within the
nations of the world glass of vodka then
the second glass of vodka and in no time
my guests would be feeling very happy
they would see everything in kind of
pink nice color and that's the way I
I had to keep them permanently for the
next 15 or 20 days at certain point in
time I had to withdraw alcohol from them
so that some of them were the most
recruitable would feel a little bit
shaky guilty trying to remember what
they were talking last night that's the
time to approach them with all kind of
nonsense such as joint communique or
statement for Soviet propaganda that's
the time they aren't the most flexible
and of course what they didn't
understand they didn't realize who
pretended not to realize that myself who
was drinking together with them
was not drinking at all I had ways to
get rid of alcohol through various
techniques including special pills which
were given to me by my colleagues but
they were taking it seriously in other
words they they they would consume quite
large volumes of alcohol and feel quite
uneasy next morning in 1967 the KGB
attached me to this magazine Look
magazine a group of 12 people arrived to
USSR from United States to cover the
50th anniversary of October socialist
revolution in my country from the first
page to the last page it was a package
of lies propaganda cliche which were
presented to American readers as
opinions and deductions of American
journalists nothing could be far from
truth this were not opinions they were
not opinions at all they were the
cliches which the Soviet propaganda
wants American public to think that they
think if it does make any sense at all
it sure does because from the viewpoint
of the Soviet propaganda although there
are some subtle criticism of the Soviet
system the basic message is that Russia
today is a nice functioning efficient
system supported by majority of
population that's the biggest lie
and of course American intellectuals and
journalists from Luke magazine
elaborated on that untruth in various
different ways
they intellectualize that lie they found
all kind of justification
for telling lies to American public this
is assuming it was partly your job to
make sure that they got these ideas yes
accepted them as their own idea right
actually even before they arrive to USSR
and they paid astronomical sum of money
for that visit they were submitted that
this novice oppressed agency developed
so-called backgrounders 20 25 pages of
information and opinions which were
presented to the journalists even before
they bought their tickets to Moscow they
had to analyze the situation and judging
on their reaction to that background the
local novice the representative or local
Soviet diplomat in Washington DC would
assess whether they have whether they'd
be given visa to USSR or not so they
were selected oh yes they were they were
pre-selected very carefully and there is
not much chance for honest journalists
to arrive to USSR and to stay there for
one year and to bring this package of
lies back home this for example is a
centerfold of the tide of the Look
magazine they presented this monument
erected by Communist Party in Stalingrad
as the symbol personification of Russian
military might and they said in the
article which is published on on the
side that Soviets are very proud of the
victory in the Second World War this is
another big myth a lie no sensible
people would be proud to lose 20
millions of their countrymen in the war
which was started by Ginoza Hitler and
Comrade Stalin and paid by American
multinationals most of the Soviet
citizens look at this type of monuments
with disgust and sorrow because every
family lost father brother sister or
child in the Second World War yet
American journalists who were trying to
appease to please their hosts presented
this picture on the centerfold as the
symbol and personification of Soviet
national they call it Russian national
spirit and it was greatest greatest
misconception and in a very tragic miss
and
standing of course Luke magazine was not
distributed in USSR the main audience
was in the United States but I presume
that many Americans millions of
Americans who were reading Look magazine
at that time had absolutely wrong idea
about the sentiments of my nation about
what the Soviets are proud of and what
they hate this is a group you see the
same lady with this ward in Stalingrad
this is the group of journalists myself
is in the center with the same devilish
smile and mr. Philip Harrington is on
the extreme left there with his camera
this is the gentleman which was so deaf
were so uninterested in what I had to
say to him this is the same picture a
blow-up of the same of the same picture
many many guests from various countries
in this particular case from Asia and
Africa were taken by me as a novice to
press agency employee for a tour across
Siberia for example we would show them
typical kindergarten you see nothing
special by American standards just nice
children sitting eating their breakfast
or lunch what they could not understand
or they pretended not to understand that
this is an exemplary kindergarten this
is not the kindergarten for average
person or every family in USSR and we
maintained that illusion in their minds
you can see myself under the red spot in
the middle there with the same
businesslike expression iemon you know
I'm doing my job that that's what I am
assigned to do and that's what I was
paid to do but deep inside I still hope
that at least some of these useful
idiots would understand that what they
are looking at has nothing to do with
the level of affluence in my nation this
is a better picture which reflects the
true spirit of of the Soviet Soviet
childhood this picture was printed in a
Canadian government publication by
mistake
in the middle you can see children
playing on a small courtyard and the
caption goes
this is a typical kindergarten in
Siberia what this idiots didn't
understand that it is not kindergarten
at all
it is a prison for children of political
prisoners but there was not a single
mentioning that what they were visiting
actually was an area of concentration
camps and the job of people like myself
to help them to me not to notice that
they are actually talking to prisoners
most of the children were dressed
especially on the occasion of the
foreigners visit the of course there
were no corpses and on the ground there
were no machine-gun guards and the well
it looks not very pleasant as you see it
so it looks dull but obviously it does
not create an impression that this is
actually a prison well did any of the
journalists have the curiosity to ask
about prisons and that kind of in
Siberia yes is what you saw yes some of
them ask questions and naturally we
would give them for the stupid question
we give them stupid answer no there are
no prisons in Siberia no most of the
people who will you see our free
citizens of USSR they are very happy to
be here and they are contributing to the
glory of the socialist system some of
them pretended that they believed what
what I was telling them and most of them
we may discuss it later what are the
motivations of these people why would
they stubbornly bring lies to their own
population through their own mass media
I have various answers to this there is
not a single explanation it's a complex
of explanations it's fear pure
biological fear they understand that
they are on the territory of an enemy
state a police state and just to save
their rotten skins and their miserable
jobs their affluence back home they
would prefer to tell a lie than to ask
truthful questions and report truthful
information second most of these
Schmucks were afraid to lose their jobs
because obviously if you tell truth
about my country you will not last long
as
correspondent of New York Times or Los
Angeles Times they will fire you
what kind of correspondent are you you
obviously cannot find common language
with Russians if they kick you out in 24
hours so just by by trying to be confirm
this to their own editorial bosses they
tried not to offend the sentiments of
the Soviet administrators and people
like myself deep inside I hope they
would insult my or offend by sentiments
obviously they preferred not to another
reason I did I refuse to believe it but
obviously there is another reason
obviously it's agreed these people earn
a lot of money when they come back to
USA they claim that they are experts in
my country they write books which sells
a million copies title like Russians the
truth about Russia
most of it is lie about Russia yet they
claim to be Soviet ologists they they
break they play back myth about my
country the propaganda cliches yet they
stubbornly resisted the word of truth if
a person like Solzhenitsyn is either
defecting or kicked out of USSR
they try all their best to this to
discredit him and to discourage him I
don't have much chance to appear on
national network with the true story
about my country but the useful eejit
like Hendrik Smith or Robert Kaiser they
are big heroes they come back from USSR
they say all we were talking to
dissidents in Russia big deal
so the distance a chasing American
correspondents in the streets and they
are cowardly escaping from this context
for some strange reason if you want to
know more about Spain you refer to
Spanish writers if you want to learn
more about French you read French or
writers even about Antarctica I bet you
would rip in Queens only about the
Soviet Union for some strange reason you
read Hendrix and Schmendrick sand all
kind of Kissinger's because they claim
that they know more about my country
they know nothing or next to nothing
oh they pretend that they know more
than they actually do I would say they
are dishonest people who lack integrity
and common sense and intellectual
honesty they bring back all kind of
stories like that a kindergarten in
Siberia a meeting the most important
fact it's a prison
for children of political prisoners
another greatest example of monumental
idiocy of American politicians Edward
Kennedy was in Moscow and he thought
that he is a popular charismatic
American politician who is easygoing who
can smile dance at the wedding in in
Russian palace of marriages what he done
what he did not understand or maybe he
pretended not to understand that
actually he was being taken for a ride
this is a staged wedding especially to
impress foreign media or or useful
idiots like Ed Kennedy
most of the of the guests there they had
security clearance and they were
instructed what to say to foreigners
this is exactly what I was doing you can
see me in the same damn wedding palace
in Moscow where F Kennedy was dancing
here is he smiling he thinks he is very
smart from the viewpoint of Russian
citizens who observed this idiocy he is
his narrow-minded ego centrical idiot
who tries to earn his own popularity
through the through participation in
propaganda Fox is like this here you can
see myself on the right again exemplary
Soviet bride on the left three
journalists from various countries Asia
Africa and Latin America obviously they
enjoying the situation they they will go
back home and write the reports we were
present in the on the regular Soviet
wedding they were not present on a
regular Soviet reading they were present
they were part of a farce of a circus
performance another thing which I had to
sometimes risking my life to explain to
foreigners Prime magazine for example is
very critical of South African racist
regime the whole article was dedicated
to the shameful internal passport system
where black blacks are not allowing to
live with whites for some strange reason
for the last fourteen years since my
defection nobody wanted to pay attention
to my passport this is my passport
it also shows my nationality and it has
a police rubber stamp which is called
prat Pisgah in Russian language which
assigns me to a certain area of
residence I cannot leave that area same
way as this black man cannot leave the
area in South Africa yet we call South
African government racist regime not a
single Jane Jane Fonda or Fonda is brave
enough courageous enough to come to
mediate and say look this is what
happens in u.s. a song I send a copy of
my passport to many American liberals
and civil rights defenders and all the
other useful idiots they never they
never bothered to answer me back this
shows what kind of integrity what kind
of honesty these people are they are a
bunch of hypocrites because they don't
want to recognize a good example of
races in my country this is the first
stage of befriending a professor you can
see myself on the left with the same
James Bond smile on my on the right is
my KGB supervisor comrade Leonid metro
Keon and in the middle a professor of
political science in Delhi University
the next stage would be to invite him to
a gathering of in the Soviet Friendship
Society there he is sitting next to his
wife before he is being sent to USSR for
free trip everything is paid by the
Soviet government he was made to believe
that he is invited to USSR because he is
a talented sober thinking intellectual
absolutely false he is invited because
he is a useful idiot because he would
agree and subscribe to most of the
Soviet propaganda cliche and when he is
coming back to his own country he is
going for years and years to teach the
beauties of Soviet socialism to newer
and newer generations
students thus promoting the Soviet
propaganda line the KGB was even curious
about this gentleman it may look
innocent Maharishi Mahesh Yogi a great
spiritual leader or maybe a great
charlatan and crook depending on which
from which side you are looking at him
beetles were trained at his ashram in
hardware in India how to meditate mia
farrow and other useful idiots from
Hollywood visited his school and they
returned back to the United States
absolutely stoned out of their minds
with marijuana hashish and crazy ideas
of meditation to meditate in other words
to isolate oneself from the current
social and political issues of your own
country to get into your own bubble to
forget about troubles of the world
obviously KGB was very fascinated with
such a beautiful school such a
brainwashing center for stupid Americans
I was dispatched by the KGB to check
what kind of VIP Americans attend this
school that's you analyzed yes I am on
the left I was trying to get enrolled in
that school unfortunately the Maharishi
Mahesh Yogi asked too much he wanted 500
American dollars for enrollment but my
function was not actually to get
enrolled in the school my function was
to discover what kind of people from
United States attend this school and we
discovered that yes there are some
influential members of family public
opinion makers of United States who come
back with the crazy stories about Indian
philosophy Indians themselves look up
upon them as idiots useful idiots to say
nothing about KGB who looked at them as
as as extremely naive misguided people
obviously a VIP say a wife of a
congressman or or a prominent Hollywood
personality after the after being
trained in that school is much more
instrumental in the hands of
manipulators of public opinion
KGB then a normal person who who
understands who looks through this is
sure this this type of fake religious
training now why would they be more
susceptible to manipulation I just
mentioned that because you see a person
who is too much involved in in
introspective meditation you see if you
carefully look what what Maharishi
Mahesh Yogi is teaching to to Americans
is that all most of the problems most of
the burning issues of today can be
solved simply by meditating don't don't
don't rock the boat don't get involved
just sit down look at your navel and
meditate and the things due to some
strange logic due to cosmic vibration
will settle down by themselves this is
exactly what the KGB and Marxist
Leninist propaganda ones from Americans
to distract their opinion attention and
mental energy from real issues of United
States into an on issues into a known
world non existent harmony obviously
it's more beneficial for the Soviet
aggressors to have a bunch of duped
Americans than Americans who are
self-conscious healthy physically fit
and alert to the reality Maharishi
Mahesh Yogi obviously is not on the
payroll of the KGB but whether he knows
it or not he contributes greatly to
generalization of American society and
he is not the only one there are
hundreds of those gurus who come to you
to your country to capitalize on naivete
and stupidity of Americans it's a
fashion it's a fashion to meditate it's
a fashion not to be involved so
obviously you can see that if KGB were
that curious if they paid my trip to
Harvard if they assigned me to that to
that strange job obviously they were
very much fascinated they were convinced
that that type of brainwashing is very
efficient and instrumental in the more
the United States our conversation with
Yuri Alexandrovich Esme INAF who is a
defector from the Soviet Union a form of
propaganda agent for novice D and KGB
will continue after this message
[Music]
this picture shows the part of the
building of USSR embassy and my
supervisors on the left is comrade McGee
an Indian communist and on the right
comrade Metro him my supervisors in the
secret Department of research and
counter-propaganda it has nothing to do
with either research or country
propaganda most of the activity of the
department was to compile huge ammount
volume of information on individuals who
were instrumental in creating public
opinion publishers editors journalists
actors educationalists professors of
political science members of parliament
representatives of business circles most
of these people were divided roughly
into groups those who would toe the
Soviet foreign policy they would be
promoted to the positions of power
through media and public opinion
manipulation those who refused the
Soviet influence in their own country
would be character assassinated or
executed physically come revolution same
way as in a small town of Heuer in south
vietnam several thousands of Vietnamese
were executed in one night when the city
was captured by the Vietcong for only
two days an American CIA could never
figure out how could possibly communists
know each individual where he lives
where where to get him and would be
arrested in one night
basically in some four hours before dawn
put on a van taken out of the city
limits and shot the answer is very
simple
long before communists occupied the city
there was extensive network of informers
local Vietnamese citizens who knew
absolutely everything about people who
are instrumental in public opinion
including barbers and taxi drivers
everyone who is sympathetic to the
United States was executed same thing
was done under the guidance of the
Soviet embassy in Hanoi and same thing I
was doing in New Delhi to my horror I
discovered that in the files where
people were doomed to execution there
were names of pro-soviet journalists
with whom I was personally
friendly pressure of you yes they were
idealistically minded leftists who made
several visits to USSR and yet the KGB
decided that come revolution or drastic
changes in political structure of India
they will have to go wise not because
they know too much
simply because you see the useful idiots
the the leftists who are idealistic aliy
believing in the beauty of soviet
socialist or communist or whatever
system when they get disillusioned they
become the worst enemies that's why my
KGB instructors specifically made a
point never bother with leftists forget
about these political prostitutes aim
higher this was my instruction try to
get into into large circulation
established conservative media reach
filthy rich movie makers intellectuals
so-called academic circles cynical
egocentric people who can look into your
eyes with angelic expression and tell
you a lie this are the most recruitable
people people who lack moral principles
who are either too greedy or to suffer
from self-importance
they feel that they they matter a lot
these are the people who KGB wanted very
much to recruit but to eliminate the
others to execute the others don't they
serve some purpose wouldn't they be not
one they realize they serve purpose only
at the stage of destabilization of a
nation for example your leftists in
United States all these professors and
all this beautiful civil rights
defenders they are instrumental in the
process of the of the subversion only to
destabilize the nation when their job is
completed they are known they are not
needed anymore
they know too much some of them when
they get disillusioned when they see
that Marxist Leninist come to power
obviously they get offended they think
that they will come to power that will
never happen of course they will be
lined up against the wall and shot but
they may turn into the most bitter
enemies of Marxist Leninist when they
come to power and that's what happened
in Nicaragua you remember most of this
former Marx
Leninist word either put to prison or
one of them split and now he is working
again Sandinistas it happened in Granada
when Maurice Bishop was he was already a
Marxist he was executed by a new Marxist
who was more Marxist than this Marxist
same happen in Afghanistan when first
there was Taraki he was killed by I mean
then I mean was killed by babrak karmal
with the help of KGB same happen in him
in Bangladesh when Mujibur Rahman very
Pro Soviet leftist was assassinated by
his own Marxist Leninist
military comrades it's the same pattern
everywhere the moment they serve their
purpose all the useful idiots are used
either be executed entirely all the
idealistic reminded Marxist or were
exiled or put in prisons like in Cuba
many many former Marxists are in Cuba I
mean in prison so most of the Indians
who were cooperating with the Soviets
especially without the Department of
Information of the USSR embassy were
listed for execution and when I
discovered that fact of course I was
sick I was mentally and physically sick
I thought the time I'm going to explode
one day during the briefing at the
ambassador's office I would stand up and
say something that we are basically a
bunch of murderers that's what we are we
there's nothing to do with friendship
and understanding between the nation and
bla bla bla we're murderers we behave as
a bunch of thugs in the country which
which is hospitable to us a country
which which with ancient traditions but
I I did not the fact I tried to get the
message across to my horror
nobody wanted even to listen least of
all to believe what I had to say and I
tried all kinds of tricks I would I
would I would leak information through
letters or lost documents or something
like that and still I got no message the
message was not published even in the
conservative mass media of India the
immediate impulse to defect was
Bangladesh crisis which was described by
American correspondents as Islamic
grassroot revolution
which is absolute baloney there was
nothing to do with Islam and there was
no grassroot revolution actually there
are no grassroot revolutions period any
revolution is a byproduct of a highly
organized group of conscientious and
professional organizers but there's
nothing to do with grassroot in
Bangladesh it was nothing with
grassroots most of the Avani League
party members of a mulignans People's
Party were trained in Moscow in the high
party school most of the Mukti Fauj
leaders Mukti forages in Benghazi means
People's Army same as SWAPO and and all
kind of Liberation Army's all over the
world the same bunch of useful idiots
they were trained at Lumumba University
and various centres of the KGB in
Simferopol in in Crimea and in Tashkent
so when I saw that India Indian
territory is being used as a jumping
board to destroy East Pakistan
I saw myself thousands of so-called
students traveling through India to East
Pakistan through the territory of India
and Indian government pretended not to
see what was going on they knew
perfectly well the Indian pollutin knew
it the intelligence Department of Indian
government knew it the KGB of course
knew it and the CIA knew it that that
was most infuriating because when I
defected and I explained to the CIA
debriefers they should watch out because
East Pakistan is going to erupt any
moment they said that I was look I was
reading to too many James Bond novels
anyway so East Pakistan was doomed one
of my colleagues in in the Soviet
consulate in Calcutta when he was dead
drunk he ventured into the basement to
relieve himself and he found the big
boxes which said printed matter to Dhaka
University Dhaka is the capital of East
Pakistan and since he was drunk and
curious he opened one of the boxes and
he discovered not printed metric he
discovered Kalashnikov guns and
ammunition in there anyway it's a long
story when I saw the preparations for
the for the invasion into East Pakistan
obviously I wanted to defect immediate
the only thing I couldn't I couldn't at
that time and make up my mind when and
where and how one of the reasons of
course you see I was in love with the
India I mentioned it before I spoke the
languages I socialized with people and I
understood that I had to act fast unless
I want this beautiful country to be
permanently and irreparably damaged by
our presence one of the reasons not to
defect was as you can see I was living
in relative affluence who the hell in
the normal mind would defect and do what
to be abused by your media to be called
McCarthy stand fascist and paranoid or
to drive attacks in New York City what
for what they have for should I defect
to be abused by Americans to be insulted
in exchange for my effort to bring the
truthful information about impending
danger subversion as you can see I was
living in quite the comfortable
conditions next to swimming pool where
Indians were not allowed by the way I
was highly paid expert in propaganda I
had my family I was respected by my
nation my career was cloudless the third
reason how to defect with the family to
the fact that the baby and the wife
would be virtual suicide because
according to law that hypocritical law
which I quoted before the Indian police
will have to hand me over back to the
KGB and that will be the end of my
defection and probably my life again i
cannot smuggle my wife because she was
not quite sure what what i was doing she
was not that idealistically involved and
she was definitely not in in the total
picture what I was doing for the KGB she
would be shocked if I if I you know put
her in my van and drive her to your
American Embassy or elsewhere that would
be a greatest danger so again I had to
defect in such a way that my defection
would look as simple disappearance and
there were many cases like that when the
Soviet agent simply disappeared either
killed in action or thanks to their
curiosity and there
close contacts with radical some of them
were killed by the Marxists by the way
it happened in many African countries
when the Soviet KGB were killed by
Africans themselves not because they
hated Marxist Leninist but because they
were simply trigger-happy bunch of
unruly characters if you give them
machine gun they will shoot and some of
the Soviets obviously were not careful
enough to protect themselves and they
got into embarrassing situations when
they were shot at the crossfire between
factions of so-called liberation
movements anyway so I I decided as I
said to study the counterculture I
decided this probably would be the best
way to disappear I socialized the
characters like this on the left you see
is a barefoot American hippie it took me
quite a long time to study exactly what
they were doing and how to mix with them
but eventually I did most of Indian
newspapers carried my picture and
promise of 2,000 rupees for information
about my whereabouts but they were
looking for wrong person because they
obviously tried to stop a young Soviet
diplomat in white shirt and tie and this
is how I looked at the time of defection
nobody could possibly think that the
Soviet diplomat would be as crazy as to
join a bunch of hippies that's you right
yes Travel Indian small cars so I made
it literally is almost like a Hollywood
style detective story from under the
nose of the KGB in Bombay Airport I
landed the plane and I flew to Greece
where I was debriefed by the CIA that's
basically most that's all for my day we
can slice we can turn off the projectors
and that's very interesting
well you spoke several times before
about ideological subversion that is a
phrase that I'm afraid some Americans
don't fully understand when the Soviets
used the phrase ideological subversion
what do they mean by ideological
subversion is is the process which is
legitimate overt and open you can see it
with your own eyes all you have to do
American mass media has to do is to
unplug their bananas from the ears open
up their eyes and they can see it there
is no mystery there is nothing to do
with espionage I know that espionage
intelligence-gathering looks more
romantic it sells more deodorants
through their advertising probably
that's why your Hollywood producers are
so crazy about James Bond type of three
words but in reality the main emphasis
of the KGB is not in the area of it
intelligence at all according to my
opinion and opinion of many defectors of
my caliber only about 15% of time money
and manpower is spent on espionage as
such the other 85% is a slow process
which we call either ideological
subversion or active measures actively
Mariotti in the language of the KGB or
psychological warfare what it basically
means is to change the perception of
reality of every American to such an
extent that despite of the abundance of
information no one is able to come to
sensible conclusions in the interests of
defending themselves their families
their community and their country it's a
great brainwashing process which goes
very slow and it's divided in four basic
stages the first one being
demoralisation it takes from 15 to 20
years to demoralize a nation why that
many years because this is the minimum
number of years which requires to
educate one generation of students in
the country of your enemy exposed to the
ideology of the enemy in other words
Marxism Leninism ideology is being
pumped into the soft heads of at least
three generations of American students
without being challenged or
counterbalanced by the basic values of
Americanism American patriotism the
result the result you can see most of
the people who graduated in sixties drop
outs or half-baked intellectuals are now
occupying the positions of power in the
govern
civil service business mass media
educational system you are stuck with
them you cannot get rid of them they are
contaminated they are programmed to
think and react to certain stimuli in a
certain pattern you cannot change their
mind even if you expose them to
authentic information even if you prove
that white is white and black is black
you still cannot change the basic
perception and the logic of behavior in
other words these people the process of
demoralization is complete and
irreversible to get rid society of these
people you have you need another 20 or
15 years to educate a new generation of
patriotically minded and and and common
common sense people who would be acting
in favor and in the interests of the
United States society and yet these
people have been programmed and as you
say in place when you are favourable to
an opening with the Soviet concept these
are the very people who would be marked
for extermination in this case most of
them yes simply because the
psychological shock when when they will
see in future what they what the
beautiful Society of equality and social
justice means in practice obviously they
will revolt they will there will be very
unhappy frustrated people and the
Marxist Leninist regime does not
tolerate these people they obviously
they will join the links of dissenters
dissidents unlike in present United
States there will be no place for
dissent in future Marxist Leninist
America here you can you can get popular
like Daniel Ellsberg and filthy rich
like Jane Fonda for being dissident for
criticizing your Pentagon in future
these people will be simply squashed
like cockroaches nobody is going to pay
them nothing for their beautiful noble
ideas of equality this they don't
understand and it will be greatest shock
for them of course the demoralization
process in the United States is based
we completed already for the last 25
years actually it's over fulfilled
because demoralization now reaches such
areas where previously not even comrade
and drop of and all his experts would
would even dream of such a tremendous
success most of it is done by Americans
to Americans
thanks to lack of moral standards as I
mentioned before exposure to true
information does not matter anymore a
person who was demoralized is unable to
assess true information the facts tell
nothing to him even if I shower him with
information with the authentic proof
with documents the pictures even if I
take him by force to the Soviet Union
and show him concentration camp he will
refuse to believe it until he is going
to receive a kick in the in his fat
bottom when the military booth crashes
his balls then he will understand but
not before that that's the tragic of the
situation of demoralisation so basically
America is stuck with with
demoralisation and unless even if you
start right now here this minute you
start educating new generation of
American it will still take you 15 to 20
years to turn the tide of ideological
perception of reality back to normal
normalcy and and patriotism the next
stage is destabilization this time
subvert our does not care about your
ideas and the patterns of your
consumption whether you eat junk food
and get fat and flabby it doesn't matter
anymore this time and it takes only from
two to five years to disturb you lies a
nation it's but what what matters is
essentials economy Foreign Relations
defense systems and you can see it quite
clearly that's in some areas in such
sensitive areas as defense and economy
the influence of Marxist Leninist ideas
in the United States is absolutely
fantastic I could never believe it 14
years ago when I landed in this part of
the world
that the process will go that fast the
next stage of course is crisis it may
take only up to six weeks to to bring a
country to the verge of crisis you can
see it in in Central America now and
after crisis with a violent change of
power structure and economy you have
so-called the period of normalization it
may last indefinitely normalization is a
cynical expression borrowed from Soviet
propaganda when the Soviet tanks moved
into Czechoslovakia in 68 comrade
Brezhnev said now the situation in
brotherly Czechoslovakia is normalized
this is what will happen in the United
States if you allow all the Schmucks to
bring the country to crisis to promise
people all kinds of goodies and the
paradise on earth - to destabilize your
economy to eliminate the principle of
free market competition and to put a Big
Brother government in Washington DC with
the benevolent dictators like Walter
Mondale who will promise lots of things
never mind whether the promises are
fulfilled will or not he will go to
Moscow to kiss the bottoms of new
generation of Soviet assassins never
mind he will create false illusions that
the situation is under control situation
is not under control situation is
disgustingly out of control most of the
American politicians media and
educational system trains and not a
generation of people who think they are
living at the peace time false United
States is in the state of war undeclared
total war against the basic principles
and the foundations of this system and
and the initiator of this war is not
comrade Andropov of course it's it's the
system however ridiculous it may sound
the world communist system or the world
communist conspiracy where they scare
some people or not I don't give a hoot
if you are not scared by now nothing can
scare you but you don't have to be
paranoid about it what what actually
happens now
that unlike myself you have literally
several years to live on unless the
United States wake up the the time bomb
is ticking with every second the
disaster is coming closer and closer
unlike myself you will have nowhere to
defect to unless you want to live in
Antarctica with penguins this is it this
is the last country of freedom and
possibility okay so what do we do what
is your recommendation to the American
people well they're the the immediate
thing that comes to my mind is of course
there must be a very strong national
effort to educate people in the spirit
of real patriotism number one number two
to to explain them the real danger of
socialist communist whatever welfare
state Big Brother government if people
will fail to grasp the impending danger
of their development nothing ever can
help United States you may kiss goodbye
to your freedom including freedoms to
homosexuals to a prison inmate all this
freedom will vanish evaporated in five
seconds including your precious lives
the second thing I the moment at least
part of United States population is
convinced that the danger is real they
have to force their government and I'm
not talking about sending letters
signing petitions and all this beautiful
noble activity I am talking about
forcing United States government to stop
aiding communism because there is no
other problem more burning and urgent
than to stop the Soviet military
industrial complex from destroying what
is whatever is left of the free world
and it is very easy to do no credits no
technology no money no political or
diplomatic recognition and of course no
such idiocy as grain deals to USSR the
Soviet people 270 millions of Soviets
will be eternally thankful to you if you
stop aiding a bunch of murderers who sit
now increment and whom President Reagan
respect
calls government they do not govern
anything least of all such complexity as
the Soviet economy so basic - - very
simple maybe too simplistic answers or
solutions but never nevertheless they
are the only solutions educate yourself
understand what's going on around you
you are not living at the time of peace
you are in a state of war and you have
precious little time to save yourself
you don't have much time especially if
you are talking about young generation
there's not much time left for
convulsions and sexual masturbation -
the beautiful
disco music very soon it will go just
just overnight if we are talking about
capitalists or wealthy businessmen they
I think they are selling the rope on
which they will hang very soon if they
don't stop if they cannot curb the
unsettle desire for profit and if they
keep on trading with the monster of the
Soviet Communism
they're going to hang very soon and they
will pray to be killed but unfortunately
they will be sent to Alaska probably to
manage industry of slaves it's it's
simplistic I know it sounds unpleasant I
know Americans don't like to listen to
things which are unpleasant but I have
defected not to tell you the stories
about such agencies as microfilm James
Bond type espionage this is garbage you
don't need any espionage anymore I have
come to talk about survival it's a
question of survival of this system you
may ask me what is it in for me survival
obviously because unlike as I said I am
now in your boat if we sing together
we'll sing beautifully together there is
no other place on this planet to defect
[Music]