this videos not mine it is a lecture
video given by Thomas Schumann his real
name is Yuri basmanov he gave this
lecture back in 1980s it took me a while
to find this golden nugget and the
reason I uploaded this video on my
channel is because it is a great lecture
that helps us in understanding the
current political scenario both around
the world as well as in our own country
and I believe it needs to be seen after
watching this you will be able to relate
what is happening today in many Western
societies like America in Europe and
unfortunately it is also happening in
India since it's a long video please
watch it whenever you have time and
maybe you all get a bit more educated
the video starts now subversion is the
term if you're looking at in a
dictionary or criminal code to that
matter usually his explained as a part
of activity to destroy things like
religion government system political
economical system of a country and
usually it's linked to espionage and
such romantic things as blowing up
bridges sidetracking trains clock and
dagger activity in Hollywood style when
what I'm going to talk about now has
absolutely nothing to do with the cliche
of espionage or KGB activity of
collecting information so the greatest
mistake or missmiss misconception I
think is that whenever we are talking
about KGB for some strange reason
starting from Hollywood movie makers to
professors of political science and
quote-unquote experts on Soviet affairs
or criminologists as they call
themselves they think that the most
desirable thing for undraw off and the
whole KGB is to steal blueprints of some
supersonic jet bring it back to Soviet
Union and sell it to the Soviet military
industrial complex it's only partly true
if if we take
the whole time money and manpower that
the Soviet Union and KGB in particular
spends outside of USSR border we will
discover of course there are no official
statistics our banquet CIA or FBI the
the espionage and such occupies only ten
to fifteen percent of money time and
manpower 50 percent of the activity of
KGB the rest eighty five percent is
always subversion and unlike a
dictionary of English
Oxford Dictionary subversion in Soviet
terminology means always a destructive
aggressive activity aimed to destroy the
country nation or geographical area of
your enemy so there is no romantics in
there absolutely no blowing up bridges
no micro films in coca-cola cans nothing
of that sort not James Bond nonsense its
most of this activity in all word
legitimate and easily observable if you
give yourself time and trouble to
observe it but according to the law and
law enforcement systems of the Western
civilization it's not a crime exactly
because of misconception manipulation of
terms we think that subvert er is a
person who is going to blow up our
beautiful bridges no subvert er is a
student who come for exchange a diplomat
an actor an artist a journalist like
myself was ten years ago now subversion
is an activity which is a two-way
traffic
you cannot subvert an enemy which
doesn't want to be subverted if you know
history of Japan for example
before 30th century Japan was a closed
society the moment a foreign boat comes
to the shores of Japan the Imperial
Japanese Army politely tell them to get
lost and if American salesman comes to
the shore of Japan let's say 60 or 70
years from now back and says oh I have a
very beautiful vacuum cleaner for you
know that the good financing is please
leave us with the media vacuum cleaner
if they don't leave they shoot them to
preserve their culture ideology
traditions values in fact you were not
able to separate Japan you cannot
separate Soviet Union because the
borders are closed the media is censored
by the government the population is
controlled by the KGB and internal
police with all the beautiful glossy
pictures of Time magazine and magazine
America which is published but by the
American Embassy in Moscow
you can not subvert Soviet citizens
because the magazine never reaches
Soviet citizens it's collected from
their new stance and thrown to garbage
can subversion can be only successful
when the initiator they act or the act
the agent of subversion has a responsive
target it's a two-way traffic the United
States is a receptive target of
subversion there is no response similar
to that one from United States to the
Soviet Union it stops halfway somewhere
it never reaches here the theory of
subversion goes all the way back 2500
years ago the first human being who
formulated the tactics of subversion was
a Chinese philosopher by the name of
sunset
to 3,500 years bc was an advisor for
several Imperial courts and in ancient
China and he said after long meditation
that to implement foreign birth to
implement state policy in a world like
manner it's the most counterproductive
barbaric and inefficient to fight on a
battlefield you know that war is
continuation of state policy right so if
you want successfully to implement your
state policy and you start fighting this
is the most idiotic way to do it the
highest art of warfare is not to fight
at all but to subvert anything of value
in the country of your enemy until such
time that the perception of reality of
your enemy is screwed up to such an
extent that it does not perceive you as
an enemy and that your system your
civilization and your four ambitions
look to your enemy as an alternative if
not desirable then at least visible
better red than dead does the ultimate
purpose the final stage of subversion
after which you can simply take your
enemy without a single shot being fired
if the subversion is successful this is
basically what subversion is as you see
not the single mentioning of blowing up
bridges of course sons that didn't know
about blowing up bridges maybe they were
not that many bridges at that time but
the basics of subversion is being taught
to every student of KGB school in USSR
and to officers of military academies
I'm not sure if the same author is
included in the list of reading for
American or
is to say nothing about ordinary
students of political science I have
difficulty to find the translation of
Sansa in in the library of a university
in Toronto and later on here in Los
Angeles but it's a it's a book which is
not available
it is forced to every students in USSR
every students who is taught to be
dealing further in his future career
with foreigners
what subversion is basically it consists
of four periods timewise if we start
from here and go this way time right
this is the beginning point the first
stage of subversion is the process which
is called basically demoralization says
for itself what it is
it takes from say 15 to 20 years to
demoralize a society-wide by 15 or 20
years this is the time sufficient to
educate one generation of students or
children one generation one lifetime
span of a person a human being which is
dedicated to study to shaping up the
outlook ideology personality no more or
less usually it takes from 15 to 20
years what it includes it includes
influencing or by various methods
infiltration propaganda methods direct
contacts doesn't really matter I will
describe them later of various areas
where public opinion is formulated or
shaped religion educational system
social life administration law
enforcement system military of course
and labor and employer relations economy
okay
five areas I will not write them down
because will not have enough space some
sometimes when I describe all the
methods students ask me question are you
sure this is the result of the Soviet
influence not necessarily you see the
tactic of subversion about which I'm
talking it's similar to the martial art
the Japanese martial art if you're if
some of you familiar with that tactic
probably you will remember that it an
enemy is bigger and heavier than
yourself it would be very painful to
resist his direct strike if a heavier
person wants to strike me in the face it
would be very naive and
counterproductive to stop his blow
the Chinese and Japanese judo art tells
us what to do first to avoid the stripe
then to grab the fist and continue his
movement in the direction where it was
before right until the enemy crashes in
the wall you see so what happens here
the target country obviously does
something wrong if it's a free
democratic society there are many
different movements within the society
there obviously in every society there
are people who are against the society
they may be simple criminals
ideologically in disagreement with with
state policy conscientious enemies
simply psychotic personalities who are
against anything right and finally there
are a small group of agents of a foreign
nation but subverted recruited right the
moment all these movements will be
directed in one direction right this is
the time to catch the movement and to
continue it until the movement forces
the whole society into collapse into
crisis right so that's exactly the
martial art tactic we don't stop an
enemy we let him go with helping to go
in the direction we want them to go and
so on the stage of demoralization
obviously there are tendencies in each
society in each country which are going
to opposite direction from the basic
moral values and principles to take
advantage of these movements to
capitalize on them is the main purpose
of the originator of subversion so we
have religion we have education we have
social life we have power structure we
have labor relations unions and finally
we have law and order one two three four
five six
okay these are the areas of application
of subversion what it means exactly in
case of religion destroy ridicule it
replaces the various sex cults which
bring people's attention faith whether
it is naive primitive doesn't really
matter as long as the basically accepted
religious dogma is being slowly eroded
and taken away from the supreme purpose
of religion to keep people in touch with
with the Supreme Being that serves the
purpose therefore Ripley is accepted
respected religious organizations with
fake organizations distract people
attention from the real faith and
attract them to various different faiths
education distract them from learning
something which is constructive
pragmatic efficient instead of
mathematics physics foreign languages
chemistry teach them history of urban
warfare natural food home economy your
sexuality anything long as it takes you
away okay social life replace
traditionally established institutions
and organizations with fake
organizations take away the initiative
from people take away the responsibility
from naturally established links between
individuals group of individuals and
society at large and replace them with
artificially bureaucratically controlled
bodies instead of social life and
friendship between neighbors establish
social workers institutions the people
who are on payroll of whom society no
bureaucracy the main concern of social
workers is not your family not you not
social relations different groups of
people the main concern is to get the
paycheck from the
what will be the result of their social
work doesn't really matter they can
develop all kind of concepts to show
them to show to the government and for
the people that they're useful okay away
from the natural links power structure
okay the natural bodies of
administration which are traditionally
either elected by by people at lodge or
appointed by elected leaders of society
are being actively substituted by
artificial bodies the bodies of people
groups of people who nobody elected
never as a matter of fact most of the
people don't like them at all and yet
they exist
one of such group is media who elected
them how can they they think they have
so much power
almost monopolistic power on your mind
they can rape your mind but who elected
them how come they are they have a nerve
to decide what is good and what is bad
for for the elected by you president and
his administration who the hell are they
Spiro Agnew who was hated by the liberal
left call them a bunch of enfeebled
snobs and that's exactly what they are
they think they know they don't the
level of mediocracy in a big
establishment like New York Times Los
Angeles time major television network
you don't have to be excellent
journalist you have to be exactly a
mediocre journalist that's easier to
survive there's no competition anymore
you have your good nice income one
hundred thousand dollars a year that's
it whether you are better or worse it
doesn't really matter anymore as soon as
you're smiling to the camera and do your
job no more no more competition
power structure slowly is eroded by the
bodies and groups of people who do not
have neither qualifications nor the will
of people to keep them in power and yet
they do have power okay together with
that there's another process law
enforcement law and order organization
and structure is being eroded for the
last 2025 years you you if you see all
movies and new movies you can see that a
new movies a policeman an officer of the
United States Army looks dumb angry
psychotic paranoid a criminal looks nice
kind of well he smokes hash and and
shoots the whatever drug but basically
he's a nice human being he's creative
and he's unproductive only because
society oppresses him whereby a general
Pentagon is always by definition dumb a
war maniac a policeman is a big rude
policeman he abuses his power no a
generality generalization like that the
hatred the mistrust to the people who's
supposed to protect you and enforce law
and order moral relativity the Angela
Warner process lasted two years in Los
Angeles a little et the Angela Borna
process lasted two years in Los Angeles
and yet there are still some lawyers and
say look he's a nice character as a
matter of fact there were some witness
who said also a criminal who said well
he's a nice guy I asked him one day to
burn a house of my enemy and he wouldn't
do it
[Laughter]
a slow substitution of basic moral
principles whereby a criminal is not a
criminal actually he's a defendant even
if his guilt is proven there is still
adult to kill or not that you to be or
not to be thou shalt not kill yes but
this line may not necessarily be
applicable to a murderer
thou shalt not murder that should be the
the presumption not not that I shall not
kill okay regulations at this stage
within fifteen to twenty years we
destroy the traditional established
links of bargaining between employer and
employee the classical Marxist Leninist
theory of natural exchange of goods the
person a has five sacks of grain and
person B has five pairs of shoes and the
natural exchange without money is when
they bargain between each other and only
with the introduction of the third for C
an entirely third foreign stranger who
says no don't give him five sacks of
grain give it to me and you give you
your five pairs of shoes and I will
distribute it accordingly so that the
economy will go this is the death of
natural exchange that death of natural
bargaining well trade unions were
established hundred years ago the
objective was to improve working
conditions and to protect the rights of
workers from those employers who are
abusing their their right because they
had more money objectively at that time
initially the trade union movement deep
work what we see now is that the
bargaining pot process is no longer
resulting into in the compromise which
is leading objectively to betterment of
working conditions and
increase of salary what we see is that
after each prolonged strike the workers
lose even if they have 10% increase of
their salaries they cannot catch up due
to inflation and due to missed time more
than that millions of people suffer from
that strike because economy now is
interdependent it's intertwined like one
body if previously still workers say
hundred years ago could strike and
nobody would suffer now it's impossible
anymore if a garbage collector strikes
today the rest of the multi-million city
is stinking I mean that there's no more
service in Quebec for example we have
the electricians who are in strike in
the middle of winter you can freeze your
bottom and they still weren't strike did
they catch up with the Saudi no they
lost who benefited the leaders of trade
union what is the motivation for strike
improving improving at work a workers
condition no it's not then what is it
ideology to prove to these capitalists
and the obedient horde of workers like
ship follow these people and they cannot
disobey why because if they do you know
what happens to them tickets murders
shooting truck drivers by picketers in
Montreal for example I saw with my own
eyes when I was correspondent of CBC
international Canadian Broadcasting
Corporation when the workers of aircraft
factory destroyed computers and the
equipment in the factory and they the
administration employed strike breakers
their cars were turned upside down and
burned their houses were burned their
kids were intimidated and some victims
were there of that you can be sure why
to improve conditions of workers no
ideology okay so this is what happens
basically
it may or may not happen without the
help of the Soviet Union but the natural
tendencies are being greatly taken
advantage of and capitalized by the
Soviet propaganda systems how whenever
trade union strikes
we have influx of propaganda mass media
ideological dissemination the workers
right and repeated like parrots
yes workers right whose rights workers
know the only freedom of workers to sell
his labour according to his own desire
and will is taken away from him by whom
by trade union boss unlimited power is
given responsibility I want to sell my
labor not for 250 an hour but for 2
dollars I don't have right my freedom is
denied to me I know that if I sell my
work for to hunt for $2 an hour not for
3 dollars now I will compete better with
the other guy who is lazy and more
greedy I don't need to $3 I need only 2
dollars no I was made to believe by
media by business by advertising
agencies that I need more and more and
more have you ever heard any advertising
on TV to consume less no no way whether
you need a six-cylinder car or not you
have to buy it and hurry up on the local
radio station an excited announcer said
you hurry up rush and save save save
there is a pantyhose a sale
same by buying more of course of course
if before the tuna if you expect the KGB
makes that advertising agency to do such
a crazy commercial no of course not
but what we did when I was working for
NOAA secrecy we would snow plow
editorial offices student organizations
religious group with literature of class
struggle may if not directly Marxist
Leninist propaganda then a propaganda of
of illegitimate aspirations of
working-class betterment of life
equality equality mind you President
Kennedy once said people we will make
America to believe that people who are
born equal our people born equal is
there any mentioning in the Bible or any
other Holy Scripture in any religion any
religion if you don't believe me go to
library and check it there is not a
single word about equality
just the opposite by your deeds God will
judge you what you do is important the
merit of your personality you cannot
legislate equality if you want to be
equal you have to be equal you have to
deserve it
and yet we built our society on the
principle of equality we say people are
equal you know it is false it's a lie
some people are tall and stupid others
are short bald and clever
[Laughter]
if we make them if we make them equal by
force if we put the principle of
equality in the basis of our
socio-political structure is the same
thing as building a house on sand sooner
or later it will collapse and that's
exactly what happens and we as solid
propaganda makers are trying to push you
in the direction which you go yourself
equality yes the quality people are
equal land of equal opportunities is it
true or not think about it
equal opportunities should they be equal
opportunities for me and for lazy
bastards who come here from some other
country and immediately registers as a
welfare recipient benefit I never
received a single dot note sorry I
didn't visit once but I never applied
for welfare for the 13 years I took any
job security guard journalists taxi
driver anything well I was Restless but
some people don't like it they
immediately so why should we be it why
should we have equal opportunities why
the equal opportunity to excel equal
opportunity in equal circumstances yes
but you know people are different to
excel yes provided we reach the same
level of excellency perfection which is
hypothetical distant future yes maybe
but we know perfectly well that even the
best intentions people could not be
equal why should we have equality in the
same legal system myself I'm considering
myself a law abiding citizen and the
person who comes here to rob and shoot
safer the United States Administration
under Carter imported thousands of Cuban
criminal they were non criminal yet they
were accepted do you think it's fair if
myself and my wife from Philippines who
work like excuse me as a lab
technician and in the hospital should
have the same rights as a criminal film
from Cuba why
and yet we repeat as parrots equality
equality equality and the solid
propaganda system helps us to believe
that equality is something which is
desirable democracy as it was
established by fathers of this country
of the system and the last century is is
not equality is the system where
different people unequal people have a
chance to survive and help each other in
constant competition in constant
perfection not in equality which is
super imposed from from a godfather or a
nice person in Washington DC and the
absolute equality exists in Soviet Union
quote unquote equality everybody is
equal in in dirt except some people are
more equal than the others in fully
Bureau so the moment you you bring a
country to the point of almost start
with the mobilization when nothing works
anymore when you are not sure that is
right or or wrong good and bad but there
is no division between evil and good
when even the leaders of church
sometimes say well violence for the sake
of justice especially social justice is
justified in a countries like Nicaragua
and Salvador well maybe Rhodesia and we
listen to them and say here probably
it's true is it true no it is not true
violence is not justified especially for
the sake of quote unquote social justice
introduced by Marxist Leninist that is
my former colleagues from knowledge to
press agents in our case we reach that
point the next step is this
zatia
again this word says for itself what it
is to disturb you lies all the relations
all the accepted institutions and
organizations in a country of your enemy
how you do it you don't have to send up
a battalion of KGB agents to blow up
bridges no you let them do it themselves
the area of application is again it's
it's narrower now not like the previous
case the overt legitimate actions of the
of the KGB in this case would be hardly
noticeable there is no crime if a
professor who recently went to USSR
introduces the course of Marxism
Leninism in in a Californian college for
example nobody is going to come to his
doorstep and say okay mr. come you're
under arrest
no it's not a crime it's not even
considered a moral crime against your
country so the area of application here
is narrowing down to economy again labor
relations right to law and order plus
military and economy law and order yes
and again the media but why does coke
little bit different I'll explain when
okay basically three areas the economy
the radicalization of bargaining process
if on that stage we still could achieve
theoretically some positive compromise
between the negotiating sides with with
say arbitrary an introduction of
arbitrary judges a third side and
objectively judging the the demands of
both side here it's radicalization on
this on the stage of disorganization we
cannot come to compromise even within a
family the husband and wife couldn't
figure out which is better husband wants
his kids to eat at the table and life
him a child to roam around the room and
and drop food all over the floor they
cannot come to compromise unless they
start a fight it's impossible to reach a
compromise constructive compromise
between neighbors some people say I
don't like you to work during you alone
at that time because exactly at that
time I'm walking my dog and he's getting
nervous he cannot pass his balls you
know so they cannot compromise they go
to a civil court or something like that
radicalization of human relations no
more compromise fight fight fight
the normal traditionally accepted
relations are destabilized the relations
between teachers and students in schools
and colleges fight the relations between
in economical sphere between Labour's
and and employers are further
radicalized no more acceptance of the
legitimacy of demands of workers unlike
Japanese with the theories if you ever
heard about it where the workers are
involved in the decision-making process
therefore they don't have model
incentive to to fight their bosses in
the United States has just the opposite
the harder is the fight the better the
more heroic they look when the Greyhound
network was on strike recently the
correspondence of local TV networks all
over the United States were approaching
these strikers and they say oh yes we
are doing something nice they look like
heroes and they were proud there was
some family the husband was a bus driver
now they decided in in the protest
against the bosses to camp somewhere in
the forest and they were presented to
the to the audience as as a heroic nice
people you see the violent clashes
between passengers ticket errs and the
strikers are presented as something
normal
10 15 20 years ago we would we would be
would be angry said why right why so
much hatred today we are not we say well
commonplace radicalization
militarization sometimes as I explained
on that stage I took a step a little bit
further shooting people
ok law and order now also is pushed into
the area where previously people settle
their differences peacefully and
legitimately now we are getting with us
court cases in them in the smallest
irrelevant cases we cannot solve our
problems anymore the society at large
becomes more and more antagonistic
between individuals between groups of
individuals and the society at large the
media puts himself in the opposition to
the society in general at large separate
alienated okay on that stage you
remember I was talking a couple of hours
ago about the sleepers that's when the
students from say United States if they
are trained in in Lumumba University or
developing nations that's the students I
was dealing with are being sent back
from the Soviet Union here or if they
were already in the United States in the
country
which is the object of subversion they
spring to action the sleepers go up they
slept for 15 to 20 years now they become
leaders of groups preachers I don't know
public public figures prominently they
actin they actively include themselves
in the political process all of a sudden
we see a homosexual 15 years ago he did
his dirty job and nobody cared now he
makes it a political
issue it's a political issue he demands
recognition respect human rights and
here all is a large group of people and
their violent clashes between him and
police his group and ordinary people no
matter what it's black against white
yellows again green doesn't matter
where's the vision line goes as long as
this group come into antagonistic
question sometimes militantly sometimes
with firearms that is the stabilization
process the sleepers many of whom are
simply KGB agents become leaders of the
process of destabilization doesn t the
common drop of sense
comrade even off the United States the
person who takes care is already here
his respected citizen of the United
States sometimes he gets money from
various foundations for his legitimate
struggle for I don't know human rights
women rights kiddley prison bleep
whatever there are sympathetic Americans
who donate their money to this to be
like this stabilization process usually
leads directly to the process of crisis
in case of developing nations there's
the area where I I was actor the process
starts
when when be legitimate bodies of power
the social structure collapse it's it
cannot function anymore so instead we
have artificials body injected into
society such as non elected committees
you remember I was talking about them
here social workers who are not elected
by people media who sell who are
self-appointed rulers of your opinion
some strange groups which claim that
they know how to lead society forward
they don't usually only cares how to
collect the nation's and and from and
sell their own concocted ideology
mixture of religion and ideology here we
have all this art officials body
claiming power if the power is denied to
them they take it by force in case of
Iran for example all of a sudden we have
Revolutionary Committees who what what
kind of revolution there was no
revolution yet and yet they had two
committees they were taking power of
judgment they had they had the power of
execution they had the power of
legislation and that they had the power
of judicial all of them combined in one
person who is half-baked intellectual
sometimes graduated from Harvard
University or Berkeley he comes back to
his country and them he thinks that he
knows the answer to all the social
economical problem ok crisis is when
society cannot function any more
productively it collapses obviously
that's the word for crazy
so therefore the population at large is
looking for savior the religious groups
are expecting a messiah to come the
workers say we have family to feed let's
have a strong government maybe socialist
government centralized when when
somebody put put their employers on
their place and let us work we are sick
and tired of going to strike and this
over time and all that stuff we need
some strong man strong government and
leader a savior is needed population is
sick and tired already and here we are
we have a savior either a foreign nation
comes in or the local group of leftists
Marxist no matter what they call
themselves Sandinista a reverend or some
sort bishop user ever like in in
zimbabwe doesn't matter
a savior comes and says I will lead you
so we have two alternatives here civil
war and invasion
okay see how it goes Civil War we know
what it is Lebanon is is the best
example the Civil War which was
artificially implanted in Lebanon by
injection of force of PLO Palestinian
Liberation Organization the invasion we
have in many other countries like
Afghanistan name any East European
country it was invaded by the Soviet
Army but the result is the same the next
stage is normalization normalization is
a very ironic word of course it is
bordered from 1968 situation in
Czechoslovakia when the Soviet
propaganda and after them New York Times
declared the country is normalized the
tanks moved into Prague so there is no
more Prague Spring there is no more
violence
normal normalization at that stage the
self-appointed rulers of the society
don't need any revolution anymore they
don't need any radicalism anymore so
this is the reverse from this table
ization basically it is stabilizing the
country by force so all the sleepers and
activists and social workers and
liberals and homosexuals and professors
and Marxist Americans are being
eliminated physically sometimes they
done their job already okay they are not
needed anymore the new rulers need
stability to exploit the nation to
exploit the country to take advantages
of the victory okay so no more
revolution is please and that's exactly
what happens in number of countries you
remember Bangladesh this is the crisis
in which I was instrumental first they
had Mujibur Rahman in 1971 he was the
leader of People's Party
Avani League with moustache like Stalin
he was in Russia many times
in five years he was shot by his former
colleagues Marxists he fulfilled his
function in Afghanistan it happened
three times
first there was Karachi then there was a
min nowadays babrak karmal they killed
each other
successively one after another the
moment he fulfills his duty the first
one demoralized country the second
disturb you lies
the third one brought it to crisis
goodbye Congress babrak karmal comes
from Moscow and put him into the seat of
power same thing happened in Granada
recently Maurice Bishop Marxist was
killed by Austin what's his name general
something was also a Marxist right so no
more revolutions please normalization
now from now on no more strikes normal
homosexual sexual normal women lead
normal kid lead normally period good
solid democratic proletarian freedom now
to reverse this process takes enormous
effort when today United States had to
invade Grenada to reverse the process of
subversion some people say boy this is
not good it's not kosher to invade the
beautiful country island of Grenada well
why didn't you stop the process here
when Grenada was just approached by
leftists why not to prevent Maurice
Bishop to come in power in the first
place
didn't aliens want him very questionable
they did not was more information in the
first place he came to power by coup
d'etat himself ok no we let the
situation develop further and further
and further until the crisis and
normalization very soon and then the
United States decided to invade country
discovering that the the country was
absolutely a military base for the
Soviet Union of course it's a drastic
measure of course it's it's a pity that
marine course had to lose what 17 lines
very bad why not to stop
process before it comes to crisis or no
intellectuals will not let you it's
interference into into domestic affairs
they're very careful not to not not to
let American administration to interfere
in domestic affairs of Latin American
countries they don't mind Soviet Union
interfere miss affair so to reverse this
process from here it takes only and
always military force no other force on
earth can reverse this process at this
point at this point it does not take
military invasion of United States Army
it takes strong action like in Chile a
CIA covert involvement to prevent the
savior from outside to come into power
and to stabilize country before it
erupts into civil war that's country
before it erupts into civil war okay
support the right wing conservative
forces by money by crook so love doesn't
matter study lies and don't let the
crisis develop into into civil war or
invasion or no you're liberals mistakes
it's against the law the Congress will
not appropriate money for covert actions
of CIA why not
should we wait till the normalization
come and Soviet tanks landed in Los
Angeles Airport now at that point at the
point of destabilization also the
process could be reverse again easily
than this no CIA involvement at this
point you know what it takes here
restriction of some liberties for small
groups which are self declared enemies
on the society as simple as that
although the median liberals will tell
you this is against the American
Constitution how can we by force denied
the civil rights to criminals for
example it's not good okay so we allowed
them to okay if you allow the criminals
to have civil rights go on
in the country to the crisis this is a
bloodless way to do curb the rides I
mean not to put them in prison no no I'm
not talking about putting all the gays
from San Francisco in the concentration
camp do not allow them to take political
force do not elect them to the seats of
power whether it is municipality level
state level or federal level it has to
be written in the heads of American
voters at the person like that in the
city of power is an enemy do not be
afraid of this word it is an enemy if
he's not an enemy here he will be here
later on he will be shot of course okay
you are doing great service by denying
him a right to capitalize on his own
crazy ideas and become a powerful man a
man who uses the seat of power
restriction of certain freedoms and
permissiveness at that point would
prevent sliding into crisis and probably
will return the process of
destabilization to curb unlimited power
monopolistic power of trade unions here
at that point would say economy from
collapsing to introduce a law to stop
private companies of raping public
opinions mind income in the in the
direction of consumerism no company must
have a right to force you into buying
more unless you want it there must be a
law you want to advertise your your car
okay but not a single mentioning of
buying it now and saving money it must
be against the law to force people to
consume more self-restraint previously
before this process started the
self-restraint
was a business of church religion
because our preaches the fathers of
church would tell us material values are
good but it's not the prime function of
human being because you have to live
with something obviously the design for
our life is not to consume more the
audience must be something greater if
such a complicated instrument this human
body was created obviously there must be
some higher purpose for that and it's
very easy to avoid destabilization by
denying the greedy companies one little
freedom one little Liberty forcing you
into turning yourself into professor's
of unwanted products and goods they turn
you into machines like a the worm who
that is Inlet and outlet and how long an
average appliance lost this day less
than a year why where's workmanship we
want you to buy them ok this
stabilization process could be easily
overcome if as I say the society by its
own will or after persuasion by the
leaders will come to the idea of
self-restraint it's so hard we want to
consume more but you have to unless you
will come to this stage when as we say
in Russia if the heart of desert ever
becomes the communist state they'll be
sure to send you have to curb your
[Laughter]
you have to you have to curb your
expectations at this point before it's
too late but no we don't want to do it
demo realization process again it's the
easiest thing to reverse first of all by
restricting import of propaganda the
easiest thing to do unlimited
unrestrained import of Soviet literature
so that journalists giving solid
propaganda and ideological agitators
equal time on American TV network it has
to be stopped
and it's easy they won't they won't be
offended minded as a matter of fact they
will respect American War but then my
former colleague Vladimir Posner
appears on Nightline and Ted Koppel
asking well regime and what do you think
about this and what can he think he is
an instrument of propaganda he thinks
what what what comrade Andropov tells me
to think he's just a nice articulate
mouthpiece of the Soviet era a
submersion system and Ted Koppel makes
you believe that my friend Vladimir
Posner things
the process of dimerization may not have
started at all if at that point the
country which is a recipient of
subversion actively not violently but
actively prevents importation of foreign
ideology
I don't want America to follow the
pattern of ancient Japan you don't have
to shoot every foreigner when it
approaches the sacred borders of the
United States but when he offers you a
junk in the disguise of very shiny
something you have to tell him no we
have our own junk
[Laughter]
if at that point the society is strong
brave and conscientious enough to stop
importation of ideas which are foreign
then the whole chain of events could be
prevented
recently identify Lapine's and I was
shocked how in big cities like Manila
children listened to deafening music a
melodious nation with long traditions of
good nice ethnic music introduced by
Spanish long time ago maybe two
centuries three centuries ago I don't
remember all of a sudden listen to
musical garbage blasting their radios at
full blast at the full volume why in
India I spent many years watching the
reactions of Indians walking out of
movie theaters after seeing Hollywood
production they couldn't figure out why
Americans are so wasteful they smash
their cars their shiny cars every 5
minutes how come they should each other
for half million dollars is it true that
they are so sex sex
but I mean obsessed with sex can you
imagine showing a movie where each 5
minutes there is copulation on the
screen so I country like India with long
traditions tradition of of respect to
this private matters for to Pakistan and
United States expect these people to
respect you no way oh yes they will see
the movie they'll pay 5 rupees to see
that garbage but they walk out and will
tell their kids don't respect Americans
don't be like Americans see so the
process of dimerization could be stopped
right here both as an expert and as an
input
and that takes one step one very
important thing to do you don't have to
expel all the KGB agents from Washington
DC the most difficult and at the same
time the simplest answer to the
subversion is to start it here and even
before by bringing back the society to
religion something that you cannot touch
and eat and put on yourself but
something that rules society and makes
it move and preserve it a soviet
scientist Schaffer a leech who has
nothing to do with religion he is a
computer scientist did a very intensive
research on the history of socialist
countries he call socialist or communist
in any country with a centralized
economy and the pyramidal style of power
structure and he discovered actually he
didn't discover it he just brought to
attention of his readers the
civilizations like mohenjo-daro in the
river hindus area like egypt like maya
Incas like below but Babylonian culture
collapsed and disappeared from the
surface of the moment they lost religion
as simple as that they disintegrated
nobody remembers about them anymore
well distantly so the ideas are moving
society and keeping mankind as a society
of human beings intelligent moral agents
of God the facts the truth the exact
knowledge may not all the sophisticated
technology and computers will not
prevent society from disintegrating and
eventually dying out have you ever met a
person who would sacrifice his life
freedom for the truth like that this is
truth
I never met the person who said this is
truth and I'm ready to shoot me to
defend the truth right but millions
sacrificed their life freedom comfort
everything for things like God like
Jesus Christ it's a known some markers
in the Soviet concentration camp died
and they died in peace unlike those who
shouted long live Stalin knowing
perfectly well that we may not live
wrong something which is something which
is not material moves society and helps
it to survive and they are the way
around the moment we turn into two by
two is four and make it a guiding
principle of our life our existence we
die even though this is true and this we
cannot prove when we can feel and have
faith in it so the answer to ideological
subversion strangely enough is very
simple you don't have to shoot people
you don't have to end missiles and
Pershing's and cruise missiles that and
drop of headquarters you simply have to
have faith and prevent suppression in
other words not to be a victim of
subversion don't try to be a person who
in judo is trying to smash your enemy
and being caught by your hand don't
strike like that strike with the power
of spirit and moral superiority
if you don't have the power it's high
time to develop it and that's the only
answer
[Applause]