I was born in the military family my
father was a high-ranking officer of the
Soviet Army general staff inspector of
land forces
stationed outside of USSR in every quote
unquote brotherly country or liberated
country of the world
I graduated from Oriental Studies
Institute Affiliated to Moscow State
University in 1963
I started working with novice tea press
agency the biggest propaganda and
ideological subversion organization of
USSR which is directly under KGB
ostensibly it's a it's a public news
agency no obviously in Russian language
means news but there are no news that
it's mainly propaganda
uh my first job was a translator with
economical Aid group in India we were
building refineries and and other
industrial projects in public sector
social sector of India my last job was
press officer of the Soviet Embassy in
New Delhi I defected in 1970 came landed
in Canada worked for several years as a
producer of
Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
overseas service in in Russian language
similar to Voice of America then I was
teaching at the University of Toronto
political science department McGill
University Slavic studies and school of
Journalism Ottawa in Carlton University
in Ottawa
last year I joined a small Russian
language publishing house here in Los
Angeles and now I'm a political analyst
for weekly Panorama newspaper
lumumba University language instruction
was my so-called extracurricular
activity which is usually given to
Soviet young Communists as a non-paid
job to prove loyalty to the party I was
instructing students from Asia Latin
America and Africa before they entered
an ideological indoctrination class it
was mainly Russian language instruction
after which these students usually
joined two-year or three-year extensive
course in Marxist leninist ideal
ideological indoctrination plus their
own subjects of their choice medicine
physics chemistry whatever
if they if after five or six years
studying they
but they're proven to be well flexible
loyal uh cynical enough to follow the
Soviet foreign policy they are being
transferred to a KGB school for for the
for a period of two years after which
they are being dispatched back to their
native countries and become so-called
sleepers
the word from originated from sleeping
for several years they sleep in their
own countries doing nothing sometimes
they're pursuing their own careers
become lawyers doctors teachers taxi
drivers Barbers and they spring into
action after many years of
destabilization of their own countries
as Soviet agents therefore all of a
sudden you discover uh well-established
lawyers in a country like Nicaragua who
are for some strange reason are
bitterly against quote-unquote American
imperialism and idealistically for
Soviet Marxist leninist imperialism
I joined Novac press agency uh before I
graduated from the Oriental Studies
Institute where I studied Hindi and Urdu
two languages of Indian subcontinent
Urdu is the language of Pakistan and
Hindi is the language of India
the journalistic part of my training was
ordinary journalism mass media a
communication theories and studies
together with that we had a very
extensive training in military civil
defense intelligence and ideological
subversion so even before I graduated I
started working with novice depressed
agency first as a translator interpreter
and guide with foreign delegations who
were invited to USSR and who were shown
all the beauties of socialism and
dispatched back to their countries to
explain to uh to their
people how beautiful is socialism
my role was directly linked with KGB
activities of brainwashing and
psychological assessment of these guests
if they showed any sign of flexibility
which means they showed that they were
recruitable I passed them over to
professional KGB recruiters and from
there on they were actively being
involved in ideological subversion and
propaganda both in USSR and in their own
countries
well decision of course was very painful
and and difficult
but on the other hand I didn't have any
Illusions or Illusions about the Soviet
system and and Communists or socialist
system as the most rotten and unworking
system in the world some people call it
State capitalism socialism centralized
planning whatever it doesn't really
matter what kind of name you attach to
the system basically if you're a
religious person it's a devilish set and
satanistic system which appeals only to
the most primitive negative side of
human nature
it's the basis of that system is denial
of private property human dignity and
and personal responsibility and of
course any religion religious
affiliation of a human being to God as a
Supreme Being
my dissatisfaction disillusionment if
you can call it because I never was
illusioned
with this with the communism started as
early as
age from age six I guess uh
the first shock was after the second
World War
when most of the children of my age
understood that United States is the
friend
uh with whom together Soviet people
defeated Nazis and German fascism all of
a sudden turned into an enemy
and all of a sudden the propaganda
turned
180 degrees around and we were
brainwashed in the spirit of hatred to
everything which is American but how
could you explain to a child of six
years old who holds his survival to
American spam condensed milk egg powder
and things which you probably people
never remember because nobody eats them
these days spam meat you know what I'm
talking about
how can you explain to them that these
delicious things came from an enemy who
wants to subvert and destroy us it's
impossible because the child remembers
when he was hungry he was eating spam
and and drinking condensed American
milk with the American Eagle on the on
the level so all the efforts of the
Soviet propaganda to convince me that
America is bad was futile naturally
that was the first joke the second was
this 20th Congress of the Soviet
Communist party when Khrushchev revealed
the atrocities of Stalin terrorism and
murder systematic murder of millions of
innocent people that was another
greatest shock and the third shock of
course when I was already grown up a
student invasioned into Czechoslovakia
in 1968 that was the last point
and when I was in India acting as a
Soviet official so the Diplomat I
understood that sooner or later I have
to defect and to explain what exactly I
was doing in India I fell in love with
that country because at that time this
country didn't do any harm to any
neighbors least of all to the Soviet
Union and yet we did so much harm to
that country that I decided to defect
and explain at first to Indians then to
American
politicians intelligence communities and
media unfortunately I didn't have much
success because my stories were treated
by the great skepticism I was called
paranoid macarthy's fascist Cold War
maniac and other names which I don't
want to mention here and it took me
quite a number of years to understand
that I'm talking to people who are
trying to prevent average American from
knowing the truth about communism
the basic methods are not that much
different from activities of any Public
Relation officer from any big company
say Coca-Cola I bet they have their own
Department of Person of public relations
and press relations but the ultimate
goal the ultimate purpose is different
if Coca-Cola wants to make profit and to
sell more Coca-Cola to nations of the
world the Soviet Union the ultimate
purpose of the Soviet system is not to
sell anything list of all ideology is to
destroy the civilization on which the
affluence and freedom based and replace
it with the system of total control over
life of human beings the system of total
exploitation that's the ultimate purpose
my specific measures which which I was
forced to do unwillingly of course but I
had to do them just to promote myself
further and further is a bribery
corruption
befriending politicians members of
parliament influential Scholars
members of civil service businessmen
in other words anyone who has any
um anything to do with shaping of public
opinion in the interests of the Soviet
foreign policy
that would include a long process which
sometimes is unnoticeable to an average
person it's a long-term process which is
called so ideological subversion it's
unnoticeable as movement of a small hand
of a clock you know it's going around
but even if you watch it intensely you
don't see the movement the eventual
result is befriending these people and
trying to get them involved in the
activity in the interests of the Soviet
foreign policy the immediate impulse
when I learned that the Soviet Embassy
Department of research and Conquer
propaganda of which I was a deputy chief
is engaged neither in research nor in
Contra propaganda it is Department which
is compiling information of private
nature on individuals divided in two
groups good boys and bad boys the
sympathetic people were promoted in
media and public life the people who
were opposed to the Soviet foreign
policy were black washed blackmailed and
and destroyed first morally and
sometimes physically to
uh
understanding of what I was doing came
to me when I when I looked through a
press release of United States
information service describing an
incident in a South Vietnamese City of
Houston captured by Communists from
Hanoi for for 48 hours then it was
recultured by United States and South
Vietnamese armies and to the horror they
discovered that within two nights the
Communists could manage to round up more
than 15 000 people and execute them
most of these people were either
sympathetic to United States or to the
Western culture or directly involved in
activities
supporting the United States present in
South Vietnam agents of CIA naturally
even Barbers because they know too much
they were executed and the United States
intelligence couldn't figure out how
could they possibly do it in such short
period of time later on they discovered
they found out from several defectors
that long before Communists occupied
that City
there was an extensive
omnipresent network of informers who
knew exactly their dresses the names the
whereabouts of each individual who was
later executed
when I turned to my own files I
discovered that basically that
information exists in my department
so it doesn't take much intelligence to
understand what I was doing in India I
was compiling information comes
Revolution these people would be
executed
indirectly I was involved in in a
criminal activity in mass murder I
decided to defect and explain it to
Americans and the response I already
described I was called a paranoid
but I decided to defect and try
nevertheless
here's another long story it's virtually
impossible to defect in India simply
because Indian government under pressure
from the Soviet government if you can
call them government I don't call them
government I call them Junta they
adopted Allah as early as as in 61 or 62
after after Stalin's daughter defection
especially that law states that no
Embassy no no foreign
ligation on the territory of Indian
Republic has a right to extend
political Asylum to any Defector from
any country which is very it's it's a
masterpiece of hypocrisy no other
Defector but the Soviet one needs a
political Asylum
if you are a Canadian or American if you
want to be nasty to your own government
the maximum you can do is just to pick
up a phone and make a dirty phone call
to your Ambassador buy yourself a ticket
and get lost
what happens to a Soviet Defector in
under that law if I knock a door of
United States Embassy by that law the
American diplomats have to turn him back
to the Indian police and Indian police
takes me back directly back to the
Soviet Embassy and that's the end of my
defection so knowing that perfectly well
and having contacts both with Indian
police and American Media Corps I I
understood that the only way for me was
to
disappear for a while and the best way I
discovered was to mix with group of
hippies mind you that that
was the time
I was 13 years younger so I looked
slightly different of course
I started so-called Contra culture in
India sometimes
good sincere young people who wanted to
study Oriental mysticism and culture and
religion
but most of them were simply easygoing
individuals who were delighted with
exotic exotic life and and the easiness
with which they can purchase hashish and
Other Drugs in India and sometimes they
traveled Indian subcontinent without any
identification papers so the best way to
to escape detection was to mix with the
group of hippies and travel in India
until they campaign in the media and in
the police the police search will
subside all the newspapers in India
carried my picture and announcement of
the police
that anyone coming forward with
information about my whereabouts would
receive 5000 or 2 000 rupees knowing
that perfectly well I just walked in
their Barefoot with beads and blue jeans
smoking hush and
enjoying life
until I found sympathetic journalists
who smuggled me from India to briefs
minded that was a military dictatorship
at that time then only I approached
American CIA and they helped me to
land in Canada as a legit ordinary
immigrant
it's now I'm a Canadian citizen as you
can see from my patriotic diet
Canada is kind of middle of the way of
the road country where there are so many
various ethnic groups that another
strange character who speaks both
Russian and English and to Oriental
languages I I didn't have any problems
fitting into academic circles and first
being just a student at University of
Toronto later a producer with a Canadian
Broadcasting Corporation
I think it was successful and until and
unless that they'll be follow up to that
movie
it will remain as as an open wound in in
the United States
as a scare tactic which in this
particular case I'm not sure whether KGB
paid for production of that movie or not
but it's totally irrelevant what is the
most important unless
after seeing the tragic sequences of the
nuclear attack an American population is
not explained what to do about it if you
still stop at that and let it be
obviously this is the scare tactic this
is the greatest harm done to United
States by by Americans by American
filmmaker I bet on drop of in all his
disinformation
system could not could not possibly do
that much harm to the United States when
when you see something obviously
sponsored by the Soviets you understand
well this is propaganda you may or may
not agree with this depending on your
background and and intelligence and
education but here it's a subtle
approach playing on the most sensitive
strings of your soul appealing to to the
most Basic Instincts of of human nature
survival
but there are no answers how to survive
well obviously disarmament is not the
answer simply because some people
naively expect a drop off to blush out
of Shame and reduce the number of
warheads and it doesn't happen this way
this we are facing
unresponsive irresponsible group of
people for whom
uh nuclear war is not a theory it's a
practice and the military strategy of
the Soviet Union is designed to to do
nuclear war and to survive and possibly
to win
I I was I started my military training
when I was six or seven years old when I
when I entered Secondary School
and I graduated in 63 after almost 15
years of continuous training as a junior
Lieutenant of reserve of the Soviet Army
and
psychologically every Soviet citizen is
well prepared for for war nuclear war
and technically he is equipped with
facilities and the knowledge how to use
it in case of war or or natural disaster
doesn't matter
survival tactics and survival
methods are taught
extensively in in various manners they
are exposed to documentary movies about
nuclear war they know the the technical
data of radiation or contamination of of
air and and land they know the
organizational patterns of civil defense
to such an extent that even if there is
no nuclear attack even if there's a
conventional Warfare each individual
at a certain time knows exactly where to
go what to do where is the shelter whom
to call by telephone
which is not the case unfortunately in
the United States I think if if a bomb
ordinary bomb maybe a sting bomb is
dropped in the middle of Los Angeles
most of the people will not die of
atomic radiation they will die of panic
they will they will run and the
traffic jams and and and the Panic will
kill more people than many anything else
and where do they go is is there any
literature about how to protect an
individual with the medical first aid
treatment but it's not taught to to kids
in American colleges unfortunately
for example there is obvious tension in
the world it's a television newscasts
inform American Family about happenings
in in East and West Germany and only at
the last moment they decide to bring the
canned food down to the basement and to
share idiocy why not to have them in the
basement
at the peacetime number two there's
there's very realistic picture of what
happens when the first nuclear bomb
strikes a big City Kansas City I think
in people's a big panoramic picture
shows almost an ant hill when you know
people are disoriented totally that
would produce love in Russia because
unlike that Soviets know exactly what to
do they'll be much less Panic if at all
thank you
I I know about infiltration of kgbin to
peace movement probably as much as an
average American who reads newspapers
systematically
but I I'm obviously I'm aware that the
world peace council is is a front
organization of the KGB Ramesh Chandra I
know personally both in India and USSR I
worked with delegations of of
various peace Nicks who came to the
World Congress of Peace Council in
Moscow I think it was in 1961 or 62.
yeah it was before Cuban crisis
and at that time they struck me as as
people who are pathologically unable to
see the truth
not to talk about the military aspects
when I when as a translator and a guy
that used to take them to places in
Moscow which are not supposed to be for
foreigners eyes
and they didn't want to see it they had
their preconceived ideas they they were
suffering from self-importance they
thought it's it's a great honor to sit
in the Kremlin in the Palace of of
congresses next to uh next to dibio from
Kremlin and you know talk about peace as
if that person from politburo means
anything in in peace movement
self-delusion is is the most predominant
phenomenon among these people Ramesh
Chandra is is a very shrewd
politician who
takes advantage of naive misguided
idealistically minded sometimes sincere
people
but he is I I would my impression is
that he's totally sold himself to the
Soviets he receives his payments or
royalties or whatever you can call it in
the form of prizes
of course it's very embarrassing if you
if you if you approach a person of his
caliber with money with cash and say
here comrador mesh Chandra there is a
money for your propaganda in the
interests of the Soviet Union
it's very unpolite so instead the Soviet
Union creates artificial International
bodies such as jabaharlal nehru peace
committee which consists of various
Progressive leaders writers sometimes
they're they're known figures and as
philosophers educationalists
sometimes they probably feel that
if there's no other possibility to
express the desire for peace at least
there is some legitimate overt activity
where they can express themselves that's
okay and they think they are too smart
not to see that part of it is Soviet
propaganda okay we are smart we are not
going to allow them to use us for
propaganda purposes this is wishful
thinking because after five or six
visits visits to USSR everything is paid
by the Soviet Government after
spending several vacations on a black
seed cost luxurious atmosphere with two
or three nice girls interpreters lots of
vodka and caviar books published that is
in the United States all of a sudden
published in millions of copies in USSR
in various languages
that tickles their ego they think they
are some somebody's all of a sudden
it's difficult to resist the temptation
Ramesh Chandra is exactly that type of
Personality he was approached at the
very early stage
and he didn't have willpower
and moral principles to resist the
temptation to resist the approach and by
now he's he's just upon in the game
high-ranking Capone and
uh if he is dismissed or dies natural
death there will be another the line of
people who would like to take his place
yes kgbtx very active part in the in the
peace movement
and if these people were sincere as they
say they are they would start
demonstrating him Kremlin or I mean in
Red Square not in Washington DC or in in
the Central Park in New York or in Los
Angeles but they don't have courage they
don't have guts to go to Russia and
protest against the nuclear Armament of
the Soviet Union therefore
I agree that they are misguided but I
think they are cowards
they're unprincipled dishonest people
and there's no justification that they
are misguided or poorly informed it's
their fault that they're pulling from
there's enough information
there's enough possibility in case of
United States sitting there's enough
freedom to do what Their Consciousness
should tell them to do go to Russia and
protest against Harmony
it doesn't take much courage to to to
take part in demonstration in Los
Angeles
but if you're really genuinely concerned
about peace
tell it to Brezhnev tell it to unblock
and we'll see how courageous and sincere
you are they don't do it
all the greatest strength I think is is
the basic principle of American
democracy common sense
and the uh
the value of of the principles of
private property and and respect to
human dignity and individual individual
rights the weakness is
the permissiveness and lack of moral
stamina
which if you are a religious person
could be could be interpreted as
probably alienation from religion
alienation from God
thinking too much in materialistic terms
thinking in short span
I'm for pragmatic
advantages
disregarding the
perspective of civilization some
philosopher I forget his name I was a
bad student in Moscow said that the
level of civilization is
in direct proportion to the time span
that human being thinks in in future for
future
the least civilized people live today
this minute the more civilized Nations
thing about tomorrow 10 years from now
100 years from now
this is one of the definitions of
unfortunately Americans are made to
think in shorter and shorter time span
terms
this is the greatest weakness
it is so therefore enjoy life and
Make Love Not work
I I think that
willpower and revitalization of
traditional moral values and principles
is the most desirable thing now today
the the sooner the better
the things that the principles and
values
on which the affluence and success of
American civilization depends and based
upon should be immediately civil uh
revitalized and brought back to school
programs to media and let's face it
propaganda I'm not afraid of this word
unlike the left liberal journalists who
think oh well it's propaganda I don't
see anything wrong in propagating the
basic moral principles and values on
which America is built
willpower
faith unshakable faith that this country
this civilization is right
and the enemy is wrong
no amount or no number of nuclear
warheads and and no size of the army
will will help United States to survive
whether there's nuclear war or
conventional Warfare Vietnam proved very
clearly
that with all the technology with all
the supersonic bombers and not power and
whatnot electronic gadgets and and cold
beer and Coca-Cola
you cannot defeat an enemy
unless you are fighting and have faith
in the righteousness of your fight
so that's the most urgent thing I think
wake up and and convince yourself that
you're on the right side
there should not be no neutralize more
object objectivity or objectivity is
good when you are discussing
philosophical Concepts
in today's world if you are neutral you
are already an enemy of your own country
you have to actively take part of your
country your side one of the reasons of
my defection is that I took sight I was
I was decided to take part to take
choice to make my own personal choice
for some strange reason today it's very
fashionable it considered to be an
intellectual sheet not to take sides
academic media
academic circles
Hollywood stars and politicians
they think it's very fashionable it's
intellectual to be non-alive
non-committed
neutral it's it's not intellectual it's
suicidical
laughs
suicidal
okay I'll start with the short
explanation I'm going to show you some
slides now the things that you're going
to see uh there's nothing new actually
they're they're reproduction from
various media organs in the United
States USSR probably you'll see these
pictures hundred times a day
I'm going to give you a very a different
viewpoint on the same thing same facts
that you see and probably don't don't
take much trouble to understand and
think what you are seeing
uh I don't know if you heard my
introduction I'm I'm a ideological
subverter yes from Russia okay
okay it's the idea of showing the slides
to you is just to provoke questions in
your mind and later on if you still have
patience with me I I will explain how
exactly the system of ideological in
indoctrination and um subversion works
well we know that we are living in a
time of peace and we know that recent
walkout from the Geneva Talks by the
Soviets is centered around the nuclear
arms and Rockets we don't see much about
the Soviet prepared as a Soviet
viewpoint on the military strategy well
this is a selection of pictures only
pictures Confucius said that one Picture
Tells more than thousand words these
pictures are from everyday newspapers in
USSR this is what the Soviet citizen
looks
in looks upon every day
basically this is a militaristic spirit
a pictures of foreign delegates
observing the Rockets passing the Red
Square the idea of invasion unlike in
the United States is not being
criticized by the Soviet media at all on
the contrary it's being forcefully
encouraged from the age of say five or
six years six years old every Soviet
student's a student or Schoolboy has to
go through military training uh this is
a picture from a special military school
where young kids well maybe four or five
years old are being trained to be future
officers of the Soviet Army that's what
they do when they grow up these are the
Soviet Sailors Navy uh officers in a
foreign country we criticize a lot
American presence in foreign countries
but we never criticize and we never pay
too much attention about these planes
landing with the ammunition and
firearms in say countries like Ethiopia
these are the pictures in Time Magazine
which probably you've seen and then
forgotten about it these are the Soviet
tanks on foreign territory are there any
protest demonstrations in the Los
Angeles or New York City no
these are the Soviet military advisers
nobody tells them Russians go home how
it starts the media obviously plays a
great role this is a political cartoon
from a western newspaper
um you see it was published sometimes
after the second world war these four
Columns of Peace pay attention to whom
they are being erected Roosevelt on the
left Churchill on the Right End Stalin
in the middle a peacemaker Stalin
okay this is another thing Chicago
Tribune January 1945
Destiny's Child
New Year 45 is born look who is looking
with with love and affection
Churchill Roosevelt and Stalin
and this is how the Soviet media
describes Churchill as a warmonger
is Gustavo Moscow 1951 this is how the
Soviet media presents American
militarism linked with Nazism
this is how the Soviet media
illustrates South African colonialism
not much different from a political
cartoon in New York Times or Los Angeles
Times a matter of fact almost similar
growth of inflation due to military
expenses
a political cartoon from Prague the
newspaper it could be published as it is
in Los Angeles Times nobody would wander
NATO is criticized by the Soviet media
but so it is by the American Media Law
and Order justifying the former military
criminals this picture this is what is
uh this this is a number of books which
I selected in a an average University
Bookstore most of them are left-wing
propaganda Eric from main man Prevail
the in the China story of course from
the Viewpoint of left Lenin's work how
to deal with Communists by
um a former ambassador to USSR
um
marks and angles Lenin
Herbert marcusian
uh the communist movement these are the
books which are included in the list of
reading for an average student of
political science department in any
college of Canada or United States
these are the books which are on sale in
United States and Canada Soviet
propaganda these are the booklets and
magazines published by novelty press
Agency for which I worked for 12 years
no restriction for this booklets I found
them in the on the campus of Toronto
University most half of these books I
edited myself when I was working for
novelty in Moscow
this is very interesting thing it
doesn't say much unless I explain what
it is these are the Seals attached to
crates of books imported from USSR to
Montreal as you can easily see the seal
is unbroken which means that the customs
in Canada didn't bother to see what's
inside and as I know from my personal
experience we used to import machine
guns AK-47 and ammunition through India
to Bangladesh in exactly the same craze
sign Printed Matter to Dr University
this is what editor of Time Magazine
suggests you to read at the time of
invasion I mean fall of Southeast Asia
to
communists
social distance Gulag archipelago is on
the bottom of the list according to the
editor's choice
why on bottom of the list these are the
books which are never included in the
list of compulsory reading to any in any
University or college in United States
or Canada look what the student is
missing the death of Stalin childhood in
prison
ferment in Ukraine
Russian Secret Service the great Terror
these are the books which for some
strange reason Americans are denied the
freedom and right to read why America is
in global Retreat have you ever seen
this book on on a campus now of course
not I know that Anthony satin National
Suicide have you ever had the chance to
read that book or you had
[Music]
this is another very interesting thing a
description how drugs penetrate into
Western Society originated in communist
world for some strange reason that
textbook is never included in in the
list of compulsely compulsory reading
for students of political science or
International affairs
this is the book written by a former
member of Communist party in
Czechoslovakia explaining the tactics of
subversion for some strange reason it
was not published in the United States
or Canada the author had to pay for the
publication himself after defecting to
to the West this is another interesting
example
exoneration and ultimate and written by
Richard Romer a science fiction novel
about invasion of United States into
Canada to expropriate the oil and
natural gas resources in that
neighboring friendly Nation why it took
Invasion I don't understand 51 or more
percent of the of the companies are
already belong to the United States in
Canada is probably you know already who
is the author Richard Roemer is a
dynamic and dedicated exponent of the
needs of potential and so anyway he's a
friend of Pierre Trudeau a former of a
former military officer
and what he writes is is something that
andropo probably would be very happy
about
he describes a situation when the only
thing that saves Canada from United
States military occupation is a call
from andropos to the president of United
States threatening him with the re with
the reply or with the military answer to
an invasion of Canada by United States
and this is written by a close friend of
Pierre Trudeau a politician a former
military man why
is he a paranoid or am I a paranoid
the three books published almost
simultaneously
sometimes in the middle of 70s CIA and
the cult of intelligence
CIA diary by Philip age and the KGB by
John Baron
but I tried to buy the KGB but it was
not in the bookstores of Canada or
United States the previous two books on
the left were
this is the author of the of the most
anti-American book The Defector to the
Communist side Philip H he is alive
nobody is threatening his life
nobody is poisoning him with with the
poison umbrella this is uh you know who
uh he's criticizing CIA for developing a
gun to kill communist agents and he
tries to present it as a crime on behalf
of the United States intelligence agency
why is it a crime
to defend you from the Communist agents
and to develop a secret gun which is
silent
is a crime
is there any logic I don't see any this
is the fellow who also criticizes the
the United States CIA for developing
technical means of bagging United's I
mean USSR embassies on the territory of
United States why not
I don't see any reason why not but
Mondale obviously does he knows better
these are the authors who publish lists
of American agents stationed all over
the world they are alive
they actually they made quite a lot of
monies in the publication and this is
the victim
the chief of CIA in grief was killed
when the book of of the previous two
Americans was published
this fella is dead the other two are not
siberi in 1971 was visited by a group of
politicians from Canada and this this is
the report about that is it this is the
group we're shaking hands with the
Soviets uh ambassador
this is a Soviet technical Miracle a
pipeline on terma
thermafrost or something in other words
what Canadians were doing in early 60s
is presented to Canadian public as an
achievement a great technological
achievement in USSR
this is the root of their travel in
Siberia the Canadians covered that much
of distance please remember that map I
will come back to that question
this is a book published by a Canadian
author Farley Mobile by the way Never
Cry Wolf a movie which is made on the
basis of uh Farley mowatt's book he's a
nice fellow drinks a lot of vodka he was
a guest of novice depressed agency which
I was working for
this is another book written by Farley
Moet after returning from Siberia he was
accompanied by a person like myself a
novice depressed agency journalist
glorification of Siberia this is what an
L this is the root I promised you to
come back to that map which follow him
of it a Canadian Progressive writer
covered when he was in USSR
this is what he makes Canadians to
believe Siberia looks like it does of
course Baikal lake is a very beautiful
natural phenomenon a nicely dressed
Soviet eskimosa I don't know some ethnic
minorities friendly talking to each
other in fluent English
please
they um
nice nice Motel somewhere in the middle
of Siberia
a huge hydroelectric electrical projects
it is true it is built but they never
mentioned by whom
and this is what I eventually wanted to
show you these are the two Roots first
one in red ink by Canadian government
delegation
in blue ink by the author Farley movers
accompanied by novice depressed agency
the black dots are locations of Soviet
concentration camps
these people were shown the places where
the slave labor is being used by the
Soviet government if you call them
government I call them Junta Mass
murderers but there is not a single
mentioning not a word
that those beautiful electric stations
were built by slave slave labor
this is what Canadian reader will never
see in the report by Canadian
politicians
or the progressive writer Farley moment
you say well that's that's Russia this
is not a kindergarten this is a prison
for children of prisoners
these are the houses
if if an American contractor would build
a house like that
I think he will end up in jail but this
is what what is being shown to to some
naive foreigners as achievements of
Soviet technology naturally
if you follow the editor's choice and
advice you will never understand
that the description the the most
detailed description of Soviet
concentration camp system
is put on the on the bottom of the list
you say well maybe in USSR the
Concentration Camp is nothing surprising
well this is a concentration camp in
Southeast Asia
in Cambodia
same thing
slave labor this is what happens to
slave laborers when they don't obey the
orders they are being executed not by
firing squad because bullets are too
expensive by showers crashing skulls
this is the victory of Communism for you
this is what happens to their children
and this is the originator of this sloth
house conversion Premiere Paul Potts
during interview with Time Magazine very
nice plump fatherly image
you're made to believe that Holocaust
happened during the second world war is
something that may
happen again it may
but the originator of it may not
necessarily be the Nazis
we don't have any Nazi submarines
roaming around the shores of United
States and Canada
we have Liberation forces that's what
Holocaust this is happening right now
after the so-called National Liberation
movement this is a as a steal from a
movie Holocaust a television production
the Nazis are shooting the Prisoners the
Jews
we are made to well it's horrible of
course there is no denial it happened
many years ago
and the tactic which I will explain you
later if you have patience with me is
side tracking your opinion from present
danger to the Past
from this this is present time
this is past time
this is happening right now
in Asia Africa and Latin America is
there any movie about Holocaust with
Shepherds now no
this is what happens in there for well
it did happen in Rhodesia before it
becomes Zimbabwe
it's a black girl by the way not a white
one
this is the result of the Socialist
movement
these people were killed by those who
are now in power in Zimbabwe and we call
them Reverend
Bishops or whatever
this is the supply of Soviet arms to
religion before it turned into Zimbabwe
and this is very interesting picture the
poor South African is showing his
internal passport saying that there is
no
freedom
and he has to live whatever he is
assigned to live by the police for some
strange reason not a single media Outlet
in the United States makes comparison
because in Russia every citizen have a
prospect like that
and the Asian ethnics in USSR do not
have the right to live in those areas
which are designed for the for the
whites and the other way around
but we are getting emotional about this
password why not about sovereign
is flowing in the wind how the same room
okay the the feeling of guilt open any
magazine there are lots of pictures like
that hungry people asking for your
dollar donation think about it Emma de
Leon has no one else to turn to except
you
see how many pictures I collected them
within one week
and who helps them rock stars through
United Nations UNICEF
and how they use this money they buy
arms
have you noticed that countries like
Philippines never ask for the Nations
why because they have free market system
oh yes they have military dictatorship
oppression of civil rights but for some
strange reason only those countries
which are already liberated by marxists
are asking for your donations why and
when they get these donations
will you be my friend this is what Time
Magazine wants you to think if not the
implication is this is what's going to
happen
when white miners stationed in this
small country African country were
murdered by so-called National
Liberation movements
this is the result rape and murder
after your donations
and who is who is supporting these
movements of course United
Nations
okay we'll we'll come later on to the
question of semantic manipulation
everybody knows that United Nation is
not United and it's not Nations but we
continually
I don't know how many people notice the
Striking similarity between the emblem
of United Nations and emblem of this of
the USSR you think it's coincidence
the symbolism is obvious unless you are
blind of course we
I'm the creator of the United Nation
Charter
is an American Alger his
standing next to comrade Molotov sitting
there on the left
we know he was a Soviet spy but he is at
large now algae is
he's a lawyer a respected citizen of the
United States a former Soviet spy
well you know this guy is Daniel
Ellsberg he published secret papers of
Pentagon why not of Soviet military
industrial complex
he's a respected citizen of the United
States
Dr Spock Agony of Vietnam
forget what's his name
oh yeah
how how many men has to die before they
understand that I don't remember the the
lyrics of the song but it was very
impressive song When I was a Soviet
student I almost cried when I listened
to that and I thought my God what a nice
fella
John Baez very nice couple of kids
Jane Fonda she was crying on location in
Vietnam's dutifully filmed by American
Hollywood
uh correspond I mean filmmakers
what is she doing now
did she ever defend both people
did she say a word in defense
Vietnamese let's say about horrors of
coming out of this no she's busy here
preaching the
health or whatever
and also she takes part in demonstration
against South and South African racism
not about this
and not about this
this is Liberation movement Warriors
Jane Fonda didn't say anything about
that racism a black killed by blacks
simply because he is anti-communist
there's just a symbolic picture okay now
next thing I'm going to show you some
slides which are
also not nothing Sensational but may
provoke some questions in your mind
maybe not
okay
the more questions you have the better
because we will come to systematic
explanation of of the phenomenon later
now I want you just to get excited
uh Hollywood actress talking to Fidel
Castro nothing wrong of course depends
what is the message or what's the
subject of talking
foreign
he's an American singer Dean Reed
he's singing in Moscow for some strange
reason and you know what he's singing
about
oppression civil rights uh in in USA and
about poor Americans who cannot survive
well I don't want to be too critical of
of
pope of Catholic church but some states
statements which he made at the earlier
years of his
becoming a appointee for Catholic Church
strikingly unpleasant to me communism
and church can coexist can they
well you should ask a Russian Orthodox
priests who were literally
exterminated by by the Soviet Communists
communism church can pre-exist I don't
think so Catholic times I I collected
this newspaper
in a Catholic Church which I attend
although I'm Orthodox Christian as
Russians most of them are
but I do come to Catholic church because
my wife is a Catholic so I don't see
much difference because God that I
suppose is one so Jesus Christ is also
the same with which church whichever you
go but
Christians and socialism is something
that doesn't really appeal to me I don't
know how about you
social justice Central to gospel is it I
never heard about it
join with marxists is from the same
newspaper
and that's how they joined it Marxist
Nicaragua before Sandinista came to
power a priest with machine gun behind
his back and the Machine Gun of course
know anything about machine guns okay
then there are some strange deviations
from religious uh
um path uh what's his name John Jim
Jones Reverend Reverend
nice looking guy with adopted kids and
shaking hands with the politician
mayor George
Moscone in 1976 very nice
that's how it all ended you remember 900
more than 900 people who poisoned
themselves together with their kids in
Guyana
this is a very interesting picture it's
not very clear instead of Jesus Christ
they put a naked lady you know in the
church
stranger
of course it's strange crucifix of a
woman for pound Sunday
boy Jesus Christ would turn in his grave
if he were engraved
now this this is something that also
indicates some strange occurrences
within the framework of organized
religion in struggle a paper with
Tamarind sickle published by a Canadian
group of trotskyites very Dynamic
extremely radical group they challenge
the question whose democracy is this
meaning the Canadian democracy is not
democracy at all simply because that
radical group is challenged by the local
police right so nothing new we know
about this
but look where this paper is being
distributed
political repression Friday October
but United Church
stranger
see this is the same leaflet
enlarged
this is another thing President Carter
handed over an antique
Crown belonged to church of Hungary to
the present Communist Regime of Hungary
why I don't understand to make them
friendlier to church I doubt
feminist movement I don't know how you
feel about feminism I don't think that
to be equal with men you have to
politicize your movement you cannot
legislate equality you have to be equal
but that distracts your mind from real
issues of family loyalty and and well if
you
the Moral Moral foundations and they
make a great political capital on that
first lady of the United States sitting
to the to to some kind of I forget what
what her name was exposing her tits to
the media I mean this is
and by by the soil by by the American
Media standards this is something normal
acceptable the first lady of the United
States together
with the lady who burns her
bra I don't know well ladies in the army
of course I don't know what's your
opinion I I never heard about
girls in the Soviet Army especially in
the Infantry Force simply because when
they have period That's that may create
a problem for invasion of say
Afghanistan
homosexualism I I to be honest me
personally I don't like the idea of
homosexuality I think it's it's
unhygienic
but
but uh homosexuality in the army
making Heroes of them gays on the March
why
why to to have population in a natural
manner deserves a public opinion uh
attention
and and the political force
why to politicize something which
doesn't belong to politics at all in
Russian in the Soviet Union we have a
joke don't mix politics and prostitution
they are already mixed
we know perfectly well this is the
medical science proved that
homosexuality leads to Distortion in in
human psychology this fellow killed 15
kids after molesting them sexually we
know that most of the agents who were
recruited by KGB including McLean and
Guy Burgess were homosexual homosexuals
but we are reading in in the media that
this is some something acceptable more
than that we are made to believe that
these people deserve equal rights and
respect
well that again is a debatable question
whether to like or not to like certain
type of music me personally I don't
this these two nice ladies one is
younger the other is a little bit older
both of them want it for some strange
reason to shoot president of the United
States defending the environment of the
United States the green trees and
vegetation
why it takes that of United States
president to defend the the environment
I I don't understand if you do please
explain
then of course glorifying all kind of
National Liberation leaders we naturally
provoke our own kids to go into some
strange Liberation movement you know who
I'm talking about this is the girl who
was abducted by terrorists and then she
became terrorists herself a daughter of
a wealthy publisher
naturally there are thousands millions
of kids who
Who Loved adored her courage
this is comrade Carlos you know who he
was he was trained and educated in
Mumbai University where I was teaching
Russian language to the likes of him
that's the result of the activity when
they come back home aldamora was killed
by Red Army terrorists who were wanted
to liberate Italians from something I
don't know from whom
these are the the persons who were part
of bother mein Hoff gang
and this is a person who also liberates
someone from someone I don't exactly
know obviously Indians from whites in
the United States but pay attention what
he holds in his hand
it's Kalashnikov AK-47 I know it by
heart I can put it apart with my eyes
closed
um war on terrorism does it exist
apart from verbal War
this is what I have collected on an a
campus in Canada
Carlton University
Ottawa
left-wing tabloids that's how they
instill in the minds of people young
people that to fight is the only way the
violence death is the only way to
achieve rights of Palestinian people
other people Quebec
separatists and jobs and peace obviously
you cannot get job if you spend all your
time walking up and down streets with
posters like that you have to go to
place with them where the jobs are
and of course to find the job the the
most unsuccessful way to find a job is
to read papers like that
I don't feel like working this is
something another this is a Playboy
magazine probably you heard the story
about Larry Flynn how how successful is
he to attract attention of media and and
public opinion by doing crazy things
getting involved in court case of of the
um
the car manufacturer why he wants to do
it I don't know but what he does
attracts some strange Mass attention
Playboy magazine makes jokes about
Russian sex
that's the image that they want to
present to American people
but they don't explain to American
people that the process of
demoralization is not as is not the
question of joke
this is Portugal after socialists came
to power on your left is a prostitute
who was imported from East Germany to
Lisbon
a communist prostitute in a country
which which is
just had its successful socialist
Revolution very interesting what for to
make money no I'll tell you later on the
right pornographic literature in the
country with strong Catholic moral
principles
well
I don't know how many people of you like
to drink alcohol I did
but I noticed that some
ads in in magazines have some strange
desire to joke about alcohol
and the jokes are closely related to
justification of Soviet Russian presence
a prominent Russian joined the Secret
Service
something to joke about while you drink
Vodka
I don't see any humor in that do you
okay this this is a number of
advertising of alcohol for which
Canadians get into hot water comes the
revolution anyone can drink McGuinness
vodka Alberta vodka is superimposed on
the picture of Cruiser Battleship Aurora
I don't know how many of you know that
this is a historical Relic in USSR the
revolution communist Bolshevik
Revolution started with the with the
cannon fired from that battleship
and obviously Soviet Embassy was
insulted so they sent a protest note to
Pure Trudeau and the picture was removed
from the magazine when I was teaching at
Carlton University in whatever my
superiors forced me to do an IQ test
with two groups of my students
the idea was to answer about four um 100
questions to give answer yes no or
undecided the more undecided or negative
answers you give the more according to
the compilers of this test you are
adaptable and useful to society
the more positive answers you give the
more questionable is your adaptability
and and usefulness for for your country
this is explanation how to score how to
count the scores and now see the
questions telling dirty joke is bad a
good soldier is a patriot yes no or
undecided
think about it
every communist should be run out of the
country yes no or undecided
the Bible is the greatest source of
Truth
right
God is everywhere a person who kills
another person is a murderer yes no or
undecided
okay now
if you don't believe me come let's come
back see I I want to repeat you once
again the conditions of the scoring
the more undecided and negative answers
you give
the more you are adaptable and flexible
and useful for the society
do you understand what they are doing to
kids okay they are doing two things at a
time
they teach them moral relativism
they teach them how to light to get a
greatest score because obviously a child
would say if a person killed another
person he is a murder but for the sake
of getting a higher score obviously a
student would put no or undecided so you
teach your kid how to lie
to be successful and to look adaptable
and useful for society
well obviously I had to do that test but
I added one more question to that thing
my own question I said what kind of
society you are going to be useful to
and
most of my students give me an excellent
answer they say a society where there is
no moral principle nor respect to God
love family and working ethics very
simple they are not that stupid
here we are comrade
now this is the picture from a Soviet
magazine obviously a Soviet media tries
to project their leaders in the most
respectful way very impressive very
fatherly very serious person there is
nothing surprising what else is new of
course
but this is Time Magazine an American
Magazine
the caption is not quite clear but it
says basically that
comrade bresner doesn't give interview
to Time Magazine the message is clear
he's a positive caretaking person he's
too busy to take care of the world
problems and the economical problems in
Russia it's a very humorous caption but
nevertheless the impact if you are not
quite concerned about politics what is
your impression about this nice
gentleman
nice smiling tired well
and this is how media presents your
leaders
I I don't know whether
he deserves to be presented like that or
not this is a different question
this is Prime Minister of Great Britain
about 10 years ago together with Beatles
you may or may not like beetles me
personally I don't like them
but
a prime minister of a country together
with entertainers
the Queen Her Majesty Queen knighted
beetles a highest honor which previously
in all times was given only to the most
deserving Patriots of the British Empire
was given to a bunch of monkeys
[Applause]
is playing football he's our guy he
plays piano no that never mind what he
does for politics or world's problems he
is nice Charming
personality
Helmut Schmidt is taking part in in the
circus performance
nice charismatic leader never mind what
his policies are he's he's popular he's
in the section of people of Time
Magazine
first lady of United States together
with the pop singer fox fox song singer
well so what
you know we had a saying in Russia that
in all times
clowns were entertaining the royalty
today the mightiest of the world
think it's a privilege to appear with
entertainers
just the reverse of the old principle
you know they are the entertainers of
entertainers
because they want it for their political
career
Ed Kennedy dances in Moscow
why I mean is is that his business to to
to to go to USSR why doesn't he occupy
himself with something more relevant to
the urging problems of the world
he thinks he's going to be popular in
America maybe but in Russia they look at
him as a schmuck
Senator McGovern
is talking to a gorilla somewhere in
Africa not the gorilla monkey but a
young member of national patriotic
movement the movement which is
indoctrinated by the Soviets armed and
paid for
he thinks he's smart and he's something
to to admire I bet the guys who are
standing behind don't think this way at
all while Kissinger just by mistake is
here would you buy a second second-hand
car from this
here for though
prime minister of one of the most
developed industrial Nations independent
nation in the world
is befriended by Fidel Castro if you
remember Canada never stopped trade
relations with Cuba despite the ER
despite the um
urge from the United States government's
administrations to not to sell Cuba's
strategic technology and materials no he
wouldn't listen to the United States he
smiled at Fidel Castro meanwhile his
wife estranged wife Margaret Trudeau is
talking to Rockstar I forget his name
Rawlings that's it that's him right and
he is posing for pictures like that
that's the prime minister's wife
that's her too in French Riviera with
some Hollywood actor why
50 years ago
for a thing like that a prime minister
would have to resign
it's a shame for a nation
not anymore
it's another debatable question why we
are so happy comrade Nixon
what is so funny I would like to ask
yeah smile again why
he's standing next to a mass murderer
and he's smiling
why
Pierre true dolls attentively listens to
comrade presidents I don't know what
uh West German counselor is helping
comrade breznick to stand up because the
senile leader of Russia is unable to
stand up without Western Aid
oh you may you may say well it's best
Germans they're too close to Russia
probably they do it just in case
okay here's the same thing Carter is
helping the president of the mightiest
Empire mightiest power in the in the
world United States is helping comrade
Brazil if you remember the incident when
he the president almost stumbled down
uh down the staircase somewhere in
Vienna of course
and thanks to to Carter he didn't fall
uh Andrew Young is talking to a dictator
in in Africa
again
uh McGovern I think is talking to
augustino Neto a Soviet puppet in Luanda
why
is it that necessary to be friendly to
smile to each other
now we're coming to space from Earth to
space clouds over the Space Program why
clouds
minded this is after three or four
successful landing on moon
why clouds
okay here's two pictures left Soviet
Cosmonaut walking into the Kremlin hall
for for
ceremonious reception on the right
choose American cosmonof casually walk
watching TV
on the top Soviet politburo talking to
the space pilots on orbit
on the lower picture Lyndon Johnson with
um I think that's Glenn
an American spice without pilot
now even if you don't know anything
about the theory of information the
comparison minded this is a French
magazine it's not the Soviet propaganda
the comparison of the size of the
pictures gives you the message already
what is more important
what is more impressive
here a picture from Soviet newspaper
Pravda a Soviet school boy compares
two replicas of I mean replicas of
Soviet
soyuz spacecraft and American Apollo
friendship in Space the tongue right pay
attention to the size of the spacecraft
they are almost identical right
now this is
what the size almost actual size is the
American spacecraft is on the left
it's almost twice as big as the Soviet
one
right
okay this is a Soviet picture
this is an American picture with true
sizes
okay
you say well Soviet media of course
tries to diminish the successes of the
American Space Program now this is an
American Media
on the left a Soviet
moon walker or Soviet Probe on moon on
the right side an American space
Volkswagen as they say it actually was
used on the surface of moon the sizes
are almost identical right wrong
the thing on the left is the size of a
tea cattle
in other words about 100 times smaller
but Time Magazine does not explain it to
the readers
an average person in the United States
has an impression
that the junk on the left is as
important and as successful
as the as the Masterpiece of Technology
produced by American mind and ingenuity
okay you remember Sky lab
there was a time when it just about to
fall down on on United States or any
other country and the Pentagon was very
worried there were pictures there were
discussions on TV some strange
characters even started joking about it
see the Skylab Target
a lot of emotions expressed about the
failure of United States Sky lab
a lot of bitter opinions were expressed
about about the unnecessary spending on
on Space research
but when Soviet nuclear-powered
satellite following the territory of
Canada there was no protest
demonstrations there were nothing like
that
nowhere in the world ask yourself why
according to some information this was
not a satellite at all it was a flying
atomic bomb
Canadians spend something like 15
million dollars just to find the junk on
their own territory thanks God it felt
in inhabited areas of of Canada in
Northwest Territories where only
penguins live or what if it fell on
Toronto
a flying nuclear bomb
oh boy but no protests here Soviet
Ambassador Anatoly dobrinim happily
looking at the linking of American and
Soviet spacecraft in where in in
American
Grounds Control Center
this is a picture from Time Magazine
this is also a picture from Time
Magazine Soviet citizens are watching
the same moment linking of spacecraft
think about it
compare here happiness
on the right American representative of
the NASA
and the brillian very happy
that's how ordinary Soviet citizens
think about the farce in space
they understand perfectly well that
linking
spacecraft in space
is just a fake it doesn't mean anything
look at their faces
they are sad
foreign
was realized was it worth the price
pessimistic question right after all the
successes of American Space Program
immediate the media tries to instill in
your mind a doubt
pessimism
why
oh this is a frog
I don't know how much you know about
frogs I'll tell you that a frog
can see a mosquito only if it moves
across this the area of its vision
if a mosquito quietly sits on a grass
blade the frog doesn't notice it
that's the attitude of American Media
they do not notice problem unless it
moves and moves close to Hilton where
they stationed
these are the people
who make
file a suit against me if like if I call
them Liars but that's exactly what they
are they've been lying to you for years
and years about the situation in Vietnam
in Russia they were selling commercials
the other risers and cars
and they sold you a rotten information
this information of what happens in the
world
they have a vision of frog
but they look like semi-gods to you and
if I challenge their credibility
probably the people will call me a
paranoid or a very nasty person I may be
a nasty person but that's my opinion I
was a person who used to take this
people for a ride when I was working for
the service side
okay if you don't believe me here one of
the most conservatives news conservative
newspapers in this particular case it's
a Canadian newspaper the Globe and Mail
editorial page
nothing's nothing special right
the malaise of liberal democracies
saving Buddha former president of
Pakistan called priority and then there
is another article on the on the right
here U.S how to dominate Pacific
Russians claim well obviously somebody's
opinion right
nothing unusual for an average reader
Russians claim that United States ought
to dominate Pacific the idea is that
while the United States is obviously
aggressive and they want to dominate
something and Russians are unhappy about
it
somebody says
you read an article and
probably you may agree or disagree but
you have a feeling the message of
urgency
the nasty Americans again how to
dominate Pacific
now look who is the author Alexandra
malishkin novelty press agency
not a word who is Malaysian and what is
novice depressed agency
an average reader will accept this
article as a legitimate overt expression
of an ordinary journalist it is not an
opinion it's a fabrication by an
extension of KGB novice depressed
agencies Organization for which I work
for 12 years
this is highest example of dishonesty
and disinformation just one line more
would explain to an average reader what
is that that he is reading
but alas there is no explanation
now this is the monument to Mother
Russia in former Stalingrad now it is
Volga grad
the
the statue is designed to to instill
feeling of patriotism
and um
I don't know what else
Pride maybe for the motherland
these are the pictures of construction
uh High high-rise apartments in Moscow
glorious achievement of Soviet
technology
caviar as an average
some staple food of Russians
these are the the minks and and Furs
that Soviet citizens were
you know
that's how they look when they relax fat
nice ladies you know
you think it's Soviet propaganda
no comrades
this is also some Fashions latest
fashions from Russia right from Kremlin
for an average Soviet housewife
well obviously it doesn't take much
intelligence to understand that this is
not quite true and obviously it has
something to do with the Soviet
propaganda
the myths and the realities of the KGB
is if you don't see the
from Stalin to curse again the myth and
the realities by Avril Harmon a former
ambassador of the United States to USSR
very complimenting article to the Soviet
system
and this is where it comes from you
thought it was from a Soviet magazine
right no it's from Luke magazine an
American Magazine which published that
crap
if if you don't believe me I'll tell you
that I was a person who accompanied a
group of journalists from Luke magazine
when they came to Moscow on invitation
from novice to press agency I made them
to publish that thing
for which I was awarded I received the
bonus a free ticket to Italy for a week
now this this is look like sheer
high-class idiocy but unfortunately this
is exactly what happened
it it didn't took me much effort to
convince the Americans to tell the
American journalists from look magazine
to bring back this magazine to dedicate
the whole issue to the Glorious
anniversary of Soviet Revolution
[Music]
this is what you were reading in your
American Magazine
this is how an average American
perceived the Soviet way of life
a happy Soviet citizens
this is what an average girl in Russia
wears
this is what they eat and drink
this is how they build their apartment
houses
and this is how they are fiercely
patriotic
amazing anyway so
I will explain you how it all happens
the last two pictures
I will not commend I want you simply to
look close into these eyes
thank you this is the person who wants
to liberate you wanted at least not
anymore he's dead but there are many
other people with the same type of eyes
if I were a deeply religious person my
answer to that picture would be these
are the eyes
of Satan
he is
nice power right
United Nations celebrated back in 1969 I
think the 100th anniversary of his
birthday
the greatest leader of mankind
God forbid us to have leaders like that
well that's all
for that
[Applause]
subversion is the term if if you look in
a dictionary or criminal code to that
matter
usually his ex is explained as a part of
activity to destroy
things like religion government system
political economical system of a country
and usually it's linked to Espionage and
such romantic things as blowing up
Bridges side tracking trains
um clock and Dagger activity in
Hollywood style
uh
when what I'm going to talk about now
has absolutely nothing to do with the
cliche of espionage
or KGB activity of collecting
information
so the greatest mistake
or mis misconception I think is that
whenever we are talking about KGB for
some strange reason
starting from Hollywood Movie Makers to
professors of political science and
quote unquote experts on on Soviet
Affairs or criminologists as they call
themselves
they think that the most desirable thing
for andropov and the whole KGB is to
steal blueprints of some supersonic jet
bring it back to Soviet Union and
sell it to the Soviet military
industrial complex
it's only partly true if if we take the
whole time money
and Manpower that the Soviet Union and
KGB in particular spans
outside of USSR border
we will discover of course there are no
official statistics unlike with CIA or
FBI the the Espionage as such
occupies only 10 to 15 percent
of money time and Manpower 15 percent
of the activity of KGB
first 85 percent
is always
subversion
and unlike a dictionary of English
Oxford dictionary subversion in Soviet
terminology means always a destructive
aggressive activity aimed to destroy
the country Nation or geographical area
of your enemy
so there's no Romantics in there
absolutely no blowing up Bridges no
microfilms in Coca-Cola cans nothing of
that sort no James Bond nonsense
it's most of this activity is overt
legitimate
and easily observable if you give
yourself time and trouble to observe it
but according to the law and and law
enforcement systems of the western
civilization it's not a crime exactly
because of misconception manipulation of
terms we think that subverter is a
person who is going to blow up our
beautiful bridges
no subverter is a student who come for
exchange a diplomat an actor an artist a
journalist like myself was 10 years ago
now subversion
is an activity which is a two-way
traffic
you cannot subvert an enemy which
doesn't want to be subverted
if you know history of Japan for example
before 20th century Japan was a closed
Society
the moment a foreign boat comes to the
shores of Japan the Imperial Japanese
Army politely tell them to get lost
and if American salesman comes to the
shore of Japan let's say 60 or 70 years
from now back and says oh I have a very
beautiful vacuum cleaner for you no with
the good financing it says please leave
us with the media vacuum cleaner
if they don't leave they shoot them
to preserve their culture ideology
Traditions values intact
you were not able to subvert Japan
you cannot subvert Soviet Union because
the borders are closed the media is
censored by the government the
population is controlled by the KGB and
internal police
with all the beautiful glossy pictures
of Time Magazine and magazine America
which is published by by the American
Embassy in Moscow you cannot subvert
Soviet citizens because the magazine
never reaches Soviet citizens
it's collected from the new stance and
thrown to garbage can
subversion can be only successful when
the initiator the actor the act the
agent of subversion
has
a responsive Target
it's a two-way traffic
United States is a receptive Target of
subversion
there is no response
similar to that one from United States
to the Soviet Union
it stops halfway somewhere it never
reaches here
the theory of subversion goes all the
way back
2500 years ago
the first human being
who formulated the tactics of subversion
was a Chinese philosopher by the name of
Sansa
two 3 500 years BC
it was an advisor
for several Imperial courts in ancient
China
and he said after long meditation
that
to implement
foreign to implement State policy
in a warlike manner
it's the most
counterproductive barbaric and
inefficient to fight on a Battlefield
you know that war is continuation of
State policy right so if you want
successfully to implement your state
policy
and you start fighting this is the most
idiotic way to do it the highest Arc of
warfare is not to fight at all
but to subvert anything of value in the
country of your enemy until such time
that the perception of reality of your
enemy is screwed up to such an extent
that he does not perceive you as an
enemy and that your system
your civilization and your for ambitions
look to your enemy as an alternative if
not desirable then at least feasible
better red than dead
that's the ultimate purpose the final
stage of subversion after which you can
simply take your enemy without a single
shot being fired
if the subversion is successful this is
basically what subversion is
as you see not the single mentioning of
blowing up bridges of course Sansa
didn't know about blowing up Bridges
maybe there were not that many bridges
at that time
but
but a subversion is being taught to
every student of KGB School in USSR and
to offices of military academies
I'm not sure if the same author is
included in the list of reading for
American officers
to say nothing about ordinary students
of political science
I had difficulty to find the translation
of sunset in in the library of a
university in Toronto and later on here
in Los Angeles
but it's a it's a book which is not
available
it is forced to every student in USSR
every student who is who is thought to
be dealing further in in his future
career with foreigners
what subversion is basically it consists
of four periods
time wise if we start from here and go
this way time right this is the
beginning point the first stage of
subversion is the process which is
called basically demoralization
says for itself what it is
it takes from
say 15
to 20 years to demoralize a society
why why 15 or 20 years
this is the time
sufficient to educate one generation
of students or children one generation
one lifetime span of a person a human
being
which is dedicated to study
to shaping up the Outlook ideology
personality
no more no less
usually it takes from 15 to 20 years
what it includes it includes
influencing or by various methods
infiltration uh propaganda methods
direct contacts doesn't really matter I
will describe them later
of various areas where public opinion is
formulated or shaped
religion
educational system
social life
Administration
law enforcement system military of
course
and labor and employer relations
economy okay
five areas
I will not write them down because we'll
not have enough space
some sometimes when I describe all the
methods uh students ask me question
are you sure this is the result of the
Soviet influence not necessarily
you see the tactic of subversion about
which I'm talking is similar to the
martial art the Japanese martial art
if you're if some of you are familiar
with that tactic probably you will
remember that if an enemy is bigger and
heavier than yourself it would be very
painful to resist his direct strike
if a heavier person wants to strike me
in the face it would be very naive and
counterproductive to stop his blow
the Chinese and Japanese
Judo art tells us what to do first to
avoid the strike then to grab the Fist
and continue his movement
in the direction where it was before
right until the enemy crashes in the
wall
you see so what happens here
the target country
obviously does something wrong
if it's a free Democratic Society there
are many different movements within the
society
they're obviously in every society
there are people who are against this
Society there may be simple criminals
ideologically in disagreement with the
with the state policy conscientious
enemies simply psychotic personalities
who are against anything
right and finally there are small group
of Agents of a foreign Nation
bought
subverted
recruited right
the moment all these movements
will be directed in One Direction right
this is the time to catch that movement
and to continue it
until the movement
forces the whole society into collapse
into crisis right so that's exactly the
martial art tactic we don't stop an
enemy we let him go we help him to go in
the direction we want them to go okay
so on the stage of demoralization
obviously there are tendencies in each
Society in each country
which are going
to opposite direction from the basic
moral values and principles to take
advantage of these movements to
capitalize on them is the main purpose
of the originator of subversion
so we have religion we have education
we have a social life
we have power structure
we have Labor Relations
unions and finally we have Law and Order
one two three four five six okay these
are the areas of application of
subversion what it means exactly
in case of religion destroyed
ridicule it
replace it with various sex cults which
bring people's attention Faith whether
it is naive primitive doesn't really
matter as long as the basically accepted
religious Dogma
is being slowly eroded
and taken away from the Supreme purpose
of religion to keep people in touch with
with the Supreme Being that serves the
purpose therefore replace it accepted
respected
religious organizations with fake
organizations
distract people attention from the real
faith and attract them to various
different faces
education
distract them from learning something
which is constructive pragmatic
efficient
instead of mathematics physics foreign
languages chemistry teach them history
of urban Warfare
natural food
home economy your sexuality
anything long as it takes you away
okay uh social life
replace traditionally established
institutions and organizations with fake
organizations
take away the initiative from people
take away the responsibility from
naturally established links between
individuals group of individuals and
Society at large and replace them with
artificial bureaucratically controlled
bodies
instead of social life and friendship
between Neighbors
establish social workers
institutions they're people who are on
payroll of whom
Society no bureaucracy
the main concern of social workers is
not your family not you not social
relations different groups of people the
main concern is to get the paycheck
from the government
what will be the result of their social
work doesn't really matter
they can develop all kind of Concepts
to show them to show to the government
and to the people that they're useful
okay away from the natural links power
structure okay the natural bodies of
administration
which are traditionally either elected
by
by people at large or appointed by
elected leaders of society are being
actively substituted by artificial
bodies
the bodies of people groups of people
whom nobody elected
Never As a matter of fact most of the
people
don't like them at all and yet they
exist
one of such group is Media who elected
them
how come how come they they face they
they have so much power almost
monopolistic power on your mind they can
rape your mind but who elected them how
come they are they have a nerve to
decide what is good and what is bad for
for the elected by you president and his
administration who the hell are they
uh
Spiro Agnew who was hated by the liberal
left called them a bunch of in feebled
snobs and that's exactly what they are
they think they know they don't say the
level of mediocracy
in a big establishment like New York
Times Los Angeles Times major television
network you don't have to be excellent
journalists
you have to be exactly a mediocre
journalist that's easier to survive
there's no competition anymore you have
your good nice income one hundred
thousand dollars a year that's it
whether you are better or worse doesn't
really matter anymore as soon as you're
smiling to the camera and do your job
that's it no more no more competition
power structure
slowly is eroded by the bodies and
groups of people who do not have neither
qualification nor the will of people
to keep them in power and yet they do
have power
okay together with that there is another
process
law enforcement law and order
organization and structure is being
eroded
for the last 20 25 years you you if you
see old movies and new movies you can
see that in new movies a policeman an
officer of the United States Army looks
dumb angry and psychotic paranoid
a criminal looks nice kind of well he
smokes hash and and shoots the whatever
drug but basically he's a nice human
being he's creative
and he's unproductive only because
Society oppresses him whereby a general
pentagon is always by definition a dumb
a war maniac
a policeman is a pig Road policeman he
abuses his power
no a generality generalization like that
the hatred the mistrust to the people
who supposed to protect you and enforce
Law and Order moral relativity the
Angela Warner process lasted two years
in Los Angeles
and yet there are still some lawyers who
say look
he's a nice character as a matter of
fact there was some witness who said
also a criminal who said well he's a
nice guy I asked him one day to burn a
house of my enemy and he wouldn't do it
a slow substitution of basic moral
principles
whereby a criminal is not a criminal
actually he's a defendant
even if his skill is proven
there is still a doubt
to kill or not to kill to be or not to
be thy shall not kill yes
but this line may not necessarily be
applicable to a murderer
thy shall not murder that should be the
the presumption not not that thy shall
not kill okay Labor Relations
at this stage within 15 to 20 years
we destroy the
traditionally established Links of
bargaining between employer and employee
the classical Marxist leninist
theory of natural exchange of goods
uh
a person a has five sacks of grain and
person B has five pairs of shoes
and the natural exchange without money
is when they bargain between each other
and only with the introduction of the
third four C
an entirely third foreign stranger who
says no don't give him five sacks of
brain give it to me and you give me your
five pairs of shoes and I will
distribute it accordingly
so the economy will go
this is the death of natural exchange
that death of natural bargaining well
trade unions were established 100 years
ago the objective was to improve working
conditions and to protect the rights of
workers from those employers who were
abusing
they're they're right because they had
more money
objectively at that time initially the
Trade union movement did work what we
see now
is that the bargaining process is no
longer resulting into in the compromise
which is leading objectively to
betterment of working conditions and
increase of salary what we see
is that after each prolonged strike the
workers lose
even if they have 10 increase of their
salaries they cannot catch up due to
inflation and due to missed time
more than that millions of people suffer
from that strike
because economy now is interdependent
it's intertwined like one body
if previously Steel Workers say hundred
years ago could strike and nobody would
suffer now it's impossible anymore if a
garbage collector strikes today the rest
of the multi-million city is stinking I
mean there's no more service in Quebec
for example we had the electricians who
were on strike in the middle of winter
you can freeze your bottom and they
still weren't strike
did they catch up with the celery no
they lost who benefited the leaders of
Trade union
what is the motivation for stride
improving improving our workers
condition no no obviously it's not
then what is it
ID oh Lord G
to prove to these capitalists
and the obedient horde of workers like
sheep follow these people and they
cannot disobey why because if they do
you know what happens to them tickets
murders shooting truck drivers by
ticketers in Montreal for example I saw
with my own eyes when I was
correspondent of CBC International
Canadian Broadcasting Corporation when
the workers of aircraft Factory
destroyed computers and and the
equipment in the factory
and they the administration employed
strike Breakers their cars were turned
upside down and burned
their houses were burned their kids were
intimidated and some victims were there
of that you can be sure why
to improve conditions of workers no
ideology okay so this is what happens
basically
it may or may not happen without the
help of the Soviet Union
but the natural tendencies
are being greatly taken advantage of and
capitalized by the Soviet propaganda
systems how
whenever Trade union strikes we have
influx of propaganda mass media
ideological dissemination the workers
right and repeated like parrots yes
workers right who's rights workers no
the the only freedom of worker to sell
his labor according to his own desire
and will is taken away from him by whom
by Trade union boss
unlimited power is given responsibility
I want to sell my labor not for 250 an
hour but for two dollars I don't have
right
my freedom is denied to me
I know that if I sell my work for 200
for two dollars an hour not for three
dollars now I will compete better with
the other guy who is lazy and more
greedy I don't need to three dollars I
need only two dollars no I was made to
believe by media my business by
advertising agencies that I need more
and more and more have you ever heard
any advertising on TV to consume less
no no way
whether you need a six-cylinder car or
not you have to buy it and hurry up
when I was driving here on the local
radio station an excited announcer said
you hurry up rush and save save save
there's a plenty of houses sale
save
by buying more
of course of course it would be too
naive to expect that KGB makes that
advertising agency to do such a crazy
commercial no of course not
but what we did when I was working for
novelty pressing we would snow plow
editorial offices student organizations
religious groups with literature of
class struggle
May if if not directly Marxism
propaganda then
a propaganda of of a legitimate
aspirations of working class betterment
of Life equality equality mind you
President Kennedy once said people we
will make America to believe that people
are born equal
are people born equal
is there any mentioning in the Bible or
any other Holy scripture in any religion
any religion if you don't believe me go
to library and check it that is not a
single word about equality
just the opposite
by your Deeds God will judge you what
you do is important the Merit of your
personality
you cannot legislate equality if you
want to be equal you have to be equal
you have to deserve it
and yet we build our society on the
principle of equality we say people are
equal we know it is false it's a lie
some people are tall and stupid others
are short bold and clever
if we make them
if we make them equal by force
if we put the principle of equality in
the basis of our social political
structure
is the same thing as building a house on
sand
ER or later it will collapse and that's
exactly what happens
and we as Soviet propaganda makers are
trying to push you in the direction
which you go yourself equality yes
equality people are equal land of equal
opportunities
is it true or not think about it
equal opportunities should there be
equal opportunities for me
and for a lazy bastard who come here
from some other country and immediately
registers as a welfare recipient
benefits
I never received a single dot note sorry
I did visit once but I never applied for
welfare for the 13 years I took any job
security guard journalist Taxi Driver
anything
while I was restless but some people
don't like it they immediately so why
should we be why should we have equal
opportunities
why the equal opportunity to excel
equal opportunity in equal circumstances
yes but we know people are different so
Excel yes provided we reach the same
level of Excellency perfection
which is hypothetical distant future yes
maybe
but we know perfectly well that even
with the best intentions people could
not be equal
why should we have equality in in the
say legal system myself
I'm considering myself a law abiding
citizen
and a person who comes here to Rob and
shoot say the United States
Administration on the card have imported
thousands of Cuban criminals
they were non-criminals
yet they were accepted
do you think it's fair if myself and my
wife from Philippines who work like a
excuse me horse as a lab technician in
the hospital should have the same rights
as a criminal film from Cuba
why
and yet we repeat as parents equality
equality equality
and the Soviet propaganda system helps
us to believe that equality is something
which is desirable democracy as it was
established by fathers of this country
of the system in the last century is is
not equality
is the system where different people
unequal people have a chance to survive
and help each other
in constant competition
in constant perfection
not inequality which is superimposed
from from a Godfather or nice person in
Washington DC
and the absolute equality exists in
Soviet Union quote unquote equality
everybody is equally in dirt
except some people are more equal than
the others in politburo so
the moment you you bring a country to
the point of almost thought of
demoralization when nothing works
anymore when you are not sure whether it
is right or or wrong good and bad but
there's no division between evil and
good when even the leaders of church
sometimes say well violence for the sake
of Justice especially social justice is
Justified in the countries like
Nicaragua El Salvador well maybe
Rhodesia
and we listen to them and say yeah
probably it's true is it true no it is
not true violence is not justified
especially for the sake of quote unquote
social justice introduced by Marxist
leninist that is my former College
from novice to press agency okay so
where is that point the next step is
destabilization
again this word says for itself what it
is to destabilize all the relations all
the accepted institutions and
organizations in a country of your enemy
how you do it
you don't have to send a battalion of
KGB agents to blow up Bridges no you let
them do it themselves
the area of application is again it's
it's narrower now
not like the previous case the overt
legitimate actions of the of the KGB in
this case
would be hardly noticeable there is no
crime if a professor who recently went
to USSR introduces a course of marxist
leninism in in a Californian college for
example nobody is going to to come to
his doorstep and say okay Mister come
you're on the rest no it's not a crime
it's not even considered a moral crime
against your country
so the area of application here is
narrowing down to economy
again Labor Relations right
so Law and Order
plus military
and uh
economy Law and Order yes and again the
uh media but why the scope little bit
different I'll explain again
okay basically three areas economy
the
radicalization of bargaining process
if on that stage
we still could achieve theoretically
some positive compromise between the
negotiating sides with with uh say
the arbitrary introduction of arbitrary
judges a third side objectively judging
the demands of both sides here it's
radicalization
on this on the stage of destabilization
we cannot come to compromise even within
a family the husband and wife couldn't
figure out which is better husband wants
his kids to eat at the table and wife
wants him a child to roam around the
room and and drop food all over the
floor they cannot come to compromise
unless they start a fight
it's impossible to reach a compromise
constructive compromise between
Neighbors some people say I don't like
you to watering you alone at that time
because exactly at that time I'm walking
my dog and he's getting nervous he
cannot pass his bowels you know so they
cannot compromise they go to
a a civil court or something like that
radicalization of human relations no
more compromise fight fight fight
the normal traditionally accepted
relations are destabilized
the relations between teachers and
students
in schools and colleges fight
the relations between an economical
sphere between
laborers and and employers are further
radicalized
no more acceptance of the legitimacy of
Demands of workers
unlike Japanese where the theories if
you ever heard about it whether workers
are involved in decision-making process
therefore they don't have moral
incentive to to fight their uh their
bosses in the United States is just the
opposite the harder is the the fight the
better the more heroic they look when
the Greyhound network was on strike
recently the correspondence of local TV
networks all over the United States
were approaching these Strikers and they
say oh yes we are doing something nice
they look like Heroes and they were
proud there was some family uh the
husband was a bus driver now they
decided in in in a protest against the
uh bosses to Camp somewhere in the
forest
and they were presented to the to the
audience as as a heroic nice people
you see
the violent clashes between passengers
ticketers and and the strikers are
presented as something normal
10 15 20 years ago we would we would be
we would be angry say why why why so
much hatred
today we are not we say well
commonplace radicalization
militarization sometimes as I explained
on that stage I took a step a little bit
further shooting people okay Law and
Order now
also is
uh pushed into the area where previously
people settle their differences uh
peacefully and legitimately
now
we are getting with this court cases in
the in this smallest irrelevant cases we
cannot solve our problems anymore
the society at large becomes more and
more antagonistic
within individuals between groups of
individuals and the society at Large
the media puts himself in the opposition
to the society in general at Large
separate alienated
okay
on that stage you remember I was talking
uh a couple of hours ago about the
sleepers
that's when the students from say United
States if they are trained in lumumba
University or developing nations that's
the students I was dealing with are
being sent back
from the Soviet Union here or if they
were already in the United States in the
country which is the object of
subversion they spring to action the
sleepers go up
they slept for 15 to 20 years
now they become leaders of groups
preachers
uh
I don't know Public public figures
prominently they act in they actively
include themselves in a political
process all of a sudden we see a
homosexual
15 years ago he did his dirty job and
nobody cared now he makes it a political
issue he demands recognition respect
human rights and hiral is a large group
of people and there are violent clashes
between him and police his group and
Ordinary People no matter what it's
black against white yellows again green
doesn't matter where's the vision line
goes as long as this group come into
antagonistic Clash sometimes militantly
sometimes with firearms that is
destabilization process the sleepers
many of whom are simply KGB agents
become leaders
of the process of destabilization
doesn't mean that comrade and drop of
sons comrade Ivanov the United States
the person who takes care is already
here
his respected citizen of United States
sometimes he he gets money from various
foundations for his legitimate
struggle for
I don't know human rights women rights
kid lib prison lib whatever
there are sympathetic Americans who
donate their money to him
this to be like this stabilization
process usually leads directly to the
process of crisis in case of developing
nations
does the area where I I was active the
process
starts
when
when the legitimate
bodies of power
the social structure collapse it cannot
function anymore
so instead we have artificial's body
injected into society such as
non-elected committees
you remember I was talking about them
here social workers who are not elected
by People Media who sell who are
self-appointed rulers of your opinion uh
some strange groups
which claim that they know how to lead
Society forward they don't usually all
they care is how to collect donations
and and prom and sell their own
concocted ideology mixture of religion
and ideology here we have all these
artificial's body claiming power
if the power is denied to them they take
it by force
in case of Iran for example all of a
sudden we have revolutionary committees
who what what kind of Revolution there
was no Revolution yet and yet they had
the Committees
they were taking power of judgment they
had they had the power of execution they
had the power of of legislation and that
they had the power of judicial all of
them combined in one person who is
half-baked intellectual sometimes
radiated from Harvard University or
Berkeley
he comes back to his country and then he
he thinks that he he knows the answer to
all the social economical problems
okay crisis is when Society cannot
function any more productively it
collapses obviously that's the word for
crisis
so therefore the population at Large
is looking for a savior
the religious groups are expecting a
messiah to come
the work is safe we have family to feed
let's have a strong government maybe
socialist government centralized when
when somebody put put their employers on
their place and and let us work we are
sick and tired of going to strike and
missing overtime and all that stuff we
need some strong man strong government a
leader
a savior is needed population is sick
and tired already
and here we are we have a savior either
a foreign Nation comes in or the local
group of of leftists marxists no matter
what they call themselves Sandinista
a reverend or some sort
Bishop Missouri like in in Zimbabwe
doesn't matter
a savior comes and says I will lead you
so we have two Alternatives here
Civil War
an invasion
okay
see how it goes
Civil War we know what it is Lebanon is
the best example
the Civil War which was artificially
implanted in Lebanon by injection of
force of PLO
Palestinian Liberation Organization
Invasion we have in many other countries
like Afghanistan
uh
name any East European country it was
invaded by the Soviet Army
but the result is the same the next
stage is normalization
normalization is a very ironic word of
course
it is borrowed from 1968 situation in
Czechoslovakia when the Soviet
propaganda and after them New York Times
declared the country is normalized the
tanks moved into Prague so there is no
more Prague spring there is no more
violence normal normalization
at that stage
the
self-appointed rulers of the society
don't need any Revolution anymore they
don't need any radicalism anymore so
this is the reverse from destabilization
basically it is stabilizing the country
by force
so all these sleepers and activists and
social workers and liberals
and homosexuals and professors and
Marxist and latinists are being
eliminated
physically sometimes
they've done their job already okay they
are not needed anymore
foreign
ERS need stability to exploit the nation
to exploit the country to take
advantages of the victory
okay so no more evolutionaries please
and that's exactly what happens in
number of countries you remember
Bangladesh this is the crisis in which I
was instrumental first they had mujibur
Rahman
in 1971 he was the leader of people's
party avami league with mustache like
Stalin he was in in Russia many times
in five years he was shocked by his
former colleagues marxists
he fulfilled His function in Afghanistan
it happened three times
because there was taraki then there was
Amin nowadays they killed each other
successively
one after another the moment he fulfills
his duty the first one demoralized
country the second destabilized the
third one brought it to crisis
goodbye comrade
Karma comes from Moscow and put in into
the seat of power
same thing happened in Granada recently
Maurice Bishop Marxist was killed by
Austin what's his name General something
who was also a Marxist
right
so no more revolutions please
normalization now from now on no more
strikes no more homosexual sexuals no
more women live no more kidly no more
lib period
good
Democratic proletarian freedom
now to reverse this process
takes enormous effort
when today United States had to invade
Granada to reverse the process of
subversion some people say boy this is
not good it's not kosher to invade a
beautiful country the island of Granada
well why didn't you stop the process
here when Granada was just approached by
leftists
why not to prevent Maurice Bishop to
come in power in the first place did
grenades want him very questionable they
didn't know who was more respiration
from the first place he came to Power by
coup d'etat himself
okay nor will let the situation develop
further and further and further until
the crisis
and normalization very soon
and then United States decided to invade
country discovering that the country was
absolutely a military base for the
Soviet Union
of course it's a drastic measure of
course it's it's a Pity that Marine
Corps had to to lose what 17 lives very
bad
why not to stop the process before it
comes to crisis all no intellectuals
will not let you its interference into
domestic affairs they're very careful
not to not not to let American
Administration to interfere in domestic
affairs of Latin American countries they
don't mind Soviet Union interfere in
this Affairs
so to reverse this process from here it
takes only and always military force no
other force on Earth can reverse this
process at this point
at this point it does not take military
invasion of United States Army it takes
strong action like in Chile
a CIA called word involvement
to prevent the Savior from outside to
come into power
and to stabilize country before it
erupts into Civil War
okay support
the right-wing conservative forces by
money by Crooks so love doesn't matter
stabilize the can don't let the crisis
develop into into Civil War or invasion
oh no your liberals will say it's it's
against the law
the Congress will not appropriate money
for covert actions of CIA why not
should we wait till the normalization
come and Soviet tanks landed in in Los
Angeles Airport
now at that point at the point of this
stabilization also the process could be
reversed again easily than this no CIA
involvement at this point
you know what it takes here
restriction of some Liberties for small
groups which are self-declared enemies
of the society as simple as that
oh no the median liberals will tell you
this is against the American
Constitution
how can we
by force deny the civil rights to
criminals for example it's not good
okay so we allow them to okay if you
allow the criminals to have civil rights
go on and bring the country to the
crisis this is a bloodless way to do
curb the rights I mean not to put them
in prison no no I'm not talking about
putting all the gates from San Francisco
in the concentration camp do not allow
them to take political force
do not elect them to the seats of power
whether it is municipality level state
level or federal level
it has to be bitten in the heads of
American voters at a person like that in
the sense of power is an enemy
do not be afraid of this word it is an
enemy if he is not an enemy here he will
be here
later on he will be shot of course
but at this point he is an enemy okay
you are doing great service by denying
him a right
to capitalize on his own crazy ideas and
become a powerful man a man who uses the
seat of power
restriction of certain freedoms and
permissiveness at that point
would prevent
sliding into crisis and probably will
return the process of destabilization to
curb unlimited power monopolistic power
of trade unions here at that point would
save economy from collapsing
to introduce a law
to stop private companies of raping
public opinions mind
in the direction of consumerism
no company must have a right
to force you into buying more unless you
want it
there must be a law
you want to advertise your your car okay
but not a single mentioning of buying it
now and saving money
must be against the law to force people
to consume more
self-restrained
previously before this process started
the self-restraint
was a business of church religion
because our preachers the fathers of
church would tell us
material values are good but it's not
the prime function of human being
because you have to live with something
obviously the design for our life is not
to consume more deodorants
there must be something greater if such
a complicated instrument this human body
was created obviously there must be some
higher purpose for that
and it's very easy to
by deny
deny greedy companies one little Freedom
one little liberty forcing you into
turning yourself into processors of
unwanted products and goods
they turn you into machines
like uh the worm who there's Inlet and
outlets and
how long an average appliance lasts
these days
less than a year why
where's workmanship or we want you to
buy more okay this stabilization process
could be easily overcome if as I say
the society
by its own will or after persuasion by
the leaders
will come to the idea of self-restrained
it's so hard we want to consume more but
you have to
unless you will come to this stage when
as we say in Russia if Sahara Desert
ever becomes a communist state there
will be shortage of sand
so you have to curb your
you have to you have to curb your
expectations at this point
before it's too late but no we don't
want to do it
demolition process again it's the
easiest thing to reverse
first of all
by restricting import of propaganda the
easiest thing to do
unlimited unrestrained import of Soviet
literature Soviet journalists
uh giving solids propaganda and
ideological agitators equal time on
American TV network
it has to be stopped
and it's easy they won't they won't be
offended minded as a matter of fact they
will respect America more
but then my former colleague Vladimir
Posner appears on Nightline and Ted kof
will ask him well Jim what do you think
about this and what can he think he's an
instrument of propaganda he thinks what
what comrade and drop off tells him to
think
he's just a nice articulate mouthpiece
of the Soviet subversion system and that
couple makes you believe that my friend
Vladimir Posner thinks
the process of demoralization may not
have started at all if at that point
the country
which is a recipient of subversion
actively
not violently but actively prevents
importation of foreign ideology
I don't want America to follow the
pattern of ancient Japan you don't have
to shoot every Foreigner when It
approaches the sacred borders of the
United States
but when he offers you a junk in the
disguise of very shiny something
you have to tell him no we have our own
junk
if at that point
the society is strong Brave and
conscientious enough
to stop impartation of ideas which are
foreign
then the whole chain of events could be
prevented
recently I've been to Philippines and I
was shocked
how invix it is like Manila children
listen to deafening music
a melodious
Nation with long traditions of good nice
ethnic music introduced by Spanish long
time ago maybe two centuries three
centuries ago I don't remember all of a
sudden listen to musical garbage
sing their radios at full blast at the
full volume why
in India I spent many years
watching the reactions of Indians
walking out of movie theaters after
seeing Hollywood production
they they couldn't figure out why
Americans are so wasteful they smashed
their cars their shiny cars every five
minutes how come they shoot each other
for half million dollars
is it true that they are so sexy
I mean obsessed with sex
can you imagine showing a movie where
each five minutes there's a copulation
on the screen to a country like India
with long Traditions tradition of of
respect to this private matter is or to
Pakistan
and United States expect these people to
respect you
no way oh yes they will see the movie
they'll pay five Rupees to see that
garbage but they walk out and will tell
their kids don't
respect Americans don't be like
Americans
see so the process of demoralization
could be stopped right here
both as an expert and as an emperor and
that takes one step one very important
thing to do you don't have to expel all
the KGB Agents from Washington DC
the most difficult and at the same time
the simplest answer
to the subversion is to start it here
and even before
by bringing back the society to religion
something that you cannot touch and eat
and put on yourself
but something that rules society and
makes it move and preserve it
a Soviet scientist
who has nothing to do with religion he
is a computer scientist
did a very intensive research on the
history of socialist countries
he calls socialist or Communists any
country with the centralized economy and
the pyramidal style of power structure
and he discovered
actually he didn't Discover it he just
brought to attention of his readers that
civilizations like Mohenjo-daro
in the river Hindus area
like Egypt like Maya Incas
like
Babylonian culture collapsed and
disappeared from the surface of
the moment they lost religion
as simple as that they disintegrated
nobody remembers about them anymore well
distantly
so
the ideas are moving society and keeping
mankind as as a society of human beings
intelligent
moral agents of God
the facts the truth the exact knowledge
may not
all the sophisticated technology and
computers will not prevent Society from
disintegrating and eventually dying out
have you ever met a person who would
sacrifice his life freedom
for the truth like that
this is truth
I never met the person who said this is
truth and I'm ready to shoot me
to defend the truth hey
but Millions sacrifice their life
Freedom comfort
everything
for things like God
like Jesus Christ
it's an horn
some Martyrs in the Soviet concentration
camp died
and they died in peace
unlike those who shouted Long Live
Stalin knowing perfectly well that he
may not live long
something which is
not Material
moves society and helps it to survive
and the other way around the moment we
turn into two by two is four
and make it a guiding principle of our
life our existence
we die
even though this is true and this we
cannot prove
we only can feel and have faith in it
so the answer to ideological subversion
strangely enough is very simple you
don't have to shoot people you don't
have
to aim missiles and pershings and cruise
missiles at on drop of headquarters
you simply have to have faith
and prevent subversion
in other words
not to be a victim of subversion
don't try to be a person who in Judo is
trying to smash your enemy and being
caught by your hand
don't strike like that strike with the
power of spirit and moral superiority
if you don't have that power it's high
time to develop it
and that's the only answer
thank you
[Applause]
can you describe how a concept is
formulated turned into propaganda and
then ends up on someone's bumper sticker
or in a newspaper what's the
step-by-step process the other thing is
how close is the put Bureau to the
actual propaganda creating process and
finally uh the 007 incident was notable
in the fact that it took a long time
before the Soviets responded to it and
then the military took the lead in terms
of explaining what had happened rather
than the political organs and I wanted
to know why that actually happened okay
now the propaganda concepts are not
being developed they have been developed
long time ago there's nothing basically
new in the concept of overall propaganda
methods and goals
the ultimate goal however ridiculous it
may sound or primitive or simplistic is
the world domination
many people
many experts in foreign policy would
ridicule my opinion but this is what it
is I saw it with my own eyes I was a
part of that
so and my father was I think I mentioned
that before he was a inspector of land
forces he traveled all over the world
where the Soviet troops were stationed
so he knows perfectly well that the
troops are not stationed there to
collect Harvest for Cubans
or or to help afghanis to
to develop the uh what the chords of
cattle or with goats they are there for
one purpose world domination
the concepts the immediate issues or
problems are created of course
for propaganda purposes and they end up
as a bumper stickers
probably not uh long uh it takes really
short period of time
unlike some other things in in the
Soviet system
propaganda takes propaganda is one of
the things that they don't save money on
and there is a huge apparatus of
propagandam experts in USSR known as The
Press agency is just one of them one of
the organizations but the part with them
that there is a Department of Education
and propaganda
with this within the Central Committee
there are faceless people names of whom
you will never learn uh they're kind of
classified
uh I didn't explain you the methods
today because it will take us another
day the methods include such thing as
semantic manipulation
the words and expressions are being
coined at the rate of five
Expressions a minute by extremely clever
educated experts
and the media outside of USSR obediently
repeats this cliche I give you just
several examples not not to take your
time not to bore you to death okay I
mentioned one thing United Nations the
expression was invented by the Soviet
propaganda experts not by Americans
we know perfectly well it's not United
and it has nothing to do with Nations
more than half of the delegations in
Yuan do not represent any Nation at all
they are disunited obviously
the United Nations had not been able to
solve a single military conflict nowhere
in the world
they provoked War yes they took part in
Wars but they didn't prevent expansion
of Communism or or they did not prevent
a single War anywhere so the true
expression the true term for United
Nations could be this United
bureaucracies
okay another cliche which was coined in
Moscow by experts of propaganda
National Liberation movement
it's not National because most of the
leaders
do do not necessarily belong to the
ethnic
Group which they lead
number one number two they are
unpatriotic and unnationalistic because
they they obey orders from a foreign
country USSR
okay they are trained in USSR they are
paid by the Soviet system and they work
in the interests of the Soviet system
Liberation whom they are liberating who
is being liberated
and movement movement we understand
there's something which moves
unlike something which is static
National Liberation does not move it's a
war
if you if you call War movement probably
but it has nothing to do with the
concept of movement in in American
terminology means a legitimate overt
organized voluntary
uh movement right I presume your your
church or your organization is voluntary
nobody keeps you here by force
okay National Liberation movement is an
army of Bandits professional Bandits
which are kept kept in within the
framework of the movement by force
if they betray it's like in Mafia
they're going to be executed
okay another example of semantic
manipulation
is uh okay
um
free medical aid for example
you think it's it's an American
Democratic expression no way this the
journal was coined by by the Communists
long time ago at the time of commentary
there is nothing free in this world
everybody knows it
list of all Medical Aid it's very
expensive thing to render medical
assistance to other people too
Somebody Sometime somewhere has to pay
for who taxpayer
all this there are many other things
that are being coined by by the Soviet
propaganda apparatus unfortunately see
if I call myself a genius
a genius writer for example
Los Angeles Times would not call me that
right they'll call me a strange crazy
Russian who calls himself a genius
hell they call Liberation movements what
what what they call themselves
just because they are men
the logic is Twisted
um
they
stickers on on the bumpers I don't know
it it depends on the ability of local
forces to
toe up to the foreign policy how close
is police Bureau to to implementation of
propaganda actions very distant see
police Bureau is a group of self-imposed
dictators
they don't really decide anything
the only objective of the existence in
their life and their struggle is to stay
in power
unlike American politician who has two
objectives first to be elected and
second to be re-elected
so the soil
the Soviet politician doesn't have the
first objective
he does not have to be elected
he just makes his way in the parking
structure all the way up the election
doesn't bother him at all so the only
purpose of his life is to stay where he
is and Don't Rock the Boat
they don't make decisions the
decision-making level are the faceless
group of experts as I as I try to
explain to you and they the the police
Bureau gives only the basic directions
what to be done and the obedient
Servants of the highest caliber
intellectuals are beautifully developing
these things
some independently thinking Progressive
academics in the United States think
that comes socialism they will be able
to preserve the integrity and
Independence it's wishful thinking there
will become obedient Servants of the
system that they are trying to force
upon you
the Korean airliner incident
from my viewpoint is not an incident at
all I believe it's it's a it's a
carefully planned
and premeditated provocation
I'm not sure whether they did it they
killed to 268 people just to get rid of
Larry McDonald but it's feasible I
wouldn't be surprised if they killed
more than 60 millions of their own men
just to implement
growth and ideas of marks and angles you
know what what what would 2168 people
matter
second it is not a military blunder and
and the order was not given by military
never a single military officer of a
highest caliber will take responsibility
to shoot a civilian airliner my father
was an officer of general staff of the
Soviet Army I know perfectly well what
I'm talking about no officer would take
responsibility it'll be short tomorrow
you're kidding it's the order was given
by a civilian by party apparatchik of a
highest caliber and I wouldn't be
surprised it was androco in any case a
drop of knew perfectly well what goes on
what goes on what went on
the Soviet power structure resembles a
triangle unlike a love triangle in in
real life drama it's a hate triangle
the the seats of Power are party
Communist Party
Elite of course not the rank and file
party but the top of the pyramid the KGB
and the military they hate each other
and each of them hate the other two
the more
the most powerful is the party this is
the real power
the Army and the KGB supposedly are
Servants of the party and the tools the
instruments of their power but in fact
sometimes they are the power themselves
andropov belongs to the most hated
triangle the KGB my father hated KGB
because he was military
both of them KGB and Military hate the
party why
because unlike in the United States
the party is the most adventuristic
people they want to invade countries
they give the orders for all kind of
Adventures outside of ussrb waters
they know perfectly well that comes War
they will go to bankers and eat caviar
and enjoy life whereby military will
burn in flames of nuclear war
was against Invasion into Czechoslovakia
because he knew that
he will have to demoralize his Army and
the first two divisions after facing the
reality and seeing that Czechoslovakia
is not being invaded by Americans will
get corrupted so you have to replace
them with other two divisions and if you
stay long enough you will corrupt the
whole Soviet Army he said no don't
invade your Slovakia but comrade
yourself who the hell they are they
think they they deserve more sausages
and butter so show them tanks so he did
he obeyed
uh the the KGB the KGB and the Army
sometimes are in cahoots against the
party the recent rumor that andropo was
shot
by son of Brezhnev is an indication that
the the other two corners of the power
structure
were really sick and tired of of the of
the andropos KGB purges
you know they were purges the many
people lost their jobs and some were
arrested and some committed suicide in
the span of some ten
ten months since I'm drop off a sentence
to power so that gives you an idea of
the Korean airliner incident is
premeditated provocation to create an
international pension
because the only power on Earth which is
interested in provoking conflicts and
preserving tension is the Soviet junta
that's the only justification of them
being in power if there is no enemy
outside they have to create him
if there is no word they have to provoke
it
to scare the hell out of taxpayers
inside
and to keep themselves in power
there are so many theories one of them
is expressed by I wouldn't say a friend
of mine but I know he made it there's
another Defector Nikolai
who defected long time before I even
joined KGB
he was also a KGB in Western Europe
now he is teaching psychology in one of
California universities he thinks that
the Soviet Union developed
ESP would you believe it system of
influencing the perception and minds of
people
and the the generators of ESP willpower
can be focused on individuals and groups
of individuals so efficiently that you
can literally Focus that beam or
whatever it is
on a pilot or two pilots or three pilots
and convince them that actually they're
flying on the safe territory so there is
no need you can convince them that
there's no need to to contact the the
ground base station
and you can
artificially draw the plane by brain
wave into the Soviet airspace whether it
is true or not I don't know but I know
one thing that when I was a student and
I graduated from Oriental Studies
Institute one of my friends he was a
extremely intelligent Jewish boy he
graduated from the mathematical
Department of Moscow State University
after three years I returned from India
for for vacation and I met him in the
on during the reception at the Academy
of Science and I say what are you doing
here he said I'm working in a secret
research Bureau
you know the secret which means
basically defense industry they don't
have addresses they have post box number
and I say if it's not is it that much
secret that you cannot tell me what your
research you said you wouldn't believe
me brain veins
and I never saw him again
ESP which officially in the Soviet media
is
described as a pseudoscience and
decadent capitalist gimmick to Sidetrack
the minds of proletariat from the real
issues of class struggle but obviously
KGB takes seriously that
pseudo signs
[Applause]