subversion is the term if if you look in
in a dictionary or criminal code to that
matter
usually is ex is explained as a part
of activity to destroy
things like religion government system
political economical system of a country
and usually it's linked to espionage and
such romantic things as blowing up
bridges
side tracking trains
clock and dagger activity in hollywood
style
when what i'm going to talk about now
has
absolutely nothing to do with the cliche
of espionage or kgb activity of
collecting information
so the greatest mistake or mis
misconception i think is that
whenever we are talking about kgb for
some strange reason
uh starting from hollywood movie makers
to professors of political science
and quote-unquote experts on soviet
affairs or
cremonologists as they call themselves
they think that
the most desirable thing for andropov
and the whole kgb
is to steal blueprints of some
supersonic jet
bring it back to soviet union and
sell it to the soviet military
industrial complex
it's only partly true if if we take
the whole time money
and manpower that the soviet union
and kgb in particular spends
outside of ussr border we will discover
of course there are no official
statistics unlike with cia or fbi
but the espionage as such
occupies only 10 to 15
of money time and manpower
of the activity kgb the rest
85 is always
subversion and unlike a dictionary
of english oxford dictionary subversion
in soviet terminology
means always a destructive aggressive
activity
aimed to destroy the country
nation or geographical area of your
enemy
so there's no romantics in there
absolutely no blowing up bridges no
microfilms in coca-cola cans
nothing of that sort no james bond
nonsense
it's most of the this activity is overt
legitimate and easily
observable if you give yourself time and
trouble to observe
it but according to the law
and and law enforcement systems of the
western civilization it's not a crime
exactly because of misconception
manipulation of terms
we think that subverter is a person who
is going to blow up
our beautiful bridges no
subverter is a student who come for
exchange a diplomat
an actor an artist a journalist like
myself
was 10 years ago
now subversion
is an activity which
is a two-way traffic
you cannot subvert an enemy which
doesn't want to be subverted
if you know history of japan for example
before 20th century japan was a closed
society
the moment a foreign boat comes to the
shores of japan
the imperial japanese army politely tell
them to get lost
and if american salesman comes to the
shore of japan
let's say 60 or 70 years from now back
and says oh i have a very beautiful
vacuum cleaner for you
you know with the good financing please
leave us we don't need your vacuum
cleaner
if they don't leave they shoot them
to preserve their culture ideology
traditions
values impact
you were not able to subvert japan
you cannot subvert soviet union because
the borders are closed
the media is censored by the government
the population is controlled by the kgb
and internal police with all the
beautiful glossy pictures of time
magazine
and magazine america which is published
by by the
uh american embassy in moscow you cannot
subvert soviet citizens because the
magazine never reaches
soviet citizens it's collected from the
new stamps and thrown to garbage can
subversion can be only successful when
the
initiator the actor the act the agent of
subversion
has a responsive target
it's a two-way traffic united states
is a receptive target of subversion
there is no response similar to that one
from united states to the soviet union
it stops halfway somewhere it never
reaches here
the theory of subversion goes all the
way back
2 500 years ago
the first human being who formulated
the tactics of subversion was a chinese
philosopher
by the name of sunset
to 3500 years bc
it was an advisor for several imperial
courts in
ancient china and he said
after long meditation that
to implement foreign to implement
state policy in a warlike manner
it's the most counterproductive barbaric
and inefficient to fight on a
battlefield
you know that war is continuation of
state policy right so if you want
successfully to implement your state
policy
and you start fighting this is the most
idiotic way to do it
the highest arc of warfare is not
to fight at all
but to subvert anything of value in the
country of your enemy
until such time that the perception of
reality of your enemy
is screwed up to such an extent that he
does not perceive you as an enemy
and that your system your civilization
and your for ambitions
look to your enemy as an alternative
if not desirable then at least visible
better red than dead
that's the ultimate purpose the final
stage of subversion after which you can
simply take your enemy without a single
shot being fired
if the subversion is successful this is
basically what subversion means
as you see not the single mentioning of
blowing up bridges of course sunset
didn't know about
blowing up bridges maybe there were not
that many bridges at that time
but the basics
of subversion is being taught to every
student
of kgb school in ussr and to offices of
military academies
i'm not sure if the same author is
included in the
list of breeding for american officers
to say nothing about ordinary students
of political science
i had difficulty to find the translation
of sunset
in in the library of a university
in toronto and later on here in los
angeles
but it's a it's a book which is not
available it is forced to every student
in ussr every student who is who is
taught to be dealing further in in his
future
career with foreigners
what subversion is basically it consists
of four
periods time wise
if we start from here and go this way
time right this is the beginning point
the first stage of subversion
is the process which is called basically
demoralization
says for itself what it is
it takes from um
say 15 to 20 years
to demoralize a society
why why 15 or 20 years this is the time
sufficient to educate one generation
of students or children one generation
one lifetime span of a person a human
being
which is dedicated to study to shaping
up
the outlook ideology personality
no more no less usually it takes from 15
to 20 years
what it includes it includes
influencing or by various matters
infiltration
uh propaganda methods direct contacts
doesn't really matter
i will describe them later of various
areas where public opinion is formulated
or shaped religion
educational system social life
administration law enforcement system
military of course and
labor and employer relations
economy okay five areas
uh i will not write them down because
will not have enough space
some sometimes when i describe all the
methods
uh students ask me question are you sure
this
is the result of the soviet influence
not necessarily
you see the tactic of subversion about
which i'm talking
is similar to the martial art the
japanese martial art
if you're if some of you familiar with
that tactic probably you will remember
that if
an enemy is bigger and heavier than
yourself
it would be very painful to resist his
direct
strike if a heavier person wants to
strike me in the face
it would be very naive and
counterproductive to stop his blow
the chinese and japanese judo
art tells us what to do first to avoid
the strike
then to grab the fist and continue his
movement
in the direction where it was before
right until the enemy crashes in the
wall
you see so what happens here
the target country obviously does
something wrong
if it's a free democratic society there
are many different movements within the
society
that obviously in every society
there are people who are against this
society they may be simple criminals
ideologically in disagreement with
with the state policy conscientious
enemies
simply psychotic personalities who are
against anything
right and finally they're a small group
of agents of a foreign
nation bought subverted
recruited right the moment
all these movements will be directed in
one direction
right this is the time to catch that
movement
and to continue it until the movement
forces the whole society into collapse
into crisis right
so that's exactly the martial art tactic
we don't stop an enemy we let him go
we help him to go in the direction we
want them to go
okay so on the stage of demoralization
obviously there are tendencies in each
society in each country which are going
to opposite direction from the basic
moral values and principles
to take advantage of these movements to
capitalize on them
is the main purpose of the originator of
subversion
so we have religion we have education
we have social life we have power
structure
we have labor relations unions and
finally we have
law and order one two three four five
six
okay these are the areas of application
of subversion
what it means exactly in case of
religion
destroy it ridicule it
replace it with various sex cults
which bring people's attention faith
whether it is naive primitive doesn't
really matter
as long as the basically accepted
religious dogma is being slowly eroded
and taken away from the supreme purpose
of religion to keep people
in touch with with the supreme being
that serves the purpose
therefore replaced accepted respected
religious organizations with fake
organizations
distract people attention from the real
faith
and attract them to various different
faiths
education distract them from learning
something which is constructive
pragmatic
efficient instead of mathematics physics
foreign languages
chemistry teach them history of urban
warfare
natural food uh
home economy your sexuality
anything as long as it takes you away
okay uh social life
replace traditionally established
institutions
and organizations with fake
organizations
take away the initiative from people
take away the responsibility
from naturally established links between
individuals group of individuals and
society at large
and replace them with artificially
bureaucratically controlled
bodies instead of social
life and friendship between neighbors
establish social workers
institutions the people who are on
payroll of whom
society no bureaucracy the main concern
of social workers is not your family not
you not social relations between groups
of people
the main concern is to get the paycheck
from the government what will be the
result of their social work doesn't
really matter
they can develop all kind of concepts
to show them to show to the government
and to the people that they're used for
okay away from the natural links
power structure okay the natural
bodies of administration which are
traditionally either elected by
by people at large or appointed by
elected leaders of society
are being actively substituted by
artificial bodies
the bodies of people groups of people
whom nobody elected
never as a matter of fact most of the
people
don't like them at all and yet they
exist
one of the such group is media who
elected them
how come how come they they face
they have so much power almost
monopolistic power on your mind
they can rape your mind but who elected
them how come
they are they have a nerve to decide
what is good and what is bad for
for the elected by you president and his
administration
who the hell are they
who was hated by the liberal left called
them
a bunch of enfield snobs and that's
exactly what they are
they think they know they don't say
the level of mediocracy in a big
establishment like new york times los
angeles time
major television network you don't have
to be excellent journalist
you have to be exactly a mediocre
journalist that's
easier to survive there's no competition
anymore you have your
good nice income 100 000
a year that's it whether you're better
or worse doesn't really matter anymore
as soon as you're smiling
to the camera and do your job
that's it no more no more competition
power structure slowly
is eroded by the bodies and groups of
people who
do not have neither qualification nor
the will of people
to keep them in power and yet they do
have power
okay together with that there is another
process
law enforcement law and order uh
organization and structure is being
eroded
for the last 20 25 years you you if you
see
old movies and new movies you can see
that in new movies
a policeman an officer of the united
states army looks
dumb angry psychotic paranoid
a criminal looks nice kind of well
he smokes hash and shoots the whatever
drug but basically he's a nice human
being
he's creative and he's unproductive only
because society oppresses him
whereby a general pentagon is always by
definition
a dumb a war maniac a policeman is a
big rude policeman he abuses his power
you know a generality generalization
like that
the hatred the mistrust to the people
who supposed to protect you
and enforce law and order moral
relativity
the angel of warner process lasted two
years in los angeles
relativity the angel of warner process
lasted two years in los angeles
and yet there are still some lawyers who
say look he's a nice character as a
matter of fact
there was some witness who said also a
criminal who said
well he's a nice guy i ask him one day
to burn a house of my enemy and he
wouldn't do it
[Laughter]
a slow substitution of basic moral
principles
whereby a criminal is not a criminal
actually
he's a defendant even if his guilt is
proven
there is still a doubt to kill or not to
kill to be or not to be
thai shall not kill yes but
this line may not necessarily be
applicable to a murderer
but i shall not murder that should be
the the presumption not not that i shall
not kill
okay labor relations at this stage
within 15 to 20 years we destroy
the traditionally established links of
bargaining
between employer and employee
the classical marxist leninist theory of
natural exchange of goods
a person a has five sacks of grain and
person b
has five pairs of shoes and the natural
exchange without
money is when they bargain between each
other
and only with the introduction of the
third four c
an entirely third foreign stranger who
says no don't give him five sacks of
drink give it to me
and you give me your five pairs of shoes
and i will distribute it accordingly
so the economy will go this
is the death of natural exchange and
that death of natural bargaining
well trade unions were established 100
years ago
the objective was to improve working
conditions and to protect the rights of
workers
from those employers who were abusing
their their right because they had more
money
objectively at that time initially the
trade union movement did work
what we see now is that the bargaining
process is no longer resulting into
in the compromise which is leading
objectively to
betterment of working conditions and
increase of salary what we see
is that after each prolonged strike the
workers
lose even if they have 10 increase of
their salaries
they cannot catch up due to inflation
and due to missed time
more than that millions of people suffer
from that strike
because economy now is interdependent
it's intertwined like one body
if previously still workers say 100
years ago
could strike and nobody would suffer now
it's impossible anymore
if a garbage collector strikes today the
rest of the multi-million city is
stinking
i mean that there's no more service
in quebec for example we had the
electricians who were on strike
in the middle of winter you can freeze
your bottom
and they still weren't strike did they
catch up with the celery no they lost
who benefited the leaders of trade union
what is the motivation for strike
improving improving of a worker's
condition
no obviously it's not then what is it
ideology to prove to these capitalists
and the obedient horde of workers like
sheep follow these people and they
cannot disobey why
because if they do you know what happens
to them tickets
murders shooting truck drivers by
picketers in montreal for example i saw
with my own eyes when i was
correspondent of cbc
international canadian broadcasting
calculation when the workers of
aircraft factory destroyed computers and
and the equipment in the factory and
they
the administration employed strike
breakers
their cars were turned upside down and
burned
their houses were burned their kids were
intimidated and some
victims were there of that you can be
sure
why to improve conditions of workers
no ideology okay so
this is what happens basically
it may or may not happen without the
help of the soviet union
but the natural tendencies are being
greatly taken advantage of and
capitalized by the soviet propaganda
systems how
whenever trade union strikes we have
influx of propaganda mass media
ideological dissemination
the workers right and we repeat it like
parrots
yes workers right who's right workers no
the the only freedom of worker to sell
his labor
according to his own desire and will is
taken away from him by whom
by trade union boss unlimited power is
given responsibility i want to sell my
labor not for 250 an hour
but for two dollars i don't have right
my freedom is denied to me
i know that if i sell my work for 200
for two dollars an hour
not for three dollars now i will compete
better with the other guy who is lazy
and more greedy i don't need two three
dollars i need
only two dollars no i was made to
believe by media
by business by advertising agencies that
i need
more and more and more have you ever
heard any advertising on tv to consume
less
no no way
whether you need a six cylinder car or
not
you have to buy it and hurry up
when i was driving here on the local
radio station
an excited announcer said you hurry up
rush and save save save there is a
plenty houses sale
save by buying more
of course of course it would be too
naive to expect that kgb makes that
advertising agency
to do such a crazy commercial no of
course not
but what we did when i was working for
novelist ukraine
we would snow plow editorial offices
student organizations religious group
with literature
of class struggle may if if not directly
marxism
is propaganda then a propaganda of
of a legitimate aspirations of working
class
betterment of life equality equality
mind you president kennedy once said
people we will make america to believe
that people are born equal
are people born equal is there any
mentioning
in the bible or any other holy scripture
in any religion
any religion if you don't believe me go
to library and check it
there is not a single word about
equality
just the opposite by your deeds
god will judge you what you do is
important
the merit of your personality
you cannot legislate equality if you
want to be equal
you have to be equal you have to deserve
it
and yet we build our society on the
principle of equality we say people are
equal
we know it is false it's a lie
some people are tall and stupid others
are short bold and clever
if we make them
[Laughter]
if we make them equal by force
if we put the principle of equality in
the basis of our social political
structure
it's the same thing as building a house
on sand
sooner or later it will collapse and
that's exactly what happens
and we as soviet propaganda makers are
trying to
push you in the direction which you go
yourself equality yes
equality people are equal land of equal
opportunities
is it true or not think about it
equal opportunities should there be
equal opportunities
for me and for a lazy bastard who come
here
from some other country and immediately
registers as a welfare
uh recipient benefits i never received a
single
no sorry i did this once but i never
applied for welfare for the 13 years i
took
any job security guard
journalist taxi driver anything
well i was restless but some people
don't like it they
immediately so why should we be why
should we have equal opportunities
why the equal opportunity to excel
equal opportunity in equal circumstances
yes but we know people are different
to excel yes provided we reach the same
level of
excellency perfection which is
hypothetical
distant future yes maybe but we know
perfectly well that
even the best intentions people could
not
be equal why should we have equality in
in the say legal system myself
i'm considering myself a law abiding
citizen
and the person who comes here to rob and
shoot say
the united states administration on the
card
imported thousands of cuban criminals
they were non-criminals yet they were
accepted
do you think it's fair if myself and my
wife from philippines who work like
excuse me horace as a lab technician in
the hospital
should have the same rights as a
criminal film from cuba
why and yet we repeat as parents
equality equality equality
and the soviet propaganda system helps
us to believe that equality is something
which is desirable
democracy as it was established by
fathers of this country
of the system in the last century
is is not equality
is the system where different people
unequal people
have a chance to survive and help each
other
in constant competition in constant
perfection
not inequality which is superimposed
from from
a godfather or a nice person in
washington dc
and the absolute equality exists in
soviet union
quote unquote equality everybody is
equally
in dirt except some people are more
equal than the others in politburo
[Laughter]
so the moment you you bring a country
to the point of almost total
demoralization when nothing
works anymore when you are not sure that
it is right or
or wrong good and bad but there is no
division between evil and good
when even the leaders of church
sometimes say
well violence for the sake of justice
especially social justice is justified
in the countries like
nicaragua el salvador well maybe
rhodesia
and we listen to them and say yeah
probably
it's true is it true no it is not true
violence is not justified especially for
the sake of
quote-unquote social justice introduced
by marxist levines
that is my former colleagues from noaa's
depressed agency
okay so where is that point the next
step is destabilization
again this word says for itself what it
is to destabilize
all the relations all the accepted
institutions
and organizations in the country of your
enemy how you do it
you don't have to send up a battalion of
kgb
agents to blow up bridges no you let
them do it themselves
the area of application is again it's
it's narrower now not like the previous
case
the overt legitimate actions of the
of the kgb in this case would be
hardly noticeable there is no crime if a
professor who recently went to ussr
introduces a course of marxism leninism
in a californian college for example
nobody is going to to come to his
doorstep and say okay
mister come you're under arrest no it's
not a crime
it's not even considered a moral crime
against your country
so the area of application here is
narrowing down
to economy again labor relations
right to law and order
plus military
and the economy law and order
yes and again the uh media but
uh wider scope little bit different i'll
explain
when okay basically three areas
economy the
radicalization of bargaining process
if on that stage we still could achieve
theoretically some positive compromise
between the
negotiating sides with with uh
say our arbitrary
introduction of arbitrary judges third
side
objectively judging the demands of both
sides here it's radicalization
on this on the stage of destabilization
we cannot
come to compromise even within a family
the husband and wife couldn't figure out
which is better husband wants his kids
to eat at the table and wife
wants him a child to roam around the
room and
and drop food all over the floor they
cannot come to compromise
unless they start a fight it's
impossible to reach a compromise
constructive compromise between
neighbors
some people say i don't like you to
watering you alone at that time because
exactly at that time i'm walking my dog
and he's getting nervous
he cannot pass his bowels you know so
they cannot compromise they go to
a a civil court or something like that
radicalization of human relations
no more compromise fight fight fight
the normal traditionally accepted
relations are destabilized
the relations between teachers and
students
in schools and colleges fight
the the relations between in economical
sphere between
laborers and and employers are further
radicalized no more
acceptance of the legitimacy of demands
of workers
unlike japanese with the theory if you
ever heard about it
where the workers are involved in
decision-making process therefore they
don't have
uh moral incentive to to fight their uh
their bosses in the united states is
just the opposite the harder is the
the fight the better the more heroic
they look
when the greyhound network was on strike
recently
the correspondence of local tv networks
uh all over the united states were
approaching these strikers and they say
oh yes we are doing something nice they
look like heroes and they were proud
there was some family the husband
was a bus driver now they decided in
in in the protest against the uh bosses
to
camp somewhere in the forest and they
were presented to the to the audience as
as a heroic nice people
you see the violent clashes between
passengers ticketers and and the
strikers
are presented as something normal
10 15 20 years ago we would we would be
we would be angry say why why why so
much hatred
today we are not we say well commonplace
radicalization militarization sometimes
as i explained on that stage i
took a step a little bit further
shooting people
okay law and order now
also is uh
pushed into the area where previously
people
settle their differences uh peacefully
and legitimately
now we are getting with this uh
court cases in this smallest
irrelevant cases we cannot solve our
problems anymore
the society at large becomes more and
more antagonistic
between individuals between groups of
individuals and the society at large
the media puts himself in the opposition
to the society
in general at large
separate alienated okay
on that stage you remember i was talking
uh
a couple of hours ago about the sleepers
that's when the students from say united
states
if they're trained in lumumba university
or developing nations that's the
students i was dealing with
are being sent back from the soviet
union here
or if they were already in the united
states in the country
which is the object of subversion they
spring to action
the sleepers go up
they slept for 15 to 20 years
now they become leaders of groups
preachers uh
i don't know public public figures
prominently
they act in they actively include
themselves in a political process
all of a sudden we see a homosexual
15 years ago he did his dirty job
and nobody cared now he makes it a
political
issue a political issue
he demands recognition respect human
rights
and hiral is a large group of people and
their violent clashes
between him and police his group and
ordinary people
no matter what it's black against white
yellows again green doesn't matter
where's the vision line goes as long as
this group come into antagonistic clash
sometimes militantly sometimes with
firearms
that is the stabilization process the
sleepers
many of whom are simply kgb agents
become leaders of the process of this
civilization
doesn't mean that comrade and drop off
sends comrades off the united states
the person who takes care is already
here
he's a respected citizen of united
states sometimes he he gets
money from various foundations for his
legitimate
struggle for i don't know human rights
women rights kid lib prison lib whatever
there are sympathetic americans who
donate their money to him
this to be like this stabilization
process usually leads directly
to the process of crisis in case of
developing nations
there's the area where i i was active
the process starts
when when the
legitimate bodies
of power the social structure collapse
it cannot function anymore
so instead we have artificial body
injected into society such as
non-elected committees
you remember i was talking about them
here social workers
who are not elected by people media who
sell who are self-appointed rulers of
your
opinion uh some strange groups
uh which claim that they know how to
lead society forward
they don't usually all they care is how
to collect the nations and
and from and sell their own concocted
ideology
mixture of religion and ideology here
we have all this artificial body
claiming power
if the power is denied to them they take
it by force
in case of iran for example all of a
sudden we have revolutionary communities
who were what what kind of revolution
there was no revolution yet
and yet they had the committees they
were taking power of
of judgement they had they had the power
of execution they had the power
of of legislation and that
they had the power of judicial
all of them combined in one person who
is half-baked intellectual sometimes
graduated from harvard university or
berkeley
he comes back to his country and he
thinks that he knows the answer to all
the social economical problems
okay crisis is when society cannot
function any more productively it
collapses
obviously that's the word for crisis so
therefore
the population at large is looking for a
savior
the religious groups are expecting a
messiah to come
the workers say we have family to feed
let's have a strong government maybe
socialist government centralized when
when somebody put put their employers on
their place
and let us work we are sick and tired of
going to strike and
missing overtime and all that stuff we
need some strong man
strong government a leader
a savior is needed population is sick
and tired already
and here we are we have a savior either
a foreign nation comes in
or the local group of leftists
marxist no matter what they call
themselves sandinista
a reverend or some sort
bishop mozareva like in zimbabwe
doesn't matter a savior comes and says i
will
lead you so we have two alternatives
here
civil war and invasion
okay see how it goes
civil war we know what it is lebanon is
the best example
the civil war which was artificially
implanted
in lebanon by injection of force of plo
palestinian liberation organization
invasion
we have in many other countries like
afghanistan
name any east european country it was
invaded by the soviet army
but the result is the same the next
stage is
normalization normalization
is a very ironic word of course
it is bordered from 1968 situation in
czechoslovakia when the soviet
propaganda
and after them new york times declared
the country is normalized
the tanks moved into prague so there is
no more prague spring there is no more
violence
normal normalization
at that stage the
self-appointed rulers of the society
don't need any revolution anymore they
don't need any radicalism anymore
so this is the reverse from
destabilization
basically it is stabilizing the country
by force
so all these sleepers and activists and
social workers
and liberals and homosexuals
and professors and marxists and letting
us
are being eliminated physically
sometimes
they've done their job already okay they
are not needed anymore
the new rulers need stability to exploit
the nation to exploit the country to
take advantages
of the victory okay so no more
revolutionaries please and that's
exactly what happens in number of
countries
you remember bangladesh this is the
crisis in which i was instrumental
first they had mujibur rahman
in 1971 he was the leader of people's
party league with mustache like stalin
he was in
in russia many times in five years he
was shot by his former colleagues
marxists he fulfilled his function in
afghanistan it happened three times
because there was taraki then there was
amin nowadays
they killed each other successively one
after another
the moment he fulfills his duty the
first one demoralized country the second
distabilized
the third one brought it to crisis
goodbye comrades
carmilla comes from moscow and put him
into the seat of power
same thing happened in granada recently
maurice bishop
marxist was killed by austin what's his
name general something
it was also a marxism right
so no more revolutions please
normalization now
from now on no more strikes no more
homosexual
sexuals no more women leave no more
kidney
no more lib period
good solid democratic proletarian
freedom
now to reverse this process
takes enormous effort when today
united states had to invade granada
to reverse the process of subversion
some people say
boy this is not good it's not kosher to
invade the beautiful country
island of granada well why didn't you
stop the process here
when granada was just approached by
leftists
why not to prevent maurice bishop to
come in power in the first place
did grenadas want him very questionable
they didn't know who was mortis bishop
in the first place
he came to power by kudeta himself
okay now we let the situation develop
further and further and further until
the crisis
and normalization very soon
and then united states decided to invade
country discovering that
the country was absolutely a military
base for the soviet union
of course it's a drastic measure of
course it's it's repeated that
marine corps had to to lose what 17
lives very bad
why not to stop the process before it
comes to crisis
or no intellectuals will not let you
it's interference into domestic affairs
they're very careful not to not not to
let
american administration to interfere in
domestic affairs of latin american
characters
they don't mind soviet union interfere
in this affair
so to reverse this process from here
it takes only and always military force
no other force on earth can reverse this
process at this point
at this point it does not take military
invasion
of united states army it takes strong
action like in chile
as cia covert involvement
to prevent the savior from outside to
come into power
and to stabilize country before it
erupts into civil war
country before it erupts into civil war
okay support the right-wing conservative
forces buy money by crooks so love
doesn't matter
stabilize and don't let the crisis
develop into into civil war or invasion
oh no your liberals will say it's
against the law
the congress will not appropriate money
for covert actions
of cia why not
should we wait till the normalization
come and soviet tanks landed in in los
angeles airport
now at that point at the point of
destabilization
also the process could be reversed again
easily than this
no cia involvement at this point you
know what it takes here
restriction of some liberties for small
groups which are self-declared enemies
of the society
as simple as that oh no the median
liberals will tell you this is against
the american constitution
how can we
by force deny the civil rights to
criminals for example
it's not good okay so we allow them to
okay if you allow the criminals to have
civil rights go on and bring the country
to the crisis
this is a bloodless way to do curb the
rights i mean not to put them in prison
no no i'm not talking about putting all
the gates from san francisco in the
concentration camp
do not allow them to take
political force do not elect them to the
seats of power whether it is
municipality
state level or federal level it has to
be
bitten in the heads of american voters
that the person like that in the cities
of power is an
enemy do not be afraid of this word it
is an enemy if he is not an enemy here
he will be here
later on he will be shot of course
but at this point he is an enemy
okay you are doing great service by
denying him a right
to capitalize on his own crazy ideas and
become
a powerful man a man who uses
the seat of power restriction of certain
freedoms and permissiveness at that
point
would prevent sliding into crisis and
probably will return the process of
destabilization
to curb unlimited power monopolistic
power of trade unions
here at that point would save economy
from collapsing
to introduce a law to stop
private companies of raping public
opinions
mind income in the in the direction of
consumerism
no company must have a right
to force you into buying more unless you
want it
there must be a law you want to
advertise your car
okay but not a single mentioning of
buying it now and saving
it money be against the law to force
people to consume more
self-restraint previously before this
process started
the self-restraint was the business of
church religion because our preachers
the fathers of church would tell us
material values are good but it's not
the prime
function of human being because you have
to live with
something obviously the design for our
life
is not to consume more deodorant
there must be something greater if such
a complicated
instrument this human body was created
obviously there must be some higher
purpose for that
and it's very easy to avoid
destabilization by denying
the greedy companies one little freedom
one little liberty forcing you into
turning yourself
into processors of unwanted
products and goods they turn you into
machines
like a the worm who there is inlet and
outlet so
and how long an average appliance lasts
these days
less than a year why
where's workmanship we want you to buy
more okay this stabilization process
could be easily overcome if as i say
the society by its own will or after
persuasion by the leaders
will come to the idea of self-restraint
it's so hard we want to consume more but
you have to
unless you will come to this stage when
as we say in russia
if sahara desert ever becomes a
communist state
there will be shortage of sand
so you have to curb your
[Laughter]
you have to you have to curb your
expectations at this point
before it's too late but no we don't
want to do it
demoralization process again it's the
easiest thing to reverse
first of all by restricting import of
propaganda
the easiest thing to do
unlimited unrestrained import of
soviet literature soviet journalists
uh giving soviet propaganda and
ideological agitators equal time on
american tv network
it has to be stopped and it's easy
they won't they won't be offended minded
as a matter of fact they will respect
america more
but then my former colleague vladimir
posner appears on nightline
and ted koppel asking well vladimir what
do you think about this
what can he think he is an instrument of
propaganda
he thinks what what what comrade
andropov tells him to think
he is just a nice articulate mouthpiece
of the soviet uh
uh subversion system and ted cottle
makes you believe
that my friend vladimir posner thinks
the process of demoralization may not
have started at
all if at that point
the country which is a recipient of
subversion actively
not violently but actively prevents
importation of foreign ideology
i don't want america to follow the
pattern of ancient japan
you don't have to shoot every foreigner
when it approaches
the sacred borders of the united states
but when he offers you a junk in the
disguise of very shiny something
we have to tell him no we have our own
[Laughter]
junk
if at that point the society is strong
brave and conscientious enough
to stop importation of ideas which are
foreign
then the whole chain of events could be
prevented
recently i've been to philippines and i
was shocked
how in big cities like manila children
listen to
deafening music a melodious
nation with long traditions of good
nice ethnic music introduced by spanish
long time ago maybe two centuries three
centuries ago i don't remember
all of a sudden listen to musical
garbage
blasting their radios at full blast at
the
full volume why in
india i spent many years watching the
reactions of
indians walking out of movie theaters
after seeing hollywood production
they they couldn't figure out why
americans are so wasteful they smash
their cars
their shiny cars every five minutes how
come they shoot each other for half a
million dollars
is it true that they are so sex sex
i mean obsessed with sex can you imagine
showing a movie
where each five minutes there's a
copulation
on the screen to a country like india
with long traditions
tradition of of respect to this private
matters
or to pakistan
and united states expect these people to
respect you
no way oh yes they will see the movie
they'll pay five rupees to see that
garbage
but they walk out and will tell their
kids don't
respect americans don't be like
americans
see so the process of demoralization
could be stopped right here
both as an expert and as an import
and that takes one step one very
important thing to do
you don't have to expel all the kgb
agents from washington dc
the most difficult and at the same time
the simplest answer
to the subversion is to start it here
and even before
by bringing back the society to
religion something that you cannot touch
and eat and put on yourself but
something that rules society and makes
it move
and preserve it a soviet scientist
who has nothing to do with religion he
is a computer scientist
did a very intensive research on the
history of socialist countries
he called socialist or communist any
country with a centralized economy
and the pyramidal style of power
structure
and he discovered actually he didn't
discover it he just
brought to attention of his readers that
civilizations like mohan jodaro
in the river hindus area
like egypt like maya incas
like below but the bologna culture
collapsed and disappeared from the
surface of earth the moment they lost
religion
as simple as that they disintegrated
nobody remembers about them anymore
well distantly so
the ideas are moving society and keeping
mankind
as a society of human beings intelligent
moral agents of god
the facts the truth the exact knowledge
may not
all the sophisticated technology and
computers will not prevent society from
disintegrating and eventually dying out
have you ever met a person who would
sacrifice his
life freedom for the truth like that
this is truth i never met the person who
said this is truth and i'm ready to
shoot me
to defend the truth right
but millions sacrifice their life
freedom comfort everything
for things like god
like jesus christ it's an honor
some markers in in the soviet
concentration camp died
and they died in peace unlike those who
shouted longleaf stalin
knowing perfectly well that he may not
live long
something which is
something which is not material
moves society and helps it to survive
and the other way around the moment we
turn into two by two is four
and make it a guiding principle of our
life our existence
we die even though this is true
and this we cannot prove we only can
feel
and have faith in it so the answer to
ideological subversion
strangely enough is very simple you
don't have to shoot people you don't
have
to aim missiles and pershings and cruise
missiles
at androple's headquarters you simply
have to have faith
and prevent subversion in other words
not to be a victim of subversion don't
try to be a person
who in judo is trying to smash your
enemy
and being caught by your hand
don't strike like that strike with power
you have spirit
and moral superiority if you don't have
the power it's high time to develop it
and that's the only answer
that's it
[Applause]
you