well you spoke several times before
about ideological subversion that is a
phrase that I'm afraid some Americans
don't fully understand when the Soviets
used the phrase ideological subversion
what do they mean by ideological
subversion is is the process
which is legitimate all word
and open you can see it with your own
eyes all you have to do all American
mass media has to do is to unplug their
bananas from their ears open up their
eyes and they can see it there's no
mystery there's nothing to do with
Espionage I know that Espionage
intelligence gathering looks more
romantic it sells more deodorants
through the advertising probably that's
why your Hollywood producers are so
crazy about James Bond type of Thrills
but in reality the main emphasis of the
KGB is not in the area of its
intelligence at all according to my
opinion and opinion of many of the
factors of my caliber only about 15
percent of time money and Manpower is
spent on Espionage as such the other 85
percent is a slow process
which we call either ideological
subversion or active measures active in
the language of the KGB or psychological
warfare what it basically means is to
change the perception of reality of
every American
to such an extent that despite of the
abundance of information
no one is able to come to sensible
conclusions
in the interests of Defending themselves
their families their community and their
country
it's a great brainwashing process which
goes very slow and it's divided in four
basic stages
the first one being demoralization it
takes from 15 to 20 years to demoralize
a nation why that many years because
this is the minimum number of years
which requires to educate one generation
of students
in the country of of your enemy exposed
to the ideology of the enemy in other
words Marxism leninism ideology is being
pumped into the soft heads of of at
least three generations of American
students without being challenged or
counterbalanced by the basic values of
americanism American patriotism the
result the result you can see most of
the people who graduated in 60s
dropouts or half-baked intellectuals are
now occupying the positions of power in
the government civil service business
mass media educational system you are
stuck with them you cannot get rid of
them they are contaminated they are
programmed to think and react to certain
stimuli in a certain pattern
you cannot change their mind even if you
if you expose them to authentic
information even if you prove that white
is white and black is black you still
cannot change the basic perception and
the logic of behavior
in other words these people
uh the process of demoralization is
complete and irreversible to get rid
Society of these people you have you
need another 20 or or 15 years to
educate a new generation of
patriotically minded and and common
common sense people who would be acting
in favor and in the interests of the of
the United States society and yet these
people have been programmed and as you
say in place and who are favorable to an
opening with the Soviet concept these
are the very people who would be marked
for extermination in this country most
of them yes uh simply because the
psychological shock when when they will
see in future what the what the
beautiful Society of equality and social
justice means in practice obviously they
will Revolt they they will they will be
very unhappy frustrated people and
Marxist leninistration does not tolerate
these people
uh they obviously they will join the
links of the centers dissidents
unlike in present United States there
will be no place for descent in future
Marxist Lenin is America
uh here you can you can get uh popular
like Daniel Ellsberg and Filthy Rich
like Jane Fonda for being dissident for
criticizing your Pentagon in Future
these people will be simply
squashed like cockroaches nobody is
going to pay them nothing for their
beautiful Noble ideas of equality this
they don't understand and it will be
greatest shock for them of course
the demoralization process in the United
States is basically completed already
for the last 25 years actually it's over
fulfilled because demoralization now
reaches such areas where previously not
even comrade and drop off and and all
his experts would would even dream of
such a tremendous success most of it is
done by Americans to Americans thanks to
lack of moral standards as I mentioned
before
uh exposure to True information does not
matter anymore
a person who was demoralized is unable
to assess true information the facts
tell nothing to him even if I shower him
with information with the authentic
proof with documents with pictures
even if I take him by force to the
Soviet Union and show him concentration
camp he will refuse to believe it until
he he is going to receive a cake in the
in his fat bottom when a military boat
crashes his balls then he will
understand but not before that that's
the tragic of the situation of
demoralization so basically America is
stuck with demoralization and unless
even if if you start right now here this
minute you start educating new
generation of Americans it will still
take you 15 to 20 years to turn the tide
of of ideological perception of reality
uh back to normal normalcy and and
patriotism
the next stage is destabilization this
time subverter does not care about your
ideas and the patterns of your
consumption whether you eat junk food
and get fat and flub it doesn't matter
anymore this time and it takes only from
two to five years to destabilize the
nation uh it's what what matters is
Essentials economy Foreign Relations
defense systems
and you can see it quite clearly that in
some areas in such sensitive areas is
defense and economy the influence of
marxist leninist ideas in the United
States is absolutely fantastic I could
never believe it 14 years ago when I
landed in this part of the world that
the process will go that fast
uh the next stage of course is Crisis it
it may take only up to six weeks to to
bring a country to the verge of Crisis
you can see it in in Central America now
after crisis with a violent change of
power structure and economy you have
so-called the period of normalization it
may last indefinitely normalization is a
cynical expression borrowed from Soviet
propaganda when the Soviet tanks moved
into Czechoslovakia in 68 comrade
breshev said now the situation in
brotherly Czechoslovakia is normalized
this is what will happen in the United
States if you allow all these Schmucks
to bring the country to crisis
to promise people all kind of goodies
and the paradise on Earth to to
destabilize your economy to eliminate
the principle of free market competition
and to put a big broader government
in Washington DC with the benevolent
dictators Like Walter Mondale who will
promise lots of things never mind this
is what will happen in the United States
if you allow all these Schmucks to bring
the country to crisis
to promise people all kind of goodies
and the paradise on Earth to to
destabilize your economy to eliminate
the principle of free market competition
and to put a big brother government
in Washington DC with the benevolent
dictators Like Walter Mondale who will
promise lots of things never mind
whether the promises are fulfillable or
not he will go to Moscow to kiss the
bottoms of new generation of Soviet
assassins never mind he will create
false illusions that the situation is
under control situation is not under
control situation is disgustingly out of
control most of the American politicians
media and educational system
trains another generation of people who
think they are living at a peace time
false the United States is in the state
of War Undeclared total war against the
basic principles and the foundations of
this system
and and the initiator of this war is not
covered on drop of of course
it's it's the system
however ridiculous it may sound the
world communist system or the world
communist conspiracy whether it's care
some people or not I don't give a hood
if you are not scared by now nothing can
scare you
but you don't have to be paranoid about
it what what actually happens now
that unlike myself you have
literally several years to live on
unless United States wake up the the
time bomb is ticking with every second
the disaster is coming closer and closer
unlike myself you will have nowhere to
defect to
unless you want to live in Antarctica
with penguins this is it this is the
last country of freedom and and
possibility okay so what do we do what
is your recommendation to the American
people well uh the uh the immediate
thing that comes to my mind is of course
there must be a very strong National
effort to educate people in in in the
spirit of real Patriots is number one
number two to to explain them the real
danger of Socialist Communist whatever
welfare state Big Brother government
if people will fail to grasp the
impending danger of that development
nothing ever can help United States you
make his goodbye to your freedom
including freedoms to to homosexuals to
prison inmate all this Freedom will
vanish evaporating in five seconds