Advertise your product or brand here
contact www.OpenSubtitles.org today
This is our land.
A land of peace and of plenty.
A land of harmony and hope.
This is our land.
Oceania.
These are our people.
The workers. The striver's.
The builders.
These are our people.
The builders of our world,
struggling, fighting,
Bleeding, dying.
On the streets of our cities
and on the far-flung battlefields.
Fighting against the mutilation
of our hopes and dreams.
(SOUNDS OF WARFARE)
Who are they?
(AUDIENCE CHANT)
Traitor! Traitor! Traitor! Traitor!
They are the dark armies.
The dark murdering
armies of Eurasia.
(SOUND OF GUNSHOTS)
In the barren deserts of Africa and India.
On the oceans of Australasia.
Courage, strength and
youth are sacrificed.
Sacrificed to barbarians
whose only honour is atrocity.
(BATTLE SCREAM)
(BATTLE SCREAM AGAIN)
But even as we grasp at victory.
There is a cancer, an evil tumour,
growing, spreading in our midst.
(SOUNDS OF EXPLOSIONS)
Shout! Shout! Shout out his name.
(AUDIENCE CHANT)
Goldstein! Goldstein!
(AUDIENCE BEGIN CHANTING AGAIN)
(AUDIENCE CHANT SO LOUDLY
FILM CANNOT BE HEARD)
(LOUD AUDIENCE CHANT CONTINUES)
(AUDIENCE IN UPROAR)
JULIA CHANTS: Death! Death! Traitor!
JULIA CHANTS: Traitor!
WINSTON CHANTS: Traitor!
AUDIENCE CHANT: Traitor!
(AUDIENCE IN HYSTERIA)
JULIA SCREAMS No! No!
(AUDIENCE BECOMES QUIET)
Innuendo deleted.
Intransigence rendered as crime think.
Inversion...
(SOUND OF DIALLING)
Ref Times, 14/2/84, page three.
Byline two should read "Mini prod forecast
increase choco ration, April 1984",
from 20g to 25g per week.
I confess to spreading the
rumour on orders from Goldstein
that the war is not really with Eurasia,
but with Eastasia.
And that for years, in fact
since the days of our glorious revolution,
I had no faith in our future.
I forged government announcements
and falsified figures
quoted for agricultural
and industrial production.
As a result of mental disturbance dating
from my experiences in the atomic wars,
I was a willing subject
of Goldstein's influence.
I was stubborn and egocentric.
When own life thoughts
occurred to me, I revelled in them.
I went into the proletarian
zones. I had sex with prostitutes.
I deliberately contracted syphilis.
It was at this time
that I made contact with the Resistance.
I was personally contacted
by the arch-traitor Goldstein
and ordered to assassinate
Inner Party officials.
- Bugger!
- This I did.
My agents forged documents and gained
entry to the Ministry of Truth...
Thought crime is death.
Thought crime does not entail death.
I have committed,
even before setting pen to paper,
the essential crime that contains
all others in itself.
... encouraging my agents to deface
party posters and announcements.
I read and memorised Goldstein's book.
For 30 years, I have plotted
to bring down the Party.
I was sick in mind and body.
Together with my colleagues,
Aaronson and Rutherford,
I did counterfeit
important Party documents,
including ex-London permits
and travel passes.
And that by use of these documents
my agents travelled freely
throughout Airstrip One,
encouraging insurrection
and organising a huge counter plot
to destroy the innermost faction
of the Oceanian leadership.
Furthermore, I used my position
of privilege within the Inner Party
to pervert and betray the truth at all
times and to suggest, wherever possible,
that our traditional allies in Eastasia
were, in fact, our deadly enemies...
April 4th 1984.
I think.
To the past, or to the future,
to an age when thought is free.
From the age of Big Brother,
from the age of the Thought Police...
from a dead man,
greetings.
(SOUND OF ALARM FROM TELESCREEN)
TELESCREEN: 30-40 group,
take your places, please.
TELESCREEN: Right let's see which
one of us can touch his toes.
TELESCREEN: Right over from the
hips, brothers and sisters please.
TELESCREEN: One, two.
TELESCREEN: Smith! 6079 Smith W.
TELESCREEN: Yes you. Bend lower.
TELESCREEN: You're not
trying, watch me.
TELESCREEN: There, brother,
that's what I want.
TELESCREEN: Anyone under 45
is perfectly capable of touching his toes.
TELESCREEN: I'm 39 and
I've had four children.
TELESCREEN: We don't all have the
privilege of fighting in the front line.
TELESCREEN: Remember our
boys on the Malabar front.
TELESCREEN: Just think what
they have to put up with.
- Morning Smith.
- Parsons.
- Heard the rumour?
- No. Good news is it?
I should say so yes.
Choco rations going up.
- Really?
- 25g next week.
Double plus good, eh?
By the way Smith, I seem to have run
out of razor blades for some reason.
Er you wouldn't happen to
have any spare would you?
I'm sorry brother, I'm on the last one.
In 1983 Oceania's coal
output reached 630 million tons.
In 1976,
coal output was 605 million tons,
an increase of 4. 1 per cent.
5.3 million tractors were produced,
an increase of 17.6 per cent.
I wanted to ask you if
you've got any razor blades.
I've tried all over the place. I've been
using the same one for six weeks.
Did you see the prisoners
hanged yesterday?
No I was working.
But I shall see it on the screens.
We'll pick up a gin on the way.
I'll have two.
Give me a gin.
2 million .5 Victory recoil
operated heavy machine guns,
6 million rifle grenades, 9
million Perry pineapple pin grenades
and 1.4 million lightweight
spigot-launching
antitank rocket projectors.
Food production is also up...
- How's the New speak Committee?
- Working overtime.
The plus big wastage is in adjectives.
Plus big problem is timing the
language to scientific advance.
Yes.
It's a beautiful thing,
the destruction of words.
You won't have seen the
dictionary tenth edition yet Smith.
It's that thick.
The 11th edition will be that thick.
So the revolution will be complete
when the language is perfect?
The secret is to move from translation
to direct thought to automatic response.
- Language coming from here not here.
- Excuse me for intruding.
We shall be rid of Goldsteinism
when the language has been cleaned.
I couldn't be more in agreement
with you brother.
Absolutely
Praise be to our leader
and the Party workers.
Other munitions production figures
are as follows.
70,000 M-20 tank destroyers
with 76 mm cannon...
Smith. Syme.
It's encouraging thought
that by 2050
not a single person
could have a conversation like this.
- Except the proles.
- Proletariat don't count. They're animals.
Did you see the hanging?
Missed it myself.
Bloody committees!
... heavy Victory
rocket bombs.
35,000 Black Eagle
500cc motor bicycles. 300,000...
Double plus good this.
Do you know I don't think there is a
single piece of meat in this stew.
Looks like meat, tastes like
meat. It isn't meat at all.
Double plus good.
- Not like it Smith?
- Yes. It's too rich for me.
Do you mind if I?
Brothers and sisters the
battle for production has been won.
Completed returns show that the standard
of living has risen by 20 per cent
over the last year.
All over Oceania, spontaneous
demonstrations of Party workers
Voicing their gratitude and joy.
In honour of this massive over fulfilment
of the ninth three year Plan.
It has been announced that the chocolate
ration is to be increased to 25g per week.
If there is hope,
it lies in the proles.
If they were conscious of their strength,
they would have no need to conspire.
History does not matter to them.
It was three years ago,
on a dark evening,
easy to slip the patrols
and I'd gone into the proletarian areas.
There was no one else in the street
and no telescreens.
She said "Two dollars."
So I went with her.
She had a young face, painted very thick.
It was really the paint
that appealed to me,
the whiteness of it like a mask,
and the bright red lips.
There were no preliminaries.
Standing there with the scent
of dead insects and cheap perfume,
I went ahead and did it just the same.
Rutherford Unperson, substitute Ogilvy.
Ogilvy biog details as follows.
War hero recently killed Malabar front.
Today awarded posthumous
Order of Conspicuous Merit 2nd class.
I accuse myself of sabotage,
embezzlement of Party funds,
sale of military secrets, of being
in the pay of the government of Eurasia.
Of being a sexual pervert
and a thought criminal.
I exploited my trusted
position at the Ministry of Peace,
to mislead our
allies in Eastasia,
and also to corrupt youth by means
of seditious literature and drugs.
I am guilty on all counts. I stand here
a victim of the influence of Emmanuel...
Under the spreading chestnut
tree I sold you, you sold me.
...and I ask only for you to accept
my love of our leader.
Can I help you?
Hmm.
Anything special?
- I was here before.
- Ah.
- Razor blades.
- Ah-hah.
- You sold me the notebook.
- Yes. Yes.
Please look around.
Ah.
What's this?
Oh it's a beautiful thing.
Over a hundred years old.
Cost you four dollars.
There's another room upstairs
that you might like to see.
Yes it's er, not much in
it. Just a few things.
My woman's dead.
I'm just trying to sell the furniture.
It's a beautiful bed, if you
can get the bugs out of it.
(SOUND OF MISSILE EXPLODING)
Interested in old prints at all?
The frame's fixed to the wall
but I daresay you could unscrew it.
How did this escape?
I know what it is.
It's the museum in the street
outside the Palace of Justice.
Oranges and lemons
say the bells of St Clement's.
What was that?
Something old.
War is peace.
Freedom is slavery.
Ignorance is strength.
A triumph of willpower over the orgasm.
At a rally of the Anti-Sex League
in Victory Square tonight
held to celebrate a 50 per cent
decrease in civil marriages.
Over 10,000 Party women
took a vow of celibacy
and pledged themselves as
vessels for the artificial...
I hate her. I should kill her
before she denounces me.
I have disliked her from
the first moment of seeing her.
(SOUND OF HELICOPTER OUTSIDE)
Sector 43. 929 male, 753 female.
Sector 44 437 male, 609 female.
(JULIA GASPS)
- Are you hurt?
- No it's nothing.
It's my arm. I'll be alright in a second.
Brother could you?
- Are you alright?
- It's nothing.
I only gave my wrist a bit of a bang.
Thank you brother.
Who is she?
All I know is that she
works in the Porno Section,
probably on the proletarian
novel writing machines.
- Mrs Parsons a spanner?
- Under the sink, beside you.
(WINSTON COUGHS)
Thank you brother.
I wouldn't have had to bother you,
but my husband's out late... committees.
You know what us Parsons are like.
You're a thought criminal.
They haven't been out much.
Thank you brother.
Attention. Your attention please.
A newsflash has this moment
arrived from the Malabar front.
The forces of Oceania in South India
have won a glorious victory.
I am authorised to say
that the war against Eurasia
is within measurable distance of its end.
40,000 Eurasian soldiers
have been killed or captured.
(SOUNDS OF EXCITEMENT FROM CROWD)
(CROWD CHANTING)
Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill!
(SOUND OF GUNSHOTS)
(CROWD CHANTING)
Hate! Hate! Hate! Hate! Hate!
(MORE SOUNDS OF GUNSHOTS)
(CROWD CHEERING))
Can you hear me?
Yes
- Do you have an ex-London permit?
- Yes.
Can you get Sunday afternoon off?
- Take this.
It's quite precise.
I rely on you to destroy it.
Are you sure you can come?
Yes.
On your own brother?
No I'm joining the Vicmans
Community Hiking Group.
I was held up on urgent Minrec business.
(SOUND OF STEAM TRAIN)
♪ Sing to the sailors
on the floating fortress ♪
♪ Sing to the soldiers
on the battlefield ♪
♪ Sing to the airmen
in the burning azure ♫
♪ Sing to the farmers' rising yields  ♪
♪ We are the children.
Builders of the future ♫
♪ and we the children swear to thee ♪
♫ loyal emotion. Fearless devotion ♪
♪ and to die with dignity... ♪
A daring and resourceful manoeuvre
under the personal direction of BB himself,
ensuring the total annihilation of
the Eurasian heavy armoured division.
Look.
It's a dream.
I want you.
Not here.
Come back to the woods, it's safer.
Have you done this before?
Of course!
Hundreds of times.
- With party members?
- Yes.
- Inner party members?
- Not with those bastards.
Though there's plenty who would.
I hate purity. I hate goodness.
I don't want virtue to exist anywhere.
- I want everyone corrupt.
- I ought to suit you then.
- I'm corrupt to the core.
- Do you like doing this?
I don't mean just me.
I adore it.
Winston we shall meet in the
place where there is no darkness.
Adult literacy amongst the
proletariat has risen by 56 per cent.
The proletarian infant mortality rate
has dropped by 12 per cent.
Incidences of leukaemia, tuberculosis and
meningitis have dropped considerably.
Improved diet has been responsible
for a dramatic decrease in rickets.
Eye diseases show a steep drop.
So too do deaths from
pneumonia and smallpox.
The improvement in sewerage and drainage
systems has resulted in better health overall.
State rodent operatives report a 50 per
cent reduction in the number of vermin
in the central proletarian zones.
I just want to finish by saying a few words
about the impact of this imminent
neurological breakthrough.
When the orgasm has
been finally eradicated,
the last remaining obstacle
to the psychological acceptance
of the principles of Ingsoc,
as applied to Artsem will be overcome.
In other words the unorthodox
tendencies towards own life,
which constantly threaten the
natural erosion of the family unit,
will no longer have the
biological support of the organism.
As we all know the biological and
social stimulation of the family
leads to private reflection
outside Party needs
and to the establishment of unorthodox
loyalties which can only lead to thought crime.
The introduction of Artsem, combined
with the neutralisation of the orgasm,
will effectively render obsolete the family
until it is impossible to conceptualise.
Thank you.
Excuse me brother.
You dropped your ink pencil.
Thank you sister.
A pincer movement
has developed
involving the floating fortresses
of the Eurasian 17th fleet...
Hmm!
- Not much.
- No.
Not much left at all these days.
The wars.
Police don't like us much.
That room. How much?
Four dollars a week.
Traitor! Traitor!
Traitor!
(CROWD SHOUTING)
Traitor! Criminal!
No! Criminal! No! No!
(ALL RISE FOR INGSOC)
A vast military build up of armoured
divisions, missiles and floating forces
accompanied by a fourfold increase
in the number of rocket bombs,
directed at the most densely
populated areas of Airstrip One...
It's folly, as though deliberately
we move one step nearer the grave.
I can't understand why
she accepted the idea.
She who is so careful.
Hello.
Let me show you what I've brought.
Look.
What is it?
Real sugar.
Not saccharine
and I've got a loaf of bread.
Proper white bread
and jam.
A real tin of milk.
Look.
Coffee.
Real coffee.
Inner Party, half a kilo.
How did you manage
to get hold of all this?
There's nothing those
bastards don't have.
- Aren't you pleased?
- Yes. Yes, of course.
Real tea.
Mm
There's been a lot of tea about lately.
They've captured India or something.
- I want you.
- I want you too.
Wait.
Turn around and don't
look until I tell you.
(NEIGHBOUR SINGING IN BACK GARDEN)
Listen to that.
How can she make a song written
by machines sound so beautiful?
You can turn round now.
- I...
- Winston...
Do you like me?
More than ever.
Was there ever a time
when this seemed ordinary?
Attention! Your attention, please.
A vast military build up has been
reported in the Sahara desert,
sectors 17 and 18 of the war zone.
14 heavy tank divisions...
There's truth
and there is untruth.
Freedom is the freedom to say
two plus two equals four.
If that is granted, all else follows.
(SOUND OF COLLEAGUE DICTATING
INTO MACHINE)
Re Times 31/10/81...
Brother Tillotson wins mini chess.
Request photo. Biog follows.
Attention!
Your attention please.
Will all Outer Party members
of Ways And Means committees
please attend their local community
centres for discussions...
Under the spreading chestnut
tree I sold you, you sold me.
Smith.
I have been reading your
New speak articles in The Times.
- Yes.
- You write very elegantly.
That is not my own opinion. I was recently
talking to a friend of yours who's an expert.
His name has slipped my
memory for a moment.
What I wanted to say was that there were
one or two unwords. Only very recent.
Have you seen the tenth edition
of the New speak dictionary?
No we're are still using
the ninth edition at Minrec.
A few advance copies have been
circulated. I have one myself.
- You might be interested.
- Yes.
There are plus-skilful new developments.
Let me give you my address.
I'm usually at home in the evenings.
If not my servant will
give you the dictionary.
14,000 Victory Vampires,
6,700 Ingsoc cadets,
4,600 Ingsoc sea cadets.
12,300 Porteous piloted missiles,
31,000 Victory fighter bombers,
23,000 Big Brother heavy bombers.
It has happened at last.
The call has come.
It seems that all my life
I have been waiting for it.
... named after Sub lieutenant
Ogilvy, hero of the state of Oceania.
Recently awarded posthumously
the Order of Conspicuous Gallantry
for his actions in the recent glorious
victory over the forces of Eastasia
on the Malabar front in South India.
Half the water's boiled away.
What does the clock say?
It's 21.00 hours.
What time do they cut
the light in your flats?
- 23.30.
- At the hostel it's 23.00.
- What is it?
- I don't know.
A little chunk of history
that they've forgotten to alter.
A message from a hundred years ago.
Oranges and lemons
say the bells of St Clement's.
You owe me three farthings
say the bells of St Martin's.
Who taught you that? What is it?
I don't know. I just know it.
You know the only thing to do is to is
walk out of here before it's too late.
Never see one another again.
Yes.
Our luck can't last.
You're young, look normal.
You're innocent.
If you keep clear of people like me
then you might stay alive.
You do, I do.
I've thought it out.
I'm good at staying alive.
- When shall we meet again?
- Not for several weeks, it's not safe.
Give me half an hour.
I love you.
Julia.
Do you think the Resistance is real?
No, none of it's real.
(DOOR CLOSES)
Steamer! Dead overhead!
Get down! Get down!
(SOUND OF SCREAMING)
(WINSTON DICTATING)
Round the clock plus a 153 set
in eyes top a PMA Willmer...
Oceania is at war with Eastasia.
Oceania has always been
at war with Eastasia.
Eurasia is our ally. Eurasia
has always been our ally.
Everything fades into mist.
The past is erased, the erasure forgotten.
The lie becomes truth
and then becomes a lie again.
What is it?
I dreamt,
about my mother.
What darling?
It was during the wars.
Before the Party.
Winston!
I couldn't help myself.
I knew what I had done
and I couldn't help myself.
When I went back, hours later,
my mother and sister were gone.
I never saw them again.
It's not so much staying alive
as staying human that's important.
What counts is that we
don't betray each other.
If you mean confessing,
we're bound to do that.
Everybody does. You can't help it.
I don't mean confessing.
Confessing isn't betrayal.
I mean feelings.
If they can make me change my feelings,
they can stop me from loving you.
That would be real betrayal.
They can't do that.
It's the one thing they can't do.
They can torture you
and make you say anything.
But they can't make you believe it.
They can't get inside you.
They can't get to your heart.
I'm going to see O'Brien.
I know.
Outer Party member 53922 Hicks,
Minirec, Proletarian Affairs Section.
Outer Party member 22315 Howard
Miniprod, Hospital Section.
Outer Party member 947743 Bolgar
Minitrue, Records Section.
Outer Party member 5739 Brady,
Outer Party member 984213 Devereux,
Minitrue. Records Section.
Outer Party member 9106 Dodds,
Minitrue, Porno Section.
Outer Party 38091 Ware,
Outer Party member 11792 Bigland,
Minitrue, News Section.
Items one, five, seven
approved full wise, stop.
Suggestion contained item six, double
plus ridiculous, verging crime think.
Cancelled, stop. End message.
Outer Party member 4392 Rosenblum,
Miniprod, Light Industry Section.
Outer Party member 66755 Davies,
Miniprod, Women's Section.
That concludes the list of
known agents of Goldstein
actively engaged in
the latest conspiracy...
Not much of this gets to the
Outer Party, I'm afraid.
To our leader.
Our eternal allies in Eurasia
are turning against us.
More nests of conspirators and
saboteurs have been uncovered
and further arrests are expected shortly.
(O'BRIEN SWITCHES OF TELESCREEN)
You can?
Yes
We're allowed that privilege.
Some more of this? It is called wine.
There are thought criminals who maintain
that the Resistance is not real.
Believe me Winston, it is very real.
Perhaps you are not familiar
with how it operates.
I'm attentive to the news.
Indeed.
Then perhaps you imagine a
huge network of conspirators,
prepared to commit any atrocity to demoralise
and weaken the order of our society.
The reality is infinitely more subtle.
If Goldstein himself fell into the
hands of the Thought Police,
he could not give them
a list of his agents.
Such a list does not exist.
They are not an organisation
in the sense we know.
Nothing holds it together but an idea.
There is no possibility of change
in their lifetime.
In the face of the Thought Police
they cannot act collectively.
Individually they cheat, forge, blackmail.
Corrupt children spread
disease and prostitution,
in the name of spreading knowledge
from generation to generation,
until in a thousand years...
You may find this of interest.
Thank you.
(O'BRIEN SWITCHES ON TELESCREEN)
A rally in Victory Square
at 21.30 hours.
That is the end of the announcement.
Goodbye brother.
Goodbye.
They have attacked an unarmed
village with rocket bombs
and murdered 4,000 defenceless,
innocent and peaceful citizens of Oceania.
This is no longer war.
This is cold blooded murder.
Until now, the war has been
conducted with honour and bravery.
With the ideals of truth and justice
in the best traditions of mankind,
until this moment.
Brothers and sisters the endless
catalogue of bestial atrocities
which will ensue from this appalling act
must, can and will be terminated.
The forces of darkness and the
treasonable maggots who collaborate
must, can and will be wiped
from the face of the earth.
We must crush them.
We must smash them.
We must stamp them out!
We the people of Oceania,
and our traditional allies,
the people of Eurasia
will not rest until the final victory
has been achieved.
Death to the eternal enemy of Oceania.
Death!
(CROWD CHEERING)
Brothers and sisters,
one week from now
in this very square.
We shall as a
demonstration of our resolve
and as a sure sign to those who attempt
to threaten our Party and our State.
We shall execute publicly
the same number of Eastasian prisoners
by hanging, drawing and quartering.
(CROWD ROARING)
In accordance with the
principles of Doublethink.
It does not matter if the war is not real or
when it is, that victory is not possible.
The war is not meant to be won.
It is meant to be continuous.
The essential act of modern warfare
is the destruction of the
produce of human labour.
A hierarchical society is only possible
on the basis of poverty and ignorance.
In principle the war effort is planned to
keep society on the brink of starvation.
The war is waged by the ruling
group against its own subjects.
Its object is not victory
over Eurasia or Eastasia,
but to keep the very
structure of society intact.
Julia.
Are you awake?
There is truth and there is untruth.
To be in a minority of one
doesn't make you mad.
Julia my love.
I understand how.
But I don't understand why.
I'm hungry.
Let's make some more coffee.
(NEIGHBOUR SINGS IN BACK GARDEN)
The water's cold.
There's no oil in it.
That's strange. I thought it was full.
NEIGHBOUR SINGING: ♪ They say
that time heals all things ♫
♪ They say you can always forget ♫
♪ But the smiles and the
tears across the years ♫
♪ They twist my heartstrings...
She's beautiful.
She's a metre across the hips, easily.
It's her style of beauty
The future is hers.
We are the dead.
TELESCREEN: You are the dead!
TELESCREEN: Remain exactly where you are!
Make no move until you are ordered.
- Now they can see us.
TELESCREEN: Now we can see you.
TELESCREEN:Clasp your
hands behind your heads.
TELESCREEN: Stand out in the middle
of the room. Stand back to back.
TELESCREEN: Do not
touch one another.
The house is surrounded.
TELESCREEN: The house is surrounded.
I suppose we may as well say goodbye.
TELESCREEN: You may as well say goodbye.
TELESCREEN: While we're on the subject,
here comes a candle to light you to bed.
TELESCREEN: Here comes a
chopper to chop off your head.
(JULIA GASPS)
Pick that up.
The Thought Police.
TELESCREEN: 6079 Smith!
Open your eyes!
(CELL DOOR OPENS)
Parsons?
Keep away from me Smith.
I'm an agent of Goldstein.
I didn't know it myself.
Thought crime is so insidious.
It just creeps up on you.
My daughter found it out.
Very proud of her.
Very grateful I've been discovered
before it's too late.
They won't shoot me will they Smith?
I could be very useful
in a labour camp.
TELESCREEN: Room 101
(CELL DOOR OPENS)
No!
Please! You don't have to take me there.
Why? There's nothing I won't confess.
Nothing.
I've told you everything already.
What is it you want me to know?
Take him instead of me.
He's the thought criminal.
It's him you want.
(CELL DOOR CLOSES)
(CELL DOOR OPENS)
- They got you too?
- They got me a long time ago.
You knew this would happen Winston.
Don't deceive yourself.
You've always known it.
(WINSTON WHIMPERS)
The photos of you and the girl will
be recycled for proletarian use.
(WINSTON WHIMPERS AGAIN)
Do you know where you are Winston?
I... I don't know.
I can guess.
In the Ministry of Love.
Do you know how long you've been here?
No.
Weeks? Months?
Do you know why you're here?
Shall I tell you why we brought
you here? To cure you.
To make you sane.
Yes.
(WINSTON IS BEING STRETCHED)
No! No! No!
That was 40. You can see that
the numbers on this dial run up to 100.
Will you please remember
that I have it in my power
to inflict pain on you at any time,
and in whatever degree I choose?
Yes.
You know perfectly well
what is the matter with you, Winston.
You've known it for years though
you fought against the knowledge.
You are mentally deranged.
You suffer from a defective memory.
You never tried to cure yourself
because you did not choose to.
It was a small effort of will
which you were not ready to make.
For example, which
power is Oceania at war with?
Eastasia.
Oceania is at war with Eastasia.
Eastasia?
Good.
And Oceania has always been at war
with Eastasia, has it not?
Tell me what you think you remember.
I remember
that until only a week
before I was arrested.
We weren't at war with Eastasia at all.
It was Eurasia.
- The last four years I think.
- Another example.
A serious delusion.
Photographs about which
you've had hallucinations,
which you believed
you held in your hand.
They never existed.
Say what you're about to say Winston.
They exist.
In memory.
I remember.
You remember.
I do not remember.
Only the disciplined mind
can see reality Winston.
It needs an act of self destruction,
an effort of the will.
Do you remember writing in your diary.
"Freedom is the freedom to say
two plus two equals four"?
Yes.
How many fingers am I holding up?
Four.
And if the Party says there are not four
but five, then how many?
Five?
(WINSTON SCREAMS IN PAIN)
No.
That's no use. You're lying.
How many fingers please?
Four, what else can I say?
Five, anything you like,
only please stop it.
Stop the pain.
How can I help it?
How can I help what
I see in front of my eyes?
Two and two makes four.
Sometimes, Winston,
sometimes they're five.
Sometimes they're three.
Sometimes they are all of them at once.
Neither the past nor the present nor the
future exists in its own right Winston.
Reality is in the human mind,
not in the individual mind.
Which makes mistakes
and soon perishes,
but in the mind of the Party,
which is collective and immortal.
Again.
No.
(WINSTON'S GROANS IN PAIN AGAIN)
How many fingers Winston?
Four... Four?
I suppose there are four
but I'm trying to see five.
- I wish I could.
- Which do you wish?
To persuade me that you can see
five or really to see them?
Really to see them.
Again.
How many Winston?
I...
I don't know...
I don't know.
Better.
No one escapes Winston.
There are no martyrs here.
All the confessions made here are true.
We do not destroy the heretic
because he resists us.
As long as he resists us
we never destroy him.
We make him one of ourselves
before we kill him.
We make his brain perfect
before we blow it out.
And then, when there is nothing left
but sorrow and love of Big Brother,
we shall lift you clean out of history.
We shall turn you into gas and
pour you into the stratosphere.
Nothing will remain of you.
Not a name in a register,
not a memory in a living brain.
You will be annihilated in the past,
as well as in the future.
3,000
This time it won't hurt you.
Before we bring this session to an end,
I want you to ask me your questions.
I want you to clear your mind.
Julia.
She betrayed you Winston.
Immediately. Unreservedly.
All her rebellion, deceit,
folly, dirty mindedness
has been turned out of her.
Does Big Brother exist?
Of course.
In the same way as me?
You do not exist.
You have not asked me the question
that is uppermost in your mind Winston.
You know what is in Room 101.
Everyone knows what's in Room 101.
Now fix your eyes on mine.
What country is Oceania at war with?
I...
I don't remember.
Oceania is at war with East Eastasia.
Do you remember that now?
Yes.
How many fingers am I holding up?
Five.
You see at least that it is possible.
You've understood the reality of the
past and the present Winston.
Now what of the future?
Question.
How does one man
assert power over another?
- By making him suffer.
- Exactly.
Obedience is not enough.
Power is inflicting pain and humiliation
otherwise you cannot be sure.
Power is tearing human minds apart
and putting them together again
in new shapes of your own choosing.
Power is not a means, it is an end.
In our world there will only be triumph
and self-abasement.
Everything else we shall destroy.
The past is forbidden.
Why.
Because when we can cut
man from his own past,
then we can cut him from his family.
His children, other men.
There is no loyalty
except loyalty to the Party.
There is no love except
love of Big Brother.
All competing pleasures, we will destroy.
If you want a vision of the future imagine
a boot stamping on a human face forever.
Winston...
You are thinking that
my face is old and tired.
That while I talk of power I am unable
to prevent the decay of my own body.
But the individual is only a cell Winston.
The weariness of the cell is
the vigour of the organism.
You'll fail.
Why?
It's impossible.
Hatred and fear have no life.
Why is hate less vital than love?
I don't know but somehow you'll fail.
Something will defeat you.
- Life will defeat you.
- We control life at all levels.
We create human nature.
Men are infinitely malleable.
Or perhaps you will return to your old idea
that the proletarians will arise.
Put it out of your mind.
They are helpless animals.
Humanity is the party.
I don't care, in the end they'll beat you.
Sooner or later they'll
tear you to pieces.
On what evidence?
Goldstein's book.
I wrote it, or at least
I collaborated in writing it.
No book is individually
produced as you know.
I just believe it.
I know you'll fail.
There's something in this world, some
spirit that you will never overcome.
What is it, this principle?
I don't know.
The spirit of man.
Do you consider yourself a man?
Yes.
If you're a man, you're the last man.
Your kind is extinct.
We are the inheritors.
Do you understand that you're alone?
You're outside history.
You unexist.
Get up.
Come here.
Look at you, you're rotting away.
That is the last man.
If you're human, that is humanity.
It won't last forever.
You can escape from it
whenever you choose.
Everything depends on you.
You did it.
You reduced me to this.
No Winston you reduced yourself to it.
When will you shoot me?
It might take a long time.
But don't give up hope.
Everyone is cured sooner or later,
and in the end
we shall shoot you.
The law of gravity is nonsense.
No such law exists.
If I think I float and you think
I float then it happens.
I love you.
You have the strength Winston.
You have the whole party.
You are the Party.
You're one of us.
One of the chosen.
I love you.
I love you too.
(GUNSHOT)
Julia.
Julia my love.
Julia!
TELESCREEN: Get up
TELESCREEN: Stand up straighter.
TELESCREEN: Look me in the face.
Tell me Winston and remember no lies.
What are your true feelings
towards Big Brother?
I hate him.
You must love him.
It's not enough to obey him.
Room 101.
You asked me once Winston
what was in Room 101?
I told you that you knew already.
Everyone knows.
The thing that is in Room 101,
is the worst thing in the world.
It goes beyond fear of pain or death.
It is unendurable and it varies
from individual to individual.
It may be burial alive or castration.
Or many other things.
In your case,
it's rats
No!
(RATS SQUEALING)
- Please, what do you want me to do?
- You will do what is required of you.
What, what?
What.
How can I do it if I
don't know what it is?
In the proletarian areas
they will attack a baby
and within five minutes
strip it to the bone.
They also attack the sick and dying.
They show astonishing intelligence in
knowing when a human being is helpless.
(RATS SQUEAL AGAIN)
Please!
The mask fits over your
head leaving no exit.
I press the first lever and the rats
move into the front compartment.
I press the second and the
door of the cage will slide up.
These starving brutes
will shoot at you like bullets.
Have you ever seen a rat
leap through the air?
(RATS SQUEAL)
They will leap onto your face
and bore straight into it.
Sometimes they attack the eyes first.
Sometimes they burrow through
the cheeks and devour the tongue.
(WINSTON WHIMPERS)
Help, help me!
What do you want?
Help me.
No! No!
(RATS SQUEAL)
I love you.
Do it to her, do it to Julia.
I don't care what you do to her. Tear
her face off! do it to Julia not to me.
Do it to Julia!
Not me!
A vast military build up has
been reported in the Sahara desert.
Sectors 17 and 18 of the war zone.
That is the end of the announcement.
Brother.
On the house.
Thank you for coming.
You are warned to stand by for
an important announcement at 15.30
This is news of the gravest national
consequence concerning the war with Eurasia.
15.30
I'm very worried about the African front.
The news is disquieting in the extreme.
I've been worrying about it all day.
It's not just a question of losing Africa.
For the first time the territory of Oceania
itself is threatened by invasion.
It's inconceivable.
It must have been possible
to outflank them in some way.
I have an instinct.
There's bad news on the way.
I told them all about you.
I'm only thankful they got
me before it was too late.
Yes I told them about you too.
Thought crime.
Sex crime, all your treachery.
I have a meeting to go to.
We must meet again.
Yes.
I accuse myself of the following crimes.
I have seduced Party
members of both sexes.
I've been to the proletarian areas.
I deliberately contracted syphilis
in order to spread the disease
to my wife and other Party members.
Together with other agents,
I have counterfeited banknotes.
Wrecked industrial machinery,
polluted the water supply
and guided Eurasian rocket bombs
to targets on Airstrip One
by means of coded radio signals.
I stand here a victim of the
influence of Emmanuel Goldstein.
Guilty on all counts.
I'm glad I was caught.
I was mentally deranged.
Now I am cured.
I ask only for you to accept
my love of our leader.
I ask only to be shot while
my mind is still clean.
(MUSICAL INTRO ON TELESCREEN)
A glorious victory.
A vast strategic manoeuvre to outflank
the Eurasian forces on the African front
has been successful.
Perfectly coordinated, it has resulted
in the utter rout of the Eurasian army.
There have been nearly
a million prisoners.
It has been an utter rout, a complete...
Waiter!
This immense victory brings the war
within measurable distance of its end.
Wonderful news.
I love you.
(THE END)
Download 1984 completely free at
https://yts.mx
Use a VPN if necessary!
Advertise your product or brand here
contact www.OpenSubtitles.org today